<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="tei-analysis.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="chs-gp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Saint Chad Gospels</title>
                <editor xml:id="bh">Bonnie Lewis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>A new transcription from digital imagery, with semantic markup, based on
                    digital images captured by the University of Kentucky’s Center for Visualization
                    and Virtual Environments, Brent Seales, Director. The images are copyrighted by
                    the Chapter of Lichfield Cathedral, 2010, and are released under a Creative
                    Commons License. This material is based upon work supported by the National
                    Science Foundation under Grants No. 0916148 &amp; No. 0916421. Any opinions,
                    findings and conclusions or recomendations expressed in this material are those
                    of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National
                    Science Foundation (NSF).</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name>Bonnie Lewis, Tony Brown, Christopher Blackwell, Brent Seales edd.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>under 1Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> The Center for Hellenic Studies of Harvard University </publisher>
                <authority>
                    <name>Casey Dué and Mary Ebbott, edd.</name>
                </authority>
                <availability>
                    <p> ©2012, Bonnie Lewis. This work is made available under the Creative Commons
                        Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States License:
                        http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/ </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p> File created electronically. </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="xgrc">Transliterated Greek</language>
                <language ident="deu">German</language>
                <language ident="fra">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>The beginning of the good news about Jesus the Messiah, the Son of God <pb
                            n="72r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>as it is written in Isaiah the prophet: <lb n="1"/> I will send my messenger
                        ahead of you who will prepare <lb n="2"/> your way</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>a voice of one calling in the wilderness <lb n="3"/> Prepare the way for the
                        Lord, make straight paths for him <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>And so John the Baptist appeared in the wilderness preaching <lb n="5"/> a
                        baptism of repentance for the forgiveness <lb n="6"/> of sins</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>The whole Judean countryside and <lb n="7"/> all the people of Jerusalem went
                        out to him. Confessing their sins, they were baptized <lb n="8"/> by him in
                        the Jordan River <lb n="9"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>John wore clothing <lb n="10"/> made of camel's hair, with a leather belt
                        around his waist <lb n="11"/>, and he ate locusts and wild honey. <lb n="12"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>And this was his message: “After me <lb n="13"/> comes the one more powerful
                        than I, <lb n="14"/> the straps of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop
                        down and untie.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>I baptize <lb n="15"/> you with water, but he will baptize you with the Holy
                        Spirit.” <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time Jesus came from Nazareth <lb n="17"/> in Galilee and was
                        baptized by John in the Jordan. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Just as Jesus was coming up out of the water, he saw heaven being torn <lb
                            n="19"/> open and the Spirit descending <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="72v"/> on him like a dove.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>And a voice came <lb n="1"/> from heaven: “You are my Son, whom I love <lb
                            n="2"/> with you I am well pleased.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>At once the Spirit sent him out into the wilderness, <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>and he was in the wilderness forty days <lb n="4"/>, being tempted by Satan.
                            <lb n="5"/> He was with the wild animals, and angels attended <lb n="6"
                        /> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>After John was put in prison, <lb n="7"/> Jesus went into Galilee,
                        proclaiming <lb n="8"/> the good news of God.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“The time has come,” <lb n="9"/> he said. “The kingdom of God has come near.
                            <lb n="10"/> Repent and believe the good news!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus walked beside <lb n="11"/> the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and his
                        brother Andrew <lb n="12"/> casting a net into the lake, for they were <lb
                            n="13"/> fishermen.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“Come, follow me,” Jesus said, <lb n="14"/> “and I will send you out to fish
                        for people.” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>At once they left their nets and followed him. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>When he had gone a little farther, he saw James son of <lb n="17"/> Zebedee
                        and his brother John <lb n="18"/> in a boat, preparing their nets.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Without delay he called <lb n="19"/> them, and they left their father Zebedee
                        in the boat <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="73r"/> with the hired men and followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>They went to <lb n="1"/> Capernaum, and when the Sabbath came, Jesus went
                        into the synagogue <lb n="2"/> and began to teach.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>The people were amazed at his teaching <lb n="3"/>, because he taught them as
                        one who had authority, <lb n="4"/> not as the teachers of the law.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Just then a man in their synagogue <lb n="5"/> who was possessed by an impure
                        spirit cried out, <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you want with us, Jesus of Nazareth? <lb n="7"/> Have you come to
                        destroy us? I know who you are-the Holy One of God!” <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“Be quiet!” said Jesus sternly. “Come out of him!” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The impure spirit shook the man violently <lb n="10"/> and came out of him
                        with a shriek.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>The people <lb n="11"/> were all so amazed that they asked <lb n="12"/> each
                        other, “What is this? A new teaching <lb n="13"/>-and with authority! He
                        even gives orders to impure spirits <lb n="14"/> and they obey him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>News about <lb n="15"/> him spread quickly over the whole region of Galilee.
                            <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>As soon as they left the synagogue, they went <lb n="17"/> with James and
                        John to the home of Simon <lb n="18"/> and Andrew.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Simon's mother-in-law <lb n="19"/> was in bed with a fever, and they
                        immediately told Jesus about her. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="73v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>So he went to her, took her hand <lb n="1"/> and helped her up. The fever
                        left her and she began to wait on <lb n="2"/> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>That evening after sunset <lb n="3"/> the people brought to Jesus all the
                        sick <lb n="4"/> and demon-possessed. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>The whole town gathered at the door, <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>and Jesus healed many who had various diseases.<lb n="7"/> He also drove out
                        many demons, but <lb n="8"/> he would not let the demons speak because they
                        knew who he was. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Very early in the morning, while it was still dark, Jesus got up, left the
                        house and went off <lb n="10"/> to a solitary place, where he prayed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Simon and <lb n="11"/> his companions went to look for him,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>and <lb n="12"/> when they found him, they exclaimed: <lb n="13"/> “Everyone
                        is looking for you!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “Let us go somewhere else-<lb n="14"/> to the nearby
                        villages-so I can preach there also. <lb n="15"/> That is why I have
                        come.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>So he traveled throughout Galilee, preaching in their synagogues <lb n="16"/>
                        and driving out demons. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>A man with leprosy came <lb n="18"/> to him and begged him on his knees, “If
                        you are willing, you can make me clean.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus was indignant. He reached out his hand <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="74r"/> and touched the man. “I am willing,” he said. “Be clean!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately <lb n="1"/> the leprosy left him and he was cleansed <lb n="2"
                        />.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus sent him away at once with a strong warning:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="3"/> “See that you don't tell this to anyone. But go, show <lb n="4"/>
                        yourself to the priest and offer the sacrifices <lb n="5"/> that Moses
                        commanded for your cleansing, as a testimony to <lb n="6"/> them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>Instead he went out and began to talk freely, spreading <lb n="7"/> the news.
                        As a result, Jesus could no longer <lb n="8"/> enter a town openly but
                        stayed outside in lonely places. <lb n="9"/> Yet the people still came to
                        him from everywhere. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>A few days later, when Jesus again entered Capernaum, <hi rend="italics"> the
                            people heard that he had come home.</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not found in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>They gathered <lb n="11"/> in such large numbers that there was no room left
                            <lb n="12"/> not even outside the door, <lb n="13"/> and he preached the
                        word to them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Some men came, <lb n="14"/> bringing to him a paralyzed man, <lb n="15"/>
                        carried by four of them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Since they could not <lb n="16"/> get him to Jesus because of the crowd, <lb
                            n="17"/> they made an opening in the roof above Jesus by digging through
                        it <lb n="18"/> and then lowered the mat the man was lying on.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus saw their faith <lb n="19"/>, he said to the paralyzed man, “Son,
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="74v"/> your sins are forgiven.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Now some <lb n="1"/> teachers of the law were sitting there, thinking to <lb
                            n="2"/> themselves,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why does this fellow talk like that? He's blaspheming! <lb n="3"/> Who can
                        forgive sins but God alone?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately <lb n="4"/> Jesus knew in his spirit that this was what they were
                        thinking in their hearts, <lb n="5"/> and he said to them, “Why are you
                        thinking these <lb n="6"/> things?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Which is easier: to say to this paralyzed man, <lb n="7"/> 'Your sins are
                        forgiven,' or to say, <lb n="8"/> 'Get up, take your mat and walk'? <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>But I want you to know that the Son <lb n="10"/> of Man has authority on
                        earth to forgive sins.” So he said to the <lb n="11"/> man,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>“I tell you, get up, take your <lb n="12"/> mat and go home.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>He got up, took his mat <lb n="13"/> and walked out in full view of them all
                            <lb n="14"/>. This amazed everyone and they praised God, saying <lb
                            n="15"/>, “We have never seen anything like this!” <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Once again Jesus went out beside the lake. A large crowd <lb n="17"/> came to
                        him, and he began to teach them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>As he walked along <lb n="18"/>, he saw Levi son of Alphaeus sitting at the
                        tax collector's <lb n="19"/> booth. “Follow me,” Jesus told him, and Levi
                        got up and followed him <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="75r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>While Jesus was having dinner at Levi's house <lb n="1"/>, many tax
                        collectors and sinners were eating <lb n="2"/> with him and his disciples,
                        for there were <lb n="3"/> many who followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>When the teachers of the law who were Pharisees <lb n="4"/> saw him eating
                        with the sinners <lb n="5"/> and tax collectors, they asked his disciples:
                            <lb n="6"/> “Why does he eat with tax collectors <lb n="7"/> and
                        sinners?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>On hearing this, Jesus <lb n="8"/> said to them, “It is not the healthy who
                        need a doctor, but the sick. <lb n="9"/> I have not come to call the
                        righteous, but sinners.” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Now John's disciples and the Pharisees <lb n="11"/> were fasting. Some people
                        came and asked Jesus, “How is it that <lb n="12"/> John's disciples and the
                        disciples of the Pharisees are fasting, <lb n="13"/> but yours are not?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered, <lb n="14"/> “How can the guests of the bridegroom fast <lb
                            n="15"/> while he is with them? They cannot, <lb n="16"/> so long as
                        they have him with them. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>But the time will come when the bridegroom will be taken <lb n="18"/> from
                        them, and on that day they <lb n="19"/> will fast.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“No one sews a patch <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="76v"/> of unshrunk cloth on an old garment. Otherwise, <lb n="1"/>
                        the new piece will pull away from the old, making the <lb n="2"/> tear
                        worse.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>And no one pours new wine into <lb n="3"/> old wineskins. Otherwise, the wine
                        will burst the skins, <lb n="4"/> and both the wine and the wineskins will
                        be ruined. No, <lb n="5"/> they pour new wine into new wineskins.” <lb n="6"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>One Sabbath Jesus was going through <lb n="7"/> the grainfields, and as his
                        disciples walked along, they began <lb n="8"/> to pick some heads of
                        grain.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>The Pharisees <lb n="9"/> said to him, “Look, why are they doing what is <lb
                            n="10"/> unlawful on the Sabbath?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, “Have you never <lb n="11"/> read what David did when he and his
                        companions <lb n="12"/> were hungry and in need? <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>In the days of Abiathar the high priest, he entered the house of God <lb
                            n="14"/> and ate the consecrated bread, <lb n="15"/> which is lawful <lb
                            n="16"/> only for priests to eat. And he also gave some <lb n="17"/> to
                        his companions.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he said to them, “The Sabbath <lb n="18"/> was made for man, not man <lb
                            n="19"/> for the Sabbath.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>So the Son of Man is Lord <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="77r"/> even of the Sabbath.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Another time Jesus went <lb n="1"/> into the synagogue, and a man with a
                        shriveled hand <lb n="2"/> was there.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Some of them were looking for a reason to accuse Jesus, <lb n="3"/> so they
                        watched him closely to see if he would heal him on the Sabbath.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to the man with the shriveled <lb n="4"/> hand, “Stand up in front
                        of everyone.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus asked <lb n="5"/> them, “Which is lawful on the Sabbath: to do
                        good or to do evil, <lb n="6"/> to save life or to kill?” But they remained
                        silent. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>He looked around at them in anger and, deeply distressed at their <lb n="8"/>
                        stubborn hearts, said to the man, “Stretch out <lb n="9"/> your hand.” He
                        stretched it out, and <lb n="10"/> his hand was completely restored.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the Pharisees <lb n="11"/> went out and began to plot with the Herodians
                            <lb n="12"/> how they might kill Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus withdrew with his disciples <lb n="13"/> to the lake, and a large crowd
                        from Galilee <lb n="14"/> followed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>When they heard <lb n="15"/> about all he was doing, many people came to him
                        from Judea, <lb n="16"/> Jerusalem, Idumea, and the regions across the
                        Jordan and <lb n="17"/> around Tyre and Sidon.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Because of the crowd he told his disciples <lb n="18"/> to have a small boat
                        ready for him, to <lb n="19"/> keep the people from crowding him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>For he had healed many <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="76v"/>, so that those with diseases were pushing <lb n="1"/> forward
                        to touch him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Whenever the impure spirits <lb n="2"/> saw him, they fell down before him
                        and <lb n="3"/> cried out, “You are the Son of God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>But he gave them strict <lb n="4"/> orders not to tell others about him. <lb
                            n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus went up on a mountainside and called to him <lb n="6"/> those he
                        wanted, and they came to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>He appointed <lb n="7"/> twelve that they might be with him and that he might
                        send them <lb n="8"/> out to preach</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>and to have authority <lb n="9"/> to drive out demons. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>These are the twelve he appointed <lb n="11"/>: Simon (to whom he gave the
                        name Peter), <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>James son of Zebedee and his brother John <lb n="13"/> (to them he gave the
                        name Boanerges, which <lb n="14"/> means “sons of thunder”),</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Andrew, Philip, <lb n="15"/> Bartholomew, Matthew, Thomas, James <lb n="16"/>
                        son of Alphaeus, Thaddaeus, Simon the Zealot <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed him. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus entered a house, and again a crowd gathered, <lb n="19"/> so that
                        he and his disciples were not even able to eat.<lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="77r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>When his family heard about this, they went to take charge of him <lb n="1"
                        />, for they said, “He is out of his mind.” <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>And the teachers of the law who came down from Jerusalem <lb n="3"/> said,
                        “He is possessed by Beelzebul! By the prince <lb n="4"/> of demons he is
                        driving out demons.” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>So Jesus called them over to him and began to speak to them in parables: <lb
                            n="6"/> “How can Satan drive out Satan?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>If a kingdom is divided against <lb n="7"/> itself, that kingdom cannot
                        stand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>If a house <lb n="8"/> is divided against itself, that <lb n="9"/> house
                        cannot stand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>And if Satan opposes <lb n="10"/> himself and is divided, he cannot stand;
                            <lb n="11"/> his end has come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>In fact, no one can enter a strong <lb n="12"/> man's house without first
                        tying him up. <lb n="13"/> Then he can plunder the strong man's house. <lb
                            n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, people can be forgiven <lb n="15"/> all their sins and
                        every slander they <lb n="16"/> utter,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>but whoever blasphemes against the <lb n="17"/> Holy Spirit will never be
                        forgiven; <lb n="18"/> they are guilty of an eternal sin.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>He said this because they were saying, <lb n="19"/> “He has an impure
                        spirit.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus' mother and brothers arrived <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="77v"/>. Standing outside, they sent someone <lb n="1"/> in to call
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>A crowd was sitting around him <lb n="2"/>, and they told him, “Your mother
                        and brothers <lb n="3"/> are outside looking for you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="4"/> “Who are my mother and my brothers?” he asked. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he looked at those seated in a circle around him <lb n="6"/> and said,
                        “Here are my mother and my brothers!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever <lb n="7"/> does God's will is my brother and <lb n="8"/> sister and
                        mother.” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Again Jesus began to teach by the lake. The crowd <lb n="10"/> that gathered
                        around him was so large that he got into a boat and sat in it out on the <lb
                            n="11"/> lake, while all the people were along the shore at the water's
                            <lb n="12"/> edge.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>He taught them many things by parables, and <lb n="13"/> in his teaching
                        said:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>“Listen! A farmer <lb n="14"/> went out to sow his seed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>As he was scattering <lb n="15"/> the seed, some fell along the path, and <lb
                            n="16"/> the birds came and ate it up.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Some fell <lb n="17"/> on rocky places, where it did not have much soil. <lb
                            n="18"/> It sprang up quickly, because <lb n="19"/> the soil was
                        shallow.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>But when <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="78r"/> the sun came up, the plants were scorched, and they withered
                        because <lb n="1"/> they had no root.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Other seed fell among thorns, which <lb n="2"/> grew up and choked the
                        plants, so that <lb n="3"/> they did not bear grain.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Still other seed fell on good soil. <lb n="4"/> It came up, grew and produced
                        a crop <lb n="5"/>, some multiplying thirty, some sixty, some <lb n="6"/> a
                        hundred times.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said, “Whoever has ears to hear, let <lb n="7"/> them hear.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>When he was alone, <lb n="8"/> the Twelve and the others around him asked him
                        about the <lb n="9"/> parables.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>He told them, “The secret <lb n="10"/> of the kingdom of God has been given
                        to you. But to those on the outside <lb n="11"/> everything is said in
                        parables</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>so that,”'they may be ever seeing <lb n="12"/> but never perceiving, and ever
                        hearing but <lb n="13"/> never understanding; otherwise they might turn and
                        be <lb n="14"/> forgiven!'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said to them, “Don't you understand this parable <lb n="15"/>? How
                        then will you understand any parable? <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>The farmer sows the word.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Some <lb n="17"/> people are like seed along the path, where the word <lb
                            n="18"/> is sown. As soon as they hear it, Satan comes and takes away
                            <lb n="19"/> the word that was sown in them. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="78v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Others, like seed sown on rocky places, <lb n="1"/> hear the word and at once
                        receive it with joy <lb n="2"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>But since they have no root, <lb n="3"/> they last only a short time. When
                        trouble <lb n="4"/> or persecution comes because of the word, <lb n="5"/>
                        they quickly fall away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Still others, like seed sown among thorns <lb n="6"/>, hear the word;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>but the worries <lb n="7"/> of this life, the deceitfulness of wealth and the
                        desires for other things come in <lb n="8"/> and choke the word, <lb n="9"/>
                        making it unfruitful.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Others, like seed sown on <lb n="10"/> good soil, hear the word, <lb n="11"/>
                        accept it, and produce a crop-some thirty <lb n="12"/>, some sixty, some a
                        hundred times what was sown.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, “Do <lb n="13"/> you bring in a lamp to put it <lb n="14"/>
                        under a bowl or a bed? Instead, don't you put it on its stand? <lb n="15"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>For whatever is hidden is meant to be disclosed, <lb n="16"/> and whatever is
                        concealed is meant to be brought out <lb n="17"/> into the open.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone has ears to hear, let them hear.” <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“Consider carefully what you hear,” he continued. <lb n="19"/> “With the
                        measure you use, it will be measured to <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="79r"/> you-and even more.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever has will be given <lb n="1"/> more; whoever does not have, even what
                        they have will be taken <lb n="2"/> from them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>He also said, “This is what the kingdom of God is like <lb n="3"/>. A man
                        scatters seed on the ground. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Night and day, whether he sleeps or gets up, the seed <lb n="5"/> sprouts and
                        grows, though he does not know how.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>All by itself <lb n="6"/> the soil produces grain-first the stalk, then the
                        head <lb n="7"/>, then the full kernel in the head.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>As soon <lb n="8"/> as the grain is ripe, he puts the sickle to it, because
                        the <lb n="9"/> harvest has come.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Again he said, “What shall we say the <lb n="10"/> kingdom of God is like, or
                        what parable shall we use to describe it? <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>It is like a mustard seed, which is the <lb n="12"/> smallest of all seeds on
                        earth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Yet when planted, <lb n="13"/> it grows and becomes the largest of all garden
                        plants, <lb n="14"/> with such big branches that the <lb n="15"/> birds can
                        perch in its shade.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>With many similar parables <lb n="16"/> Jesus spoke the word to them, as much
                        as they could <lb n="17"/> understand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>He did not say anything to them without using a parable <lb n="18"/>. But
                        when he was alone with his own disciples, he explained <lb n="19"/>
                        everything.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>That day when evening came, he said to his disciples, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="79v"/> Let us go over to the other side.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Leaving the crowd behind <lb n="1"/>, they took him along, just as he was, in
                        the boat. There were also other <lb n="2"/> boats with him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>A furious squall came up, <lb n="3"/> and the waves broke over the boat, so
                        that it was <lb n="4"/> nearly swamped.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus was in the stern, <lb n="5"/> sleeping on a cushion. The disciples woke
                        him and said to him, <lb n="6"/> “Teacher, don't you care if we drown?” <lb
                            n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>He got up, rebuked the wind and said to the waves, <lb n="8"/> “Quiet! Be
                        still!” Then the wind died down and it was <lb n="9"/> completely calm.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to his disciples, “Why are you so afraid? <lb n="10"/> Do you still
                        have no faith?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>They were terrified <lb n="11"/> and asked each other, “Who is this? <lb
                            n="12"/> Even the wind and the waves obey him!” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>They went across the lake to the region of the Gerasenes <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus got out of the boat <lb n="15"/> a man with an impure spirit came
                        from the tombs to meet him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>This <lb n="16"/> man lived in the tombs, and no one <lb n="17"/> could bind
                        him anymore, not even with a chain. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>For he had often been chained hand and foot, but he tore the chains <lb
                            n="19"/> apart and broke the irons on his feet. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="80r"/> No one was strong enough to subdue him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="1"/> Night and day among the tombs and in the hills <lb n="2"/> he
                        would cry out and cut himself with stones. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>When he saw Jesus from a distance, he ran and fell on his knees in front <lb
                            n="4"/> of him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>He shouted at the top of his voice, “What do you want with me <lb n="5"/>,
                        Jesus, Son of the Most High God? In God's name don't <lb n="6"/> torture
                        me!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>For Jesus had said to him, “Come out of this man, you impure <lb n="7"/>
                        spirit!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus asked him, <lb n="8"/> “What is your name?” “My name is Legion,”
                        he replied, <lb n="9"/> “for we are many.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>And he begged Jesus again and again <lb n="10"/> not to send them out of the
                        area.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>A large herd <lb n="11"/> of pigs was feeding on the nearby hillside. <lb
                            n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>The demons begged Jesus, “Send us among the <lb n="13"/> pigs; allow us to go
                        into them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>He gave them <lb n="14"/> permission, and the impure spirits came out and
                        went <lb n="15"/> into the pigs. The herd, about two thousand in number, <lb
                            n="16"/> rushed down the steep bank into the lake and were drowned. <lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Those tending the pigs ran off and reported this <lb n="18"/> in the town and
                        countryside, and the people went out to see what <lb n="19"/> had
                        happened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>When they came to Jesus, they saw the man <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="80v"/> who had been possessed by the legion of demons, sitting there,
                        dressed <lb n="1"/> and in his right mind; and they were afraid.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Those who had seen <lb n="2"/> it told the people what had happened to the
                            <lb n="3"/> demon-possessed man-and told about the pigs as well.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the <lb n="4"/> people began to plead with Jesus to leave their region.
                            <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus was getting into the boat, the man <lb n="6"/> who had been
                        demon-possessed begged to go <lb n="7"/> with him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus did not let him, but said, <lb n="8"/> “Go home to your own people and
                        tell them <lb n="9"/> how much the Lord has done for you, and how he has had
                        mercy on you.” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>So the man went away and began to tell in the Decapolis how much <lb n="11"/>
                        Jesus had done for him. And all the people were amazed. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus had again crossed over by boat to the other side <lb n="13"/> of
                        the lake, a large crowd gathered around him while he was <lb n="14"/> by the
                        lake.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Then one of the synagogue leaders <lb n="15"/>, named Jairus, came, and when
                        he saw Jesus, he fell at <lb n="16"/> his feet.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>He pleaded earnestly with him, <lb n="17"/> “My little daughter is dying.
                        Please come and put your <lb n="18"/> hands on her so that she will be
                        healed and live.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>So Jesus went with him. A large crowd followed <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="81r"/> and pressed around him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>And a woman was there <lb n="1"/> who had been subject to bleeding for twelve
                        years.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>She had <lb n="2"/> suffered a great deal under the care of many doctors <lb
                            n="3"/> and had spent all she had, yet instead of getting better <lb
                            n="4"/> she grew worse.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>When she heard <lb n="5"/> about Jesus, she came up behind him in the crowd
                        and touched <lb n="6"/> his cloak,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>because she thought, “If <lb n="7"/> I just touch his clothes, I will be
                        healed.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately <lb n="8"/> her bleeding stopped and she felt <lb n="9"/> in her
                        body that she was freed from her suffering.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>At once <lb n="10"/> Jesus realized that power had gone out from him. <lb
                            n="11"/> He turned around in the crowd and asked, <lb n="12"/> “Who
                        touched my clothes?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>“You see the people <lb n="13"/> crowding against you,” his disciples
                        answered, “and yet you can ask, '<lb n="14"/> Who touched me?' “</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus kept looking around to see <lb n="15"/> who had done it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the woman, <lb n="16"/> knowing what had happened to her, came and <lb
                            n="17"/> fell at his feet and, trembling with fear, told him the whole
                        truth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>He <lb n="18"/> said to her, “Daughter, your faith has healed you. <lb n="19"
                        /> Go in peace and be freed from your suffering.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>While <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="81v"/> Jesus was still speaking, some people came from the house of
                        Jairus, the synagogue leader. <lb n="1"/> “Your daughter is dead,” they
                        said. “Why bother the <lb n="2"/> teacher anymore?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Overhearing what they said <lb n="3"/>, Jesus told him, “Don't be afraid;
                        just <lb n="4"/> believe.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>He did not let anyone follow him <lb n="5"/> except Peter, James and John the
                        brother of <lb n="6"/> James.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>When they came to the home of the synagogue leader, Jesus saw a <lb n="7"/>
                        commotion, with people crying and wailing loudly. <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>He went in and said to them, “Why all this commotion and wailing? The child
                            <lb n="9"/> is not dead but asleep.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>But they laughed <lb n="10"/> at him. After he put them all out, he took the
                        child's father <lb n="11"/> and mother and the disciples who were with him,
                        and went in <lb n="12"/> where the child was.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>He took her by the hand <lb n="13"/> and said to her, “Talitha koum!” (which
                        means “Little girl, I say to you, <lb n="14"/> get up!”).</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately the girl stood up and began to walk <lb n="15"/> around (she was
                        twelve years old). At this they were <lb n="16"/> completely astonished.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>He gave strict orders <lb n="17"/> not to let anyone know about this, and
                        told them to give her something to eat. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus left there and went to his hometown, accompanied by <lb n="19"/> his
                        disciples.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>When the Sabbath came <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="82r"/>, he began to teach in the synagogue, and many who heard him
                            <lb n="1"/> were amazed. “Where did this man get these things?” they
                        asked. <lb n="2"/> “What's this wisdom that has been given him? What <lb
                            n="3"/> are these remarkable miracles he is performing? <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Isn't this the carpenter? Isn't this Mary's <lb n="5"/> son and the brother
                        of James, Joseph, Judas and Simon? <lb n="6"/> Aren't his sisters here with
                        us?” And they took offense <lb n="7"/> at him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not <lb n="8"/> without honor except in his
                        own town, among his <lb n="9"/> relatives and in his own home.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>He could not <lb n="10"/> do any miracles there, except lay his hands on a
                        few <lb n="11"/> sick people and heal them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="12"/> He was amazed at their lack of faith. Then Jesus went <lb n="13"
                        /> around teaching from village to village. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Calling the Twelve to him, he began to send them out two by two <lb n="15"/>
                        and gave them authority over impure spirits.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>These were <lb n="16"/> his instructions: “Take nothing for the journey
                        except a staff- <lb n="17"/> no bread, no bag, no money in your belts. <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Wear sandals but not an extra <lb n="19"/> shirt.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Whenever you enter a <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="82v"/> house, stay there until you leave that town. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>And if any place will not welcome you <lb n="2"/> or listen to you, leave
                        that place and shake the <lb n="3"/> dust off your feet as a testimony
                        against them.” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>They went out and preached that people should repent. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>They drove out many demons and anointed <lb n="6"/> many sick people with oil
                        and healed them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>King Herod heard <lb n="7"/> about this, for Jesus' name had become well
                        known <lb n="8"/>. Some were saying, “John the Baptist has been raised from
                            <lb n="9"/> the dead, and that is why miraculous powers are at work in
                        him.” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Others said, “He is Elijah.” And still others <lb n="11"/> claimed, “He is a
                        prophet, like one of the prophets of long ago.” <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>But when Herod heard this, he said, “John, <lb n="13"/> whom I beheaded, has
                        been raised from the dead!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>For Herod <lb n="14"/> himself had given orders to have John arrested, and he
                        had him bound <lb n="15"/> and put in prison. He did this because of
                        Herodias, his brother Philip's <lb n="16"/> wife, whom he had married. <lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>For John had been saying to Herod, “It is not lawful for you <lb n="18"/> to
                        have your brother's wife.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>So Herodias <lb n="19"/> nursed a grudge against John and wanted to kill him.
                        But she was not <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="83r"/> able to,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>because Herod feared John <lb n="1"/> and protected him, knowing him to be a
                        righteous and holy man. When Herod <lb n="2"/> heard John, he was greatly
                        puzzled; yet he liked to <lb n="3"/> listen to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Finally the opportune time came. On his birthday <lb n="4"/> Herod gave a
                        banquet for his high officials and military commanders <lb n="5"/> and the
                        leading men of Galilee.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>When the daughter <lb n="6"/> of Herodias came in and danced, she pleased <lb
                            n="7"/> Herod and his dinner guests. The king said to the girl, <lb
                            n="8"/> “Ask me for anything you want, and I'll give it to you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>And he promised <lb n="9"/> her with an oath, “Whatever you ask I will give
                            <lb n="10"/> you, up to half my kingdom.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>She went out <lb n="11"/> and said to her mother, “What shall I ask for?”
                        “The head of <lb n="12"/> John the Baptist,” she answered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>At once the girl hurried in <lb n="13"/> to the king with the request: “I
                        want you <lb n="14"/> to give me right now the head of John the Baptist on a
                        platter.” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The king was greatly distressed, but because of his oaths and <lb n="16"/>
                        his dinner guests, he did not want to refuse <lb n="17"/> her.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>So he immediately sent an executioner with orders to bring John's <lb n="18"
                        /> head. The man went, beheaded John in the prison,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>and brought back his <lb n="19"/> head on a platter. He presented <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="83v"/> it to the girl, and she gave it to her mother. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>On hearing of this, John's disciples came and took <lb n="2"/> his body and
                        laid it in a tomb. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>The apostles gathered around Jesus <lb n="4"/> and reported to him all they
                        had done and taught. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Then, because so many people were coming and <lb n="6"/> going that they did
                        not even have a chance to eat, he said to them <lb n="7"/>, “Come with me by
                        yourselves to a quiet place and get <lb n="8"/> some rest.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>So they went away by themselves in a boat <lb n="9"/> to a solitary
                        place.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>But many who saw <lb n="10"/> them leaving recognized them and ran on foot
                            <lb n="11"/> from all the towns and got there ahead of <lb n="12"/>
                        them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus landed and saw a large crowd, he <lb n="13"/> had compassion on
                        them, because they were like sheep without a <lb n="14"/> shepherd. So he
                        began teaching them many things.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>By this <lb n="15"/> time it was late in the day, so his disciples came to
                        him. <lb n="16"/> “This is a remote place,” they said, “and it's already
                        very <lb n="17"/> late.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Send the people away so that they can go to the surrounding <lb n="18"/>
                        countryside and villages and buy themselves something to eat.” <lb n="19"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>But he answered, “You give them something <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="84r"/> to eat.” <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>“How many <lb n="2"/> loaves do you have?” <lb n="3"/> he asked. “Go and
                        see.” When they found out, they said, <lb n="4"/> “Five-and two fish.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus directed them <lb n="5"/> to have all the people sit down in
                        groups <lb n="6"/> on the green grass.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>So they sat down <lb n="7"/> in groups of hundreds and <lb n="8"/>
                        fifties.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Taking the five loaves and the <lb n="9"/> two fish and looking up to heaven,
                        he gave thanks <lb n="10"/> and broke the loaves. Then he gave them to his
                        disciples to distribute to <lb n="11"/> the people. He also divided the two
                        fish among them all.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>They all ate <lb n="12"/> and were satisfied,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>and the disciples <lb n="13"/> picked up twelve basketfuls of broken pieces
                        of <lb n="14"/> bread and fish.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>The number <lb n="15"/> of the men who had eaten was five thousand. <lb
                            n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately Jesus made his disciples get into the boat <lb n="17"/> and go on
                        ahead of him to Bethsaida, <lb n="18"/> while he dismissed the crowd. <lb
                            n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>After leaving them, he went up on a mountainside to pray. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="84r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>Later that night, the boat was in the middle of the lake, <lb n="1"/> and he
                        was alone on land.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>He saw the disciples straining <lb n="2"/> at the oars, because the wind was
                        against <lb n="3"/> them. Shortly before dawn he went <lb n="4"/> out to
                        them, walking on the lake. He was about to pass by <lb n="5"/> them,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>but when they saw him walking <lb n="6"/> on the lake, they thought he was a
                        ghost. They cried out, <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>because they all saw him and were terrified. <lb n="8"/> Immediately he spoke
                        to them and <lb n="9"/> said, “Take courage! It is I. Don't be afraid.” <lb
                            n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he climbed into the boat with them, and the wind <lb n="11"/> died down.
                        They were completely amazed,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>for they had not understood <lb n="12"/> about the loaves; their hearts were
                            <lb n="13"/> hardened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="53" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had crossed over, they <lb n="14"/> landed at Gennesaret and
                        anchored there.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="54" type="verse">
                    <p>As soon as <lb n="15"/> they got out of the boat, people recognized Jesus.
                            <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="55" type="verse">
                    <p>They ran throughout that whole region <lb n="17"/> and carried the sick on
                        mats <lb n="18"/> to wherever they heard he was. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="56" type="verse">
                    <p>And wherever he went-into villages, towns <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="85r"/> or countryside-they placed the sick <lb n="1"/> in the
                        marketplaces. They begged him to let them touch <lb n="2"/> even the edge of
                        his cloak, and all who touched <lb n="3"/> it were healed.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>The Pharisees and some of <lb n="4"/> the teachers of the law who had come
                        from Jerusalem gathered around Jesus <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>and saw some of his disciples <lb n="6"/> eating food with hands that were
                            <lb n="7"/> defiled, that is, unwashed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>(The Pharisees <lb n="8"/> and all the Jews do not eat unless they give their
                        hands <lb n="9"/> a ceremonial washing, holding to the tradition of the <lb
                            n="10"/> elders.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>When they come from the marketplace they do not eat <lb n="11"/> unless they
                        wash. And they observe many other traditions <lb n="12"/>, such as the
                        washing of cups <lb n="13"/>, pitchers and kettles.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>So the Pharisees <lb n="14"/> and teachers of the law asked Jesus, “Why don't
                        your disciples <lb n="15"/> live according to the tradition of the elders
                            <lb n="16"/> instead of eating their food with defiled <lb n="17"/>
                        hands?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, <lb n="18"/> “Isaiah was right when he prophesied about you
                            hypocrites;<lb n="19"/> as it is written: “'These people honor me with
                        their lips, but their hearts <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="85v"/> are far from me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>They worship me in vain; <lb n="1"/> their teachings are merely human rules.'
                            <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>You have let go of the commands of God <lb n="3"/> and are holding on to
                        human traditions.” <lb n="4"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> A portion
                            of this verse is found in the Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV
                            translation. </note>
                        <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>And he continued, “You have a fine way of setting aside the commands <lb
                            n="6"/> of God in order to observe your own traditions!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>For Moses <lb n="7"/> said, 'Honor your father <lb n="8"/> and mother,' and,
                        'Anyone who curses their father or mother is to be put to death.' <lb n="9"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>But you say that if anyone declares that what might have been used to help
                        their father <lb n="10"/> or mother is Corban that is, <lb n="11"/> devoted
                        to God</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>then you no longer let <lb n="12"/> them do anything for their father or
                        mother.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Thus you nullify <lb n="13"/> the word of God by your tradition <lb n="14"/>
                        that you have handed down. And you do <lb n="15"/> many things like
                        that.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Again Jesus called the crowd to him and said, <lb n="16"/> “Listen to me,
                        everyone, and understand this.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Nothing <lb n="17"/> outside a person can defile <lb n="18"/> them by going
                        into them. Rather, it is what comes out of <lb n="19"/> a person that <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="86r"/> defiles them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>
                        <lb n="1"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the
                            Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>After he had left the crowd and entered the house, his disciples asked <lb
                            n="2"/> him about this parable.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Are <lb n="3"/> you so dull?” he asked. “Don't you see that <lb n="4"/>
                        nothing that enters a person <lb n="5"/> from the outside can defile <lb
                            n="6"/> them?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>For it doesn't go into their heart but into their stomach, <lb n="7"/> and
                        then out of the body.” In saying this, Jesus declared all foods clean.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>He went on <lb n="8"/>: “What comes out of a person is what defiles <lb n="9"
                        /> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>For it is from within, out of a person's heart, <lb n="10"/> that evil
                        thoughts come-sexual immorality, <lb n="11"/> theft, murder,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>adultery, <lb n="12"/> greed, malice, deceit, lewdness, envy, slander, <lb
                            n="13"/> arrogance and folly</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>All these evils come <lb n="14"/> from inside and defile a person.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus left <lb n="15"/> that place and went to the vicinity of Tyre. He
                        entered <lb n="16"/> a house and did not want anyone to know it; yet he
                        could not keep his presence <lb n="17"/> secret.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>In fact, as soon as she heard about him, a woman whose <lb n="18"/> little
                        daughter was possessed by an impure spirit came and fell <lb n="19"/> at his
                        feet.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The woman was a <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="86v"/> Greek, born in Syrian Phoenicia. She begged Jesus to drive the
                        demon <lb n="1"/> out of her daughter.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“<lb n="2"/> First let the children eat all they want,” he told her, “for it
                        is not right <lb n="3"/> to take the children's bread and toss it to the
                        dogs.” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“Lord,” she replied, <lb n="5"/> “even the dogs under the table eat the
                        children's crumbs.” <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he told her, “For such a reply, you may go; <lb n="7"/> the demon has
                        left your daughter.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>She went <lb n="8"/> home and found her child lying on <lb n="9"/> the bed,
                        and the demon gone.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="10"/> Jesus left the vicinity of Tyre and went through Sidon,
                        down <lb n="11"/> to the Sea of Galilee and into the region of the
                        Decapolis. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>There some people brought to him a man who was deaf and could hardly talk,<lb
                            n="13"/> and they begged Jesus to place his hand on him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>After he took <lb n="14"/> him aside, away from the crowd, Jesus put his
                        fingers <lb n="15"/> into the man's ears. Then he spit and touched <lb
                            n="16"/> the man's tongue.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>He looked up to heaven and with a deep sigh <lb n="17"/> said to him,
                        “Ephphatha!” which means “Be opened!”. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>At this, the man's ears were opened, his tongue <lb n="19"/> was loosened and
                        he began to speak <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="87r"/> plainly.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus commanded them not to tell anyone. But <lb n="1"/> the more he did so,
                        the more they kept <lb n="2"/> talking about it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>People were overwhelmed with amazement. <lb n="3"/> “He has done everything
                        well,” they said. “He even makes the deaf hear <lb n="4"/> and the mute
                        speak.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>During those days another <lb n="5"/> large crowd gathered. Since they had
                        nothing to eat, Jesus <lb n="6"/> called his disciples to him and said,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“I have compassion <lb n="7"/> for these people; they have already been with
                        me three days <lb n="8"/> and have nothing to eat.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>If I send <lb n="9"/> them home hungry, they will collapse <lb n="10"/> on
                        the way, because some of them have come a long distance.” <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>His disciples answered, “But where in this <lb n="12"/> remote place can
                        anyone get enough bread to feed them?” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“How many loaves do you have?” Jesus asked. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>He told the crowd to sit down <lb n="15"/> on the ground. When he had taken
                        the seven <lb n="16"/> loaves and given thanks, he broke them and gave them
                        to his disciples <lb n="17"/> to distribute to the people, and they did <lb
                            n="18"/> so.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>They had a few small fish as well; <lb n="19"/> he gave thanks for them also
                        and told the disciples to distribute them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>The people ate <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="87v"/> and were satisfied. Afterward the <lb n="1"/> disciples picked
                        up seven basketfuls of broken pieces <lb n="2"/> that were left over.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>About <lb n="3"/> four thousand were present. After he had <lb n="4"/> sent
                        them away,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>he got into the boat with <lb n="5"/> his disciples and went to the region of
                        Dalmanutha. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>The Pharisees came and began <lb n="7"/> to question Jesus. To test him, they
                        asked him for <lb n="8"/> a sign from heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>He sighed deeply and said, <lb n="9"/> “Why does this generation ask for a
                        sign? Truly I tell <lb n="10"/> you, no sign will be given to it.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="11"/> he left them, got back into the boat and crossed to the <lb
                            n="12"/> other side.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples had forgotten to bring <lb n="13"/> bread, except for one loaf
                        they had with <lb n="14"/> them in the boat.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“Be careful,” Jesus warned them. <lb n="15"/> “Watch out for the yeast of the
                        Pharisees and that of Herod.” <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>They discussed this with one another and said <lb n="17"/>, “It is because we
                        have no bread.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Aware <lb n="18"/> of their discussion, Jesus asked them: <lb n="19"/> “Why
                        are you talking about having no bread? <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="88r"/> Do you still not see or understand? Are your <lb n="1"/>
                        hearts hardened?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Do you have eyes but fail to see <lb n="2"/>, and ears but fail to hear? And
                        don't you <lb n="3"/> remember?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>When I broke the five loaves for <lb n="4"/> the five thousand, how many <lb
                            n="5"/> basketfuls of pieces did you pick up?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>“And <lb n="6"/>when I broke the seven loaves for the four thousand, <lb
                            n="7"/> how many basketfuls of pieces did you pick up?” <lb n="8"/> They
                        answered, “Seven.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, <lb n="9"/> “Do you still not understand?” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>They came to Bethsaida, and some people brought a blind man and <lb n="11"/>
                        begged Jesus to touch him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>He took the blind man by the hand <lb n="12"/> and led him outside the
                        village. When he had spit on the man's <lb n="13"/> eyes and put his hands
                        on him, Jesus asked, <lb n="14"/> “Do you see anything?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>He looked up and said, <lb n="15"/> “I see people; they look like trees
                        walking around.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="16"/> Once more Jesus put his hands on the man's eyes. Then his eyes
                            <lb n="17"/> were opened, his sight was restored, and he saw <lb n="18"
                        /> everything clearly.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="19"/> Jesus sent him home, saying <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="88v"/> “Don't even go into the village.”<lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus and his disciples went on to the villages <lb n="2"/> around Caesarea
                        Philippi. On the way he asked them, <lb n="3"/> “Who do people say I
                        am?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>They replied, <lb n="4"/> “Some say John the Baptist; others say <lb n="5"/>
                        Elijah; and still others, one of the prophets.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“But <lb n="6"/> what about you?” he asked. “Who do you say I am?” <lb n="7"
                        /> Peter answered, “You are the Messiah.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus warned <lb n="8"/> them not to tell anyone about him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>He then began to teach <lb n="9"/> them that the Son of Man must suffer many
                        things <lb n="10"/> and be rejected by the elders, <lb n="11"/> the chief
                        priests and the teachers of the law, and that he must be killed and after
                        three <lb n="12"/> days rise again.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>He spoke plainly about this <lb n="13"/>, and Peter took him aside and began
                        to rebuke <lb n="14"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>But when Jesus turned and looked at his disciples <lb n="15"/>, he rebuked
                        Peter. “Get behind <lb n="16"/> me, Satan!” he said. “You do not have in
                        mind the concerns of God, <lb n="17"/> but merely human concerns.” <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he called the crowd to him along with his disciples and said: <lb n="19"
                        /> “Whoever wants to be my disciple must deny themselves and take up <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="89r"/> their cross and follow me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>For whoever <lb n="1"/> wants to save their life will lose it, <lb n="2"/>
                        but whoever loses their life for <lb n="3"/> me and for the gospel will save
                        it. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>What good is it for someone to gain <lb n="5"/> the whole world, yet forfeit
                        their soul? <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Or what can anyone give in exchange for <lb n="7"/> their soul?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone is ashamed of me <lb n="8"/> and my words in this adulterous and
                            <lb n="9"/> sinful generation, the Son of Man will be ashamed of them
                        when <lb n="10"/> he comes in his Father's glory with the holy angels.” <lb
                            n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate
                            but not in the NIV translation. </note><lb n="12"/>
                        <lb n="13"/>
                        <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p><hi rend="italic"> And he said to them, “Truly I tell you, some who are
                            standing here will not taste death before they see that the kingdom of
                            God has come with power.”</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not in Latin Vulgate.
                        </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>After six days Jesus took Peter <lb n="15"/>, James and John with him and led
                        them up a high <lb n="16"/> mountain, where they were all alone. There he
                        was transfigured <lb n="17"/> before them.<note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:2 is Mark 9:1 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>His clothes <lb n="18"/> became dazzling white, whiter <lb n="19"/> than
                        anyone in the world could bleach them. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="89v"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:3 is Mark 9:2 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>And there appeared before them Elijah and Moses <lb n="1"/>, who were talking
                        with Jesus.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:4 is Mark 9:3 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter said to Jesus, “Rabbi, <lb n="2"/> it is good for us to be here. Let us
                        put up three shelters <lb n="3"/> -one for you, one for Moses and one for
                        Elijah.” <lb n="4"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:5 is Mark 9:4
                            in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>He did not know <lb n="5"/> what to say, they were so frightened.<note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:6 is Mark 9:5 in the Latin Vulgate.
                        </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Then a cloud appeared <lb n="6"/> and covered them, and a voice came from the
                        cloud: “This <lb n="7"/> is my Son, whom I love. Listen to him!”<note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:7 is Mark 9:6 in the Latin Vulgate.
                        </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Suddenly, when they looked around <lb n="8"/>, they no longer saw <lb n="9"/>
                        anyone with them except Jesus.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:8 is
                            Mark 9:7 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>As they were coming down <lb n="10"/> the mountain, Jesus gave them orders
                        not to tell anyone <lb n="11"/> what they had seen until the Son of Man <lb
                            n="12"/> had risen from the dead. <lb n="13"/><note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:9 is Mark 9:8 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>They kept the matter to themselves, discussing what <lb n="14"/> “rising from
                        the dead” meant. <lb n="15"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:10 is
                            Mark 9:9 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>And they asked him, “Why do the teachers of the law <lb n="16"/> say that
                        Elijah must come first?”<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:11 is Mark
                            9:10 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="17"/> “To be sure, Elijah does come first, <lb n="18"/>
                        and restores all things. Why then is it written that <lb n="19"/> the Son of
                        Man must suffer much and be rejected? <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="90r"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:12 is Mark 9:11 in
                            the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you, Elijah has come, and they have done <lb n="1"/> to him
                        everything they wished, just as it is written <lb n="2"/> about him.” <lb
                            n="3"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:13 is Mark 9:12 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>When they came to the other disciples, they saw a large crowd <lb n="4"/>
                        around them and the teachers of the law arguing with them.<note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:14 is Mark 9:13 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>As soon as all the people <lb n="5"/> saw Jesus, they were overwhelmed with
                        wonder <lb n="6"/> and ran to greet him.<note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:15 is Mark 9:14 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“What <lb n="7"/> are you arguing with them about?” he asked. <lb n="8"
                            /><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:16 is Mark 9:15 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>A man in the crowd answered, “Teacher, I brought you <lb n="9"/> my son, who
                        is possessed by a spirit that has robbed him of speech. <lb n="10"/><note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:17 is Mark 9:16 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Whenever it seizes him, it throws him <lb n="11"/> to the ground. He foams at
                        the mouth, gnashes his teeth and becomes rigid. I asked <lb n="12"/> your
                        disciples to drive out the spirit, but they could not.” <lb n="13"/><note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:18 is Mark 9:17 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“You unbelieving generation,” Jesus replied, <lb n="14"/> “how long shall I
                        stay with you? <lb n="15"/> How long shall I put up with you? Bring the boy
                        to me.”<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:19 is Mark 9:18 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>So they brought him. <lb n="16"/> When the spirit saw Jesus, it immediately
                            <lb n="17"/> threw the boy into a convulsion. He fell to the ground and
                        rolled around, foaming at the <lb n="18"/> mouth.<note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:20 is Mark 9:19 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus asked the boy's father, “How <lb n="19"/> long has he been like this?”
                        “From childhood,” <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="90v"/> he answered.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:21 is
                            Mark 9:20 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“It has often thrown him into fire or water <lb n="1"/> to kill him. But if
                        you can do anything, <lb n="2"/> take pity on us and help us.”<note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:22 is Mark 9:21 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“'If you can'?” said Jesus. <lb n="3"/> “Everything is possible for one who
                        believes.” <lb n="4"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:23 is Mark
                            9:22 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately the boy's father exclaimed <lb n="5"/>, “I do believe; help me
                        overcome my unbelief!” <lb n="6"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark
                            9:24 is Mark 9:23 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus saw that a crowd <lb n="7"/> was running to the scene, he rebuked
                        the impure spirit. <lb n="8"/> “You deaf and mute spirit,” he said, “I
                        command you, come out of him <lb n="9"/> and never enter him again.”<note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:25 is Mark 9:24 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The spirit shrieked <lb n="10"/>, convulsed him violently and came out. The
                        boy looked <lb n="11"/> so much like a corpse that many said, <lb n="12"/>
                        “He's dead.”<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:26 is Mark 9:25 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus took him by the hand <lb n="13"/> and lifted him to his feet, and
                        he stood up.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:27 is Mark 9:26 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>After Jesus had gone <lb n="14"/> indoors, his disciples asked him privately
                            <lb n="15"/>, “Why couldn't we drive it out?” <lb n="16"/><note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:28 is Mark 9:27 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “This kind can come out <lb n="17"/> only by prayer.” <lb n="18"
                            /><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:29 is Mark 9:28 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>They left that place and passed through Galilee. <lb n="19"/> Jesus did not
                        want anyone to know where they were,<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark
                            9:30 is Mark 9:29 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>because he was teaching his disciples. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="91r"/> He said to them, “The Son of Man <lb n="1"/> is going to be
                        delivered into the hands of men. They will kill him, <lb n="2"/> and after
                        three days he will rise.”<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:31 is
                            Mark 9:30 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>But they did not understand what he meant and were afraid <lb n="3"/> to ask
                        him about it. <lb n="4"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:32 is
                            Mark 9:31 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>They came to Capernaum. When he was in the house, <lb n="5"/> he asked them,
                        “What were you arguing about on the road?” <lb n="6"/><note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:33 is Mark 9:32 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>But they kept quiet because on the way they had argued <lb n="7"/> about who
                        was the greatest.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:34 is Mark 9:33
                            in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Sitting down <lb n="8"/>, Jesus called the Twelve and said, “Anyone who wants
                        to be first <lb n="9"/> must be the very last, and the servant of all.” <lb
                            n="10"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:35 is Mark 9:34 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>He took a little child whom he placed among them <lb n="11"/>. Taking the
                        child in his arms, he said to them, <lb n="12"/><note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:36 is Mark 9:35 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>“Whoever welcomes one of these little children <lb n="13"/> in my name
                        welcomes me; and whoever welcomes <lb n="14"/> me does not welcome me but
                            <lb n="15"/> the one who sent me.”<note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:37 is Mark 9:36 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>“Teacher,” said John, <lb n="16"/> “we saw someone driving out demons in your
                        name <lb n="17"/> and we told him to stop, because he was not <lb n="18"/>
                        one of us.”<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:38 is Mark 9:37 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not stop him,” Jesus said. <lb n="19"/> “For no one who does a miracle in
                        my name can in the next moment <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="91v"/> say anything bad about me,<note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:39 is Mark 9:38 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>for whoever <lb n="1"/> is not against us is for us.<note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:40 is Mark 9:39 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly <lb n="2"/> I tell you, anyone who gives you a cup of water in <lb
                            n="3"/> my name because you belong to <lb n="4"/> the Messiah will
                        certainly not lose their reward. <lb n="5"/><note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:41 is Mark 9:40 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>“If anyone causes one of these <lb n="6"/> little ones-those who believe in
                        me-to stumble, <lb n="7"/> it would be better for them if a large millstone
                        were hung around their neck <lb n="8"/> and they were thrown into the
                            sea.<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:42 is Mark 9:41 in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>If your hand causes <lb n="9"/> you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for
                        you <lb n="10"/> to enter life maimed than with two hands to go into hell,
                            <lb n="11"/> where the fire never goes out.<note place="margin"
                            type="gloss"> Mark 9:43 is Mark 9:42 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="12"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the
                            Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="13"/> And if your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off. <lb n="14"/>
                        It is better for you to enter life crippled <lb n="15"/> than to have two
                        feet and be thrown into hell. <lb n="16"/><note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:45 is Mark 9:44 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="17"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the
                            Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>And if your eye causes you to stumble <lb n="18"/>, pluck it out. It is
                        better for you to enter <lb n="19"/> the kingdom of God with one eye than to
                        have two eyes <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="91r"/> and be thrown into hell,<note place="margin" type="gloss">
                            Mark 9:47 is Mark 9:46 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>where “'the worms that eat them do not <lb n="1"/> die, and the fire is not
                            quenched.'<note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:48 is Mark 9: in the
                            Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>Everyone <lb n="2"/> will be salted with fire. <lb n="3"/><note
                            place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:49 is Mark 9:48 in the Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>“Salt is good, but if it loses its saltiness, <lb n="4"/> how can you make it
                        salty again? Have salt among yourselves, <lb n="5"/> and be at peace with
                        each other.” <lb n="6"/><note place="margin" type="gloss"> Mark 9:50 is Mark
                            9:49 in the Latin Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus then left that place and went into the region of Judea <lb n="7"/> and
                        across the Jordan. Again crowds of people came to him, and as was <lb n="8"
                        /> his custom, he taught them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Some Pharisees came <lb n="9"/> and tested him by asking, “Is it lawful for a
                        man <lb n="10"/> to divorce his wife?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>“What did <lb n="11"/> Moses command you?” he replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>They said, “Moses permitted <lb n="12"/> a man to write a certificate of
                        divorce and send her away.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“It was <lb n="13"/> because your hearts were hard <lb n="14"/> that Moses
                        wrote you this law,” Jesus replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“But at the beginning <lb n="15"/> of creation God 'made them male and
                        female.' <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>'For this reason a man will leave his father and mother <lb n="17"/> and be
                        united to his wife,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>and the two <lb n="18"/> will become one flesh.' So they are no longer two,
                        but one <lb n="19"/> flesh.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore what God has joined together, let no one separate.” <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="92v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>When they were in the house again, the disciples <lb n="1"/> asked Jesus
                        about this. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, “Anyone who divorces his wife <lb n="3"/> and marries another
                        woman commits adultery against her.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>And if she divorces <lb n="4"/> her husband and marries another man, she
                        commits adultery.” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>People were bringing little children to Jesus for him to place his hands on
                        them <lb n="6"/>, but the disciples rebuked them. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus saw this, he was indignant. He said to <lb n="8"/> them, “Let the
                        little children come to me, and do not hinder them, <lb n="9"/> for the
                        kingdom of God belongs to such as these. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, anyone who will not receive <lb n="11"/> the kingdom of God
                        like a little child will never <lb n="12"/> enter it.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>And he took the children in his arms, placed his hands <lb n="13"/> on them
                        and blessed them. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus started on his way, a man ran <lb n="15"/> up to him and fell on his
                        knees before him. <lb n="16"/> “Good teacher,” he asked, “what must I do to
                        inherit <lb n="17"/> eternal life?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why do you call me good?” Jesus answered. <lb n="18"/> “No one is
                        good-except God alone.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>You know <lb n="19"/> the commandments: 'You shall not murder, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="93r"/> you shall not commit adultery, you shall not steal, you shall
                        not give false testimony, you shall not defraud, honor your father and
                        mother. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>“Teacher,” he declared, “all these <lb n="2"/> I have kept since I was a
                        boy.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus looked at him <lb n="3"/> and loved him. “One thing you lack,” he said.
                        “Go, sell <lb n="4"/> everything you have and give to the poor <lb n="5"/>,
                        and you will have treasure in heaven. Then come, follow me.” <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>At this the man's face fell. He went away sad, <lb n="7"/> because he had
                        great wealth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus looked around <lb n="8"/> and said to his disciples, “How hard <lb
                            n="9"/> it is for the rich to enter the kingdom of God!” <lb n="10"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p><hi rend="italic"> The disciples were amazed at his words. But Jesus said
                            again, “Children, how hard it is to enter the kingdom of God!</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not found in Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle <lb n="11"/> than
                        for someone who is rich to enter the kingdom of God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples were even more amazed <lb n="12"/>, and said to each other,
                        “Who then can be <lb n="13"/> saved?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus looked at them and said, “With man <lb n="14"/> this is impossible, but
                        not with God; <lb n="15"/> all things are possible with God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Peter spoke up <lb n="16"/>, “We have left everything to follow <lb
                            n="17"/> you!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you,” Jesus replied, <lb n="18"/> “no one who has left home or
                        brothers <lb n="19"/> or sisters or mother or father or <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="93v"/> children or fields for me and the gospel <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>will fail to receive a hundred times as much <lb n="2"/> in this present age:
                        homes, brothers, sisters, <lb n="3"/> mothers, children and fields-along
                        with persecutions- <lb n="4"/> and in the age to come eternal life. <lb
                            n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>But many who are first will be last, and the last <lb n="6"/> first.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>They were on their way up to Jerusalem, <lb n="7"/> with Jesus leading the
                        way, and the disciples were astonished, while those who followed were
                        afraid. <lb n="8"/> Again he took the Twelve aside and told them <lb n="9"/>
                        what was going to happen to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“We are going up to Jerusalem,” <lb n="10"/> he said, “and the Son of Man
                        will be delivered over to the chief <lb n="11"/> priests and the teachers of
                        the law. They will condemn him to death and <lb n="12"/> will hand him over
                        to the Gentiles,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>who will mock <lb n="13"/> him and spit on him, flog him <lb n="14"/> and
                        kill him. Three days later he will rise.” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Then James and John, the sons of Zebedee, <lb n="16"/> came to him.
                        “Teacher,” they said, “we want you to do for us whatever <lb n="17"/> we
                        ask.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you want me to do for you?”<lb n="18"/> he asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>They replied, “Let one of us sit at your right <lb n="19"/> and the other at
                        your left <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="94r"/> in your glory.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>“You don't know what you are asking,” Jesus said. <lb n="1"/> “Can you drink
                        the cup I drink or be baptized with the baptism <lb n="2"/> I am baptized
                        with?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>“We can,” they answered. <lb n="3"/> Jesus said to them, “You will drink the
                        cup <lb n="4"/> I drink and be baptized with the baptism <lb n="5"/> I am
                        baptized with,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>but to sit at my right <lb n="6"/> or left is not for me to grant <lb n="7"
                        />. These places belong to those for whom they have been prepared.” <lb
                            n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>When the ten heard about this, they became indignant with <lb n="9"/> James
                        and John.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus called them together and said, “You know that <lb n="10"/> those who
                        are regarded as rulers of the Gentiles lord it over <lb n="11"/> them, and
                        their high officials exercise authority over <lb n="12"/> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Not so with you. Instead, <lb n="13"/> whoever wants to become great among
                        you must be your servant, <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>and whoever wants to be first <lb n="15"/> must be slave of all. <lb n="16"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>For even the Son of Man did not come <lb n="17"/> to be served, but to serve,
                        and to give his <lb n="18"/> life as a ransom for many.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>Then they came to Jericho. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="94v"/> As Jesus and his disciples, together with a large crowd, were
                        leaving the city, a blind man, <lb n="1"/> Bartimaeus (which means “son of
                        Timaeus”), was sitting by the roadside begging. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>When he heard that it was Jesus of Nazareth, <lb n="3"/> he began to shout,
                        “Jesus, Son of David, have mercy <lb n="4"/> on me!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>Many rebuked him and told him to be quiet, <lb n="5"/> but he shouted all the
                        more, “Son of David, <lb n="6"/> have mercy on me!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus stopped and said, “Call him.” <lb n="7"/> So they called to the blind
                        man, “Cheer up! <lb n="8"/> On your feet! He's calling you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>Throwing his cloak aside, <lb n="9"/> he jumped to his feet and came to
                        Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you want me to do for you?” <lb n="10"/> Jesus asked him. The blind
                        man said, “Rabbi, <lb n="11"/> I want to see.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>“Go,” said Jesus, “your faith has healed you.” <lb n="12"/> Immediately he
                        received his sight and <lb n="13"/> followed Jesus along the road. <lb
                            n="14"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>As they approached Jerusalem and came to Bethphage and Bethany <lb n="15"/>
                        at the Mount of Olives, Jesus sent two of his disciples,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>saying to them, <lb n="16"/> “Go to the village ahead of you, and just as you
                        enter it, <lb n="17"/> you will find a colt tied there, <lb n="18"/> which
                        no one has ever ridden. Untie it and <lb n="19"/> bring it here.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone asks you, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="95r"/> 'Why are you doing this?' say, 'The Lord needs it <lb n="1"/>
                        and will send it back here shortly.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>They <lb n="2"/> went and found a colt outside in the street, tied <lb n="3"
                        /> at a doorway. As they untied it,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>some people standing there asked, <lb n="4"/> “What are you doing, untying
                        that colt?” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>They answered as Jesus had told them to, and the people let <lb n="6"/> them
                        go.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>When they brought the colt to Jesus and threw <lb n="7"/> their cloaks over
                        it, he sat on it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Many <lb n="8"/> people spread their cloaks on the road, while <lb n="9"/>
                        others spread branches they had cut in the fields. <lb n="10"/>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> A portion of this verse is found in the
                            Latin Vulgate but not in the NIV translation. </note>
                        <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Those who went ahead and those who followed shouted, <lb n="12"/> “Hosanna!”
                        “Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>“Blessed is the coming <lb n="13"/> kingdom of our father David!” “Hosanna in
                        the highest heaven!” <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus entered Jerusalem and went into the temple courts. He looked around <lb
                            n="15"/> at everything, but since it was already <lb n="16"/> late, he
                        went out to Bethany with the Twelve. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>The next day as they were leaving Bethany, Jesus was hungry.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="18"/> Seeing in the distance a fig tree in leaf, he went <lb n="19"/>
                        to find out if it had any fruit. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="95v"/> When he reached it, he found nothing but leaves, <lb n="1"/>
                        because it was not the season for figs.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he said <lb n="2"/> to the tree, “May no one ever eat fruit <lb n="3"/>
                        from you again.” And his disciples heard him say <lb n="4"/> it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>On reaching Jerusalem, Jesus entered the <lb n="5"/> temple courts and began
                        driving out those who were buying and selling <lb n="6"/> there. He
                        overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches <lb n="7"/> of
                        those selling doves,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>and would not <lb n="8"/> allow anyone to carry merchandise through <lb n="9"
                        /> the temple courts.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>And as he taught them, he said, “Is it not written: <lb n="10"/> 'My house
                        will be called <lb n="11"/> a house of prayer for all nations'? But you have
                        made it <lb n="12"/> 'a den of robbers.'” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>The chief priests and the teachers of the law <lb n="14"/> heard this and
                        began looking for a way to kill him, <lb n="15"/> for they feared him,
                        because <lb n="16"/> the whole crowd was amazed at his teaching. <lb n="17"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p><hi rend="italic"> When evening came, Jesus and his disciples went out of the
                            city.</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not found in Latin
                            Vulgate. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>In the morning, as they went along, they saw the fig tree withered from the
                        roots. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter remembered and said to Jesus, “Rabbi, look! The fig tree <lb n="19"/>
                        you cursed has withered!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“Have faith in God,” <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="96r"/> Jesus answered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you, if anyone <lb n="1"/> says to this mountain, 'Go, throw
                        yourself into the sea,' <lb n="2"/> and does not doubt in their heart but
                        believes <lb n="3"/> that what they say will happen, it will be done for
                        them. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore I tell you, whatever <lb n="5"/> you ask for in prayer, believe
                        that you have received it, and it will be <lb n="6"/> yours.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>And when you stand praying, <lb n="7"/> if you hold anything against anyone
                            <lb n="8"/>, forgive them, so that your Father in heaven <lb n="9"/> may
                        forgive you your sins.” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p/>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>They arrived again in Jerusalem, and while Jesus was walking <lb n="11"/> in
                        the temple courts, the chief priests, the teachers of the law <lb n="12"/>
                        and the elders came to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“By what authority are you doing <lb n="13"/> these things?” they asked. “And
                        who gave you authority <lb n="14"/> to do this?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “I will ask you <lb n="15"/> one question. Answer me, and I
                        will <lb n="16"/> tell you by what authority I am doing <lb n="17"/> these
                        things.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>John's baptism-was it from heaven <lb n="18"/>, or of human origin? Tell me!”
                            <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>They discussed it among themselves and said, “If we say, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="96v"/> 'From heaven,' he will ask, 'Then why didn't you believe <lb
                            n="1"/> him?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>But if we say, 'Of human origin' “” They feared the people, <lb n="2"/> for
                        everyone held that John really <lb n="3"/> was a prophet.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>So they answered Jesus <lb n="4"/>, “We don't know.” Jesus said, “Neither
                        will I <lb n="5"/> tell you by what authority I am doing these things.” <lb
                            n="6"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus then began to speak to them in parables: “A man planted a vineyard. <lb
                            n="7"/> He put a wall around it, dug a pit for the winepress <lb n="8"/>
                        and built a watchtower. Then he rented the vineyard to some farmers <lb
                            n="9"/> and moved to another place.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>At harvest <lb n="10"/> time he sent a servant to the tenants to collect from
                        them some of the fruit of <lb n="11"/> the vineyard.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>But they seized him, beat him <lb n="12"/> and sent him away
                        empty-handed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he sent another <lb n="13"/> servant to them; they struck this man on
                        the head and treated him shamefully. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>He sent still another, and that one they killed. He sent many others; <lb
                            n="15"/> some of them they beat, others they killed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“He had one <lb n="16"/> left to send, a son, whom he loved. He sent <lb
                            n="17"/> him last of all, saying, 'They will respect <lb n="18"/> my
                        son.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“But the tenants said to one another, <lb n="19"/> 'This is the heir. Come,
                        let's kill him, and the <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="97r"/> inheritance will be ours.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>So they took him and killed him, <lb n="1"/> and threw him out of the
                        vineyard.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“What then will <lb n="2"/> the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and
                        kill those tenants and give the vineyard <lb n="3"/> to others.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Haven't you read this passage of Scripture: “'The stone <lb n="4"/> the
                        builders rejected has become the <lb n="5"/> cornerstone; </p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>the Lord has done this,<lb n="6"/> and it is marvelous in our eyes'?” <lb
                            n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the chief priests, the teachers of the law and the elders looked <lb
                            n="8"/> for a way to arrest him because they knew he had spoken the
                        parable against them. But they were afraid of the crowd; <lb n="9"/> so they
                        left him and went away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Later they sent some <lb n="10"/> of the Pharisees and Herodians to Jesus to
                        catch him <lb n="11"/> in his words.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>They came to him and said, “Teacher, <lb n="12"/> we know that you are a man
                        of integrity. You aren't swayed by others, <lb n="13"/> because you pay no
                        attention to who they are; but <lb n="14"/> you teach the way of God in
                        accordance with the truth. Is it right to pay <lb n="15"/> the imperial tax
                        to Caesar or not?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Should we pay or shouldn't we?” But Jesus knew <lb n="16"/> their hypocrisy.
                        “Why are you trying to trap me?” he asked. <lb n="17"/> “Bring me a denarius
                        and let me look at it.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>They brought the coin <lb n="18"/>, and he asked them, “Whose image is this?
                        And whose inscription?” <lb n="19"/> “Caesar's,” they replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="97v"/> to them, “Give back to Caesar what is <lb n="1"/> Caesar's and
                        to God what is God's.” And they were amazed at him. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection <lb n="3"/>, came to him
                        with a question. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“Teacher,” they said, “Moses wrote for us that if <lb n="5"/> a man's brother
                        dies and leaves a wife <lb n="6"/> but no children, the man must marry the
                        widow <lb n="7"/> and raise up offspring for his brother.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Now <lb n="8"/> there were seven brothers. The first <lb n="9"/> one married
                        and died without leaving any children. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>The second one married the widow, but he also died, <lb n="11"/> leaving no
                        child. It was the same with the third. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>In fact, none of the seven left any <lb n="13"/> children. Last of all, the
                        woman died too <lb n="14"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>At the resurrection whose wife will <lb n="15"/> she be, since the seven were
                            <lb n="16"/> married to her?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="17"/> “Are you not in error because you do not know the
                        Scriptures <lb n="18"/> or the power of God?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>When the dead rise <lb n="19"/>, they will neither marry nor be given in
                        marriage; <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="98r"/> they will be like the angels in heaven. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Now about the dead rising-have you not read <lb n="2"/> in the Book of Moses,
                        in the account of the burning bush, <lb n="3"/> how God said to him, 'I am
                        the God of Abraham, <lb n="4"/> the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob'?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>He is not the God of the dead, but of the living. <lb n="5"/> You are badly
                        mistaken!” </p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>One of the teachers of <lb n="6"/> the law came and heard them debating.
                        Noticing that Jesus had given <lb n="7"/> them a good answer, he asked <lb
                            n="8"/> him, “Of all the commandments, which is the most important?” <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“The most important <lb n="10"/> one,” answered Jesus, “is this: 'Hear, O
                        Israel: The Lord <lb n="11"/> our God, the Lord is one.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Love the Lord your God with all <lb n="12"/> your heart and with all your
                        soul and with all <lb n="13"/> your mind and with all your <lb n="14"/>
                        strength.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>The second is this: <lb n="15"/> 'Love your neighbor as yourself.' There is
                        no commandment <lb n="16"/> greater than these.”<lb n="17"/>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>“Well said, teacher,” the man replied. “You are right in saying <lb n="18"/>
                        that God is one and there is no other but him. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>To love him with all your heart, with all your understanding <pb n="20v"/>
                        <pb n="98v"/> and with all your strength, and to love <lb n="1"/> your
                        neighbor as yourself is more important than <lb n="2"/> all burnt offerings
                        and sacrifices.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus <lb n="3"/> saw that he had answered wisely, <lb n="4"/> he said
                        to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” <lb n="5"/> And from then
                        on no one dared ask him any more questions.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>While Jesus <lb n="6"/> was teaching in the temple courts, he asked, “Why do
                        the teachers of the law say that the <lb n="7"/> Messiah is the son of
                        David?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>David himself, speaking <lb n="8"/> by the Holy Spirit, declared: “'The Lord
                        said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until <lb n="9"/> I put your enemies
                        under <lb n="10"/> your feet.”'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>David himself calls him 'Lord.' How then can he be his <lb n="11"/> son?” The
                        large crowd listened to him with delight. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>As he taught, Jesus said, “Watch out for the teachers of the law. <lb n="13"
                        /> They like to walk around in flowing robes and be greeted with respect in
                        the marketplaces, <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>and have the most important seats in the synagogues <lb n="15"/> and the
                        places of honor at banquets. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>They devour widows' houses and for a show make lengthy prayers. <lb n="17"/>
                        These men will be punished most severely.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>41 Jesus sat down <lb n="18"/> opposite the place where the offerings were
                        put <lb n="19"/> and watched the crowd putting their money into the temple
                        treasury. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="99r"/> Many rich people threw in large amounts.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>But a <lb n="1"/> poor widow came and put in <lb n="2"/> two very small
                        copper coins, worth only a few cents.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Calling <lb n="3"/> his disciples to him, Jesus said, “Truly <lb n="4"/> I
                        tell you, this poor widow has put <lb n="5"/> more into the treasury than
                        all the others. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>They all gave out of their <lb n="7"/> wealth; but she, out of her poverty,
                        put in everything <lb n="8"/> -all she had to live on.” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus was leaving the temple, one of <lb n="10"/> his disciples said to
                        him, “Look, Teacher! What massive stones! <lb n="11"/> What magnificent
                        buildings!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do you see <lb n="12"/> all these great buildings?” replied Jesus. “Not one
                            <lb n="13"/> stone here will be left on another; every one will be
                        thrown down.” <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives opposite <lb n="15"/> the temple,
                        Peter, James, John and <lb n="16"/> Andrew asked him privately,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>“Tell us, <lb n="17"/> when will these things happen? And what will be the
                        sign <lb n="18"/> that they are all about to be fulfilled?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to them <lb n="19"/>: “Watch out that <lb n="20"/>
                        <lb n="99v"/> no one deceives you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Many will come in my name <lb n="1"/>, claiming, 'I am he,' and will deceive
                        many. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>When you hear of wars and rumors <lb n="3"/> of wars, do not be alarmed. Such
                        things must happen, <lb n="4"/> but the end is still to come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Nation will rise against <lb n="5"/> nation, and kingdom against kingdom.
                        There will be <lb n="6"/> earthquakes in various places, and famines. <lb
                            n="7"/> These are the beginning of birth pains. <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“You must be on your guard. You will be handed over <lb n="9"/> to the local
                        councils and flogged in the synagogues. <lb n="10"/> On account of me you
                        will stand before governors and kings as witnesses to them. <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>And <lb n="12"/> the gospel must first be preached to all nations. <lb n="13"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Whenever you are arrested and brought to trial, do not worry beforehand <lb
                            n="14"/> about what to say. Just say whatever is given you at the time,
                            <lb n="15"/> for it is not you speaking, but the Holy Spirit. <lb n="16"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>“Brother will betray brother to death, and a father <lb n="17"/> his child.
                        Children will rebel against their <lb n="18"/> parents and have them put to
                        death.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Everyone will <lb n="19"/> hate you because of me, but the one <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="100r"/> who stands firm to the end will be saved. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>“When you see 'the abomination that causes desolation' <lb n="2"/> standing
                        where it does not belong-let the reader understand-<lb n="3"/> then let
                        those who are in Judea flee to the mountains. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Let no one on the housetop go down <lb n="5"/> or enter the house to take
                        anything out.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="6"/> Let no one in the field go back to get <lb n="7"/> their
                        cloak.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>How dreadful it will be in those days for pregnant <lb n="8"/> women and
                        nursing mothers! <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Pray that this will not take place in winter, <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>because those will be days of distress <lb n="11"/> unequaled from the
                        beginning, when God created the world, <lb n="12"/> until now-and never to
                        be equaled again. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>“If the Lord had not cut short those days, no one would survive. But for the
                        sake of the elect, <lb n="14"/> whom he has chosen, he has shortened them.
                            <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time if anyone says to you, 'Look, here is the Messiah!' or, 'Look,
                        there he is!' <lb n="16"/> do not believe it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>For false messiahs and false prophets <lb n="17"/> will appear and perform
                        signs and wonders <lb n="18"/> to deceive, if possible, even the elect.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="19"/> be on your guard; I have told you everything ahead of
                        time.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“But <lb n="20"/>
                        <lb n="100v"/> in those days, following that distress, “'the sun <lb n="1"/>
                        will be darkened, and the moon will not give its <lb n="2"/> light;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>the stars will fall from the sky, <lb n="3"/> and the heavenly bodies will be
                        shaken.' <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“At that time people will see the Son of Man coming <lb n="5"/> in clouds
                        with great power and glory. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>And he will send his angels and gather his elect <lb n="7"/> from the four
                        winds, from the ends of the earth to the <lb n="8"/> ends of the
                        heavens.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: 9 As soon as its twigs get tender
                        and its leaves 10 come out, you know that summer 11 is near.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Even so, when you see these <lb n="12"/> things happening, you know that it
                        is near, right at the door. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, this generation will certainly not pass away until all <lb
                            n="14"/> these things have happened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Heaven <lb n="15"/> and earth will pass away, but my <lb n="16"/> words will
                        never pass away. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>“But about that day or hour no one knows, not even the angels in heaven, nor
                        the Son, but only the <lb n="18"/> Father.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Be on guard! Be alert! You do not know when that <lb n="19"/> time will
                        come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>It's like a man going away: <lb n="20"/>
                        <seg n="101r" type="b"/> He leaves his house and puts his servants <lb n="1"
                        /> in charge, each with their assigned task, <lb n="2"/> and tells the one
                        at the door to keep watch. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore keep watch because you do not know when the owner of the house
                        will come back-<lb n="4"/> whether in the evening, or at midnight, or when
                        the rooster crows, or at dawn.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>If he comes suddenly, <lb n="5"/> do not let him find you sleeping.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>What I say <lb n="6"/> to you, I say to everyone: 'Watch!'”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Now the Passover and <lb n="7"/> the Festival of Unleavened Bread were only
                        two days away, <lb n="8"/> and the chief priests and the teachers of the law
                        were scheming <lb n="9"/> to arrest Jesus secretly and kill him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“But not during <lb n="10"/> the festival,” they said, “or the people may
                        riot.” <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>While he was in Bethany, reclining at the table in the home of Simon the
                        Leper, <lb n="12"/> a woman came with an alabaster jar <lb n="13"/> of very
                        expensive perfume, made of pure nard. She broke the jar and poured the
                        perfume <lb n="14"/> on his head.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Some of those <lb n="15"/> present were saying indignantly to <lb n="16"/>
                        one another, “Why this waste of <lb n="17"/> perfume?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>It could have been sold <lb n="18"/> for more than a year's wages and the
                        money given to the poor.” <lb n="19"/> And they rebuked her harshly.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“Leave her alone,” said Jesus. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="101v"/> “Why are you bothering her? She has done a beautiful <lb
                            n="1"/> thing to me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>The poor you will always have <lb n="2"/> with you, and you can help them any
                        time you want. <lb n="3"/> But you will not always have me. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>She did what she could. She poured perfume <lb n="5"/> on my body beforehand
                        to prepare for my burial.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you <lb n="6"/>, wherever the gospel is preached <lb n="7"/>
                        throughout the world, what she has done <lb n="8"/> will also be told, in
                        memory of her.” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Judas Iscariot, one of the Twelve, went <lb n="10"/> to the chief
                        priests to betray Jesus to them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>They <lb n="11"/> were delighted to hear this and promised to give him money.
                            <lb n="12"/> So he watched for an <lb n="13"/> opportunity to hand him
                        over.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>On the first day of the Festival of Unleavened Bread, <lb n="14"/> when it
                        was customary to sacrifice the Passover lamb, Jesus' disciples asked <lb
                            n="15"/> him, “Where do you want us to go and make preparations for you
                        to eat the Passover?” <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>So he sent two of his disciples, telling them, <lb n="17"/> “Go into the
                        city, and a man carrying a jar of <lb n="18"/> water will meet you. Follow
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Say to the owner <lb n="19"/> of the house he enters, 'The Teacher asks: <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="102r"/> Where is my guest room, where I may eat the Passover with <lb
                            n="1"/> my disciples?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>He will show <lb n="2"/> you a large room upstairs, furnished and ready. Make
                        preparations for us there.” <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples left, went into the city <lb n="4"/> and found things just as
                        Jesus had told them. <lb n="5"/> So they prepared the Passover. <lb n="6"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>When evening came, Jesus arrived with the Twelve. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>While they were reclining at the table eating, he said, “Truly I tell you,
                            <lb n="8"/> one of you will betray me-one who is eating with me.” <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>They were saddened, and one by one <lb n="10"/> they said to him, “Surely you
                        don't mean me?”<lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>“It is one of the Twelve,” he replied, “one who dips bread into the bowl with
                        me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="12"/> The Son of Man will go just as it is written about him. <lb
                            n="13"/> But woe to that man who betrays the Son of Man! <lb n="14"/> It
                        would be better for him if he had not been born.” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>While they were eating, Jesus took bread, and when he had given thanks, <lb
                            n="16"/> he broke it and gave it to his disciples, saying, “Take it;
                        this is <lb n="17"/> my body.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he took a cup, and when he had given thanks <lb n="18"/>, he gave it to
                        them, and they all drank from it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“This is <lb n="19"/> my blood of the covenant, which is <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="102v"/> poured out for many,” he said to them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you, <lb n="1"/> I will not drink again from the fruit of the
                        vine until that day <lb n="2"/> when I drink it new in the kingdom <lb n="3"
                        /> of God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“You 4 will all fall away,” Jesus told them, “for it is written: <lb n="5"/>
                        “'I will strike the shepherd, and <lb n="6"/> the sheep will be
                        scattered.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>But after I have <lb n="7"/> risen, I will go ahead of you into Galilee.” <lb
                            n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter declared, “Even if all fall away, <lb n="9"/> I will not.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you,” Jesus answered, <lb n="10"/> “today-yes, tonight-before
                        the rooster crows twice you yourself <lb n="11"/> will disown me three
                        times.” <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>But Peter insisted emphatically, “Even if I have to die with you, <lb n="13"
                        /> I will never disown you.” And all the others said the same. <lb n="14"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>They went to a place called Gethsemane, <lb n="15"/> and Jesus said to his
                        disciples, “Sit here while I pray.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>He took <lb n="16"/> Peter, James and John along with him, <lb n="17"/> and
                        he began to be deeply distressed and troubled. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>“My soul is overwhelmed with sorrow to the point of death,” he said to them.
                        “Stay here and keep watch.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Going a little farther, he fell to the ground <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="103r"/> and prayed that if possible the hour might <lb n="1"/> pass
                        from him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>“Abba, Father,” he said, <lb n="2"/> “everything is possible for you. Take
                        this <lb n="3"/> cup from me. Yet not what I will, but what <lb n="4"/> you
                        will.” </p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he returned to his disciples and found them sleeping. <lb n="5"/>
                        “Simon,” he said to Peter, “are you asleep? Couldn't <lb n="6"/> you keep
                        watch for one hour?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Watch and pray so that you will not fall into temptation. <lb n="7"/> The
                        spirit is willing, but the flesh <lb n="8"/> is weak.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>Once more he went away and prayed the <lb n="9"/> same thing.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>When he came back, he again found <lb n="10"/> them sleeping, because their
                        eyes were heavy. <lb n="11"/> They did not know what to say to him. <lb
                            n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Returning the third time, he said to them, “Are you still sleeping and
                        resting? <lb n="13"/> Enough! The hour has come. Look, the Son of <lb n="14"
                        /> Man is delivered into the hands of sinners.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Rise! Let us <lb n="15"/> go! Here comes my betrayer!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Just as he <lb n="16"/> was speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, appeared.
                        With <lb n="17"/> him was a crowd armed with swords and clubs, sent from the
                        chief priests <lb n="18"/>, the teachers of the law, and the elders. <lb
                            n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>Now the betrayer had arranged a signal with them: <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="103v"/> “The one I kiss is the man; arrest <lb n="1"/> him and lead
                        him away under guard.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>Going at once to <lb n="2"/> Jesus, Judas said, “Rabbi!” and kissed <lb n="3"
                        /> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>The men seized Jesus <lb n="4"/> and arrested him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>Then one <lb n="5"/> of those standing near drew his sword <lb n="6"/> and
                        struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his ear. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>“Am I leading a rebellion,” said Jesus, “that you <lb n="8"/> have come out
                        with swords and clubs to capture <lb n="9"/> me?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>Every day I was with you, teaching in the temple courts <lb n="10"/>, and you
                        did not arrest me. But the <lb n="11"/> Scriptures must be fulfilled.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>Then everyone deserted <lb n="12"/> him and fled.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>A young man, wearing <lb n="13"/> nothing but a linen garment, was following
                        Jesus. <lb n="14"/> When they seized him,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>he fled naked, <lb n="15"/> leaving his garment behind.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="53" type="verse">
                    <p>They took Jesus to the high priest <lb n="16"/> , and all the chief priests,
                        the elders and the teachers <lb n="17"/> of the law came together. <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="54" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter followed him at a distance, right into the courtyard of <lb n="19"/>
                        the high priest. There he sat with the guards and warmed himself <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="104v"/> at the fire.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="55" type="verse">
                    <p>The chief priests and the whole <lb n="1"/> Sanhedrin were looking for
                        evidence against Jesus so that they could put him to death, but they did not
                        find any. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="56" type="verse">
                    <p>Many testified falsely against him, but their <lb n="3"/> statements did not
                        agree.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="57" type="verse">
                    <p>Then some <lb n="4"/> stood up and gave this false testimony <lb n="5"/>
                        against him:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="58" type="verse">
                    <p>“We heard him say, <lb n="6"/> 'I will destroy this temple made with human
                        hands <lb n="7"/> and in three days will build another, not made <lb n="8"/>
                        with hands.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="59" type="verse">
                    <p>Yet even then their testimony did not <lb n="9"/> agree.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="60" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the high priest stood up before them <lb n="10"/> and asked Jesus, “Are
                        you not going to answer? <lb n="11"/> What is this testimony that these men
                        are bringing against you?” <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="61" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus remained silent and <lb n="13"/> gave no answer. Again the high
                        priest asked him, <lb n="14"/> “Are you the Messiah, the Son of the Blessed
                        One?” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="62" type="verse">
                    <p>“I am,” said Jesus. “And you will see the Son of Man sitting <lb n="16"/> at
                        the right hand of the Mighty One and coming on the clouds of heaven.” <lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="63" type="verse">
                    <p>The high priest tore his clothes. <lb n="18"/> “Why do we need any more
                        witnesses?” he asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="64" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have heard <lb n="19"/> the blasphemy. What do you think?” <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="104r"/> They all condemned him as worthy of death. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="65" type="verse">
                    <p>Then some began to spit at <lb n="2"/> him; they blindfolded him, struck him
                            <lb n="3"/> with their fists, and said, “Prophesy!” And the guards took
                            <lb n="4"/> him and beat him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="66" type="verse">
                    <p>While Peter was below in the courtyard, <lb n="5"/> one of the servant girls
                        of the high priest came by. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="67" type="verse">
                    <p>When she saw Peter warming himself, she looked closely <lb n="7"/> at him.
                        “You also were with that Nazarene, Jesus,” <lb n="8"/> she said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="68" type="verse">
                    <p>But he denied it. “I don't know <lb n="9"/> or understand what you're talking
                        about,” he said, <lb n="10"/> and went out into the entryway.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="69" type="verse">
                    <p>When the servant girl saw <lb n="11"/> him there, she said again to those
                        standing around, <lb n="12"/> “This fellow is one of them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="70" type="verse">
                    <p>Again he denied it. <lb n="13"/> After a little while, those standing near
                        said to <lb n="14"/> Peter, “Surely you are one of them, for you are a
                        Galilean.” <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="71" type="verse">
                    <p>He began to call down curses, and he swore to them, <lb n="16"/> “I don't
                        know this man you're talking about.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="72" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately <lb n="17"/> the rooster crowed the second time. Then Peter <lb
                            n="18"/> remembered the word Jesus had spoken to him: “Before the
                        rooster <lb n="19"/> crows twice you will disown me three times.” And he
                        broke down and wept. <lb n="20"/>
                        <lb n="105v"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Very early in the morning, <lb n="1"/> the chief priests, with the elders,
                        the teachers of the law and <lb n="2"/> the whole Sanhedrin, made their
                        plans. So they bound Jesus, led him away <lb n="3"/> and handed him over to
                        Pilate.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“Are you the king of the Jews?” <lb n="4"/> asked Pilate. “You have said so,”
                            <lb n="5"/> Jesus replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>The chief priests accused <lb n="6"/> him of many things. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>So again Pilate asked him, <lb n="8"/> “Aren't you going to answer? See how
                        many things they are <lb n="9"/> accusing you of.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus still made no <lb n="10"/> reply, and Pilate was amazed. <lb n="11"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Now it was the custom at the festival to release <lb n="12"/> a prisoner whom
                        the people requested. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>A man called Barabbas was in prison <lb n="14"/> with the insurrectionists
                        who had committed murder in <lb n="15"/> the uprising.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>The crowd <lb n="16"/> came up and asked Pilate to do for them what he
                        usually did.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do you <lb n="17"/> want me to release to you <lb n="18"/> the king of the
                        Jews?” <lb n="19"/> asked Pilate,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>knowing it <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="105v"/> was out of self-interest that the <lb n="1"/> chief priests
                        had handed Jesus over to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>But the chief priests <lb n="2"/> stirred up the crowd to have Pilate release
                        Barabbas instead. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>“What shall I do, then, with the one <lb n="4"/> you call the king of the
                        Jews?” Pilate <lb n="5"/> asked them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“Crucify him!” <lb n="6"/> they shouted.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p><hi rend="italic"> “Why? What crime has he committed?” asked Pilate. But they
                            shouted all the louder, ”Crucify him!”</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not found in Latin
                            Vulgate.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Wanting to satisfy the crowd, <lb n="7"/> Pilate released Barabbas to them.
                            <lb n="8"/> He had Jesus flogged, and handed him over to be crucified.
                            <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>The soldiers led Jesus away into the palace <lb n="10"/> (that is, the
                        Praetorium) and called together the whole company of soldiers.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>They put <lb n="11"/> a purple robe on him, then twisted together a crown of
                        thorns and <lb n="12"/> set it on him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>And they began to call out <lb n="13"/> to him, “Hail, king of the Jews!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Again and again they struck him on the head <lb n="14"/> with a staff and
                        spit on him. <lb n="15"/> Falling on their knees, they paid homage to him.
                            <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>And when they had mocked him, they took off <lb n="17"/> the purple robe and
                        put his own clothes on him. <lb n="18"/> Then they led him out to crucify
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>A certain man from <lb n="19"/> Cyrene, Simon, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="106r"/> the father of Alexander and Rufus, <lb n="1"/> was passing by
                        on his way in from the country, and they forced him to carry the cross.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>They brought Jesus <lb n="2"/> to the place called Golgotha which means <lb
                            n="3"/> “the place of the skull”.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Then they offered him wine <lb n="4"/> mixed with myrrh, but he did not take
                        it. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>And they crucified him. Dividing up his clothes <lb n="6"/>, they cast lots
                        to see what each would get. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>It was nine in the morning when they crucified him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The written notice of the charge against him read: THE KING <lb n="9"/> OF
                        THE JEWS.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>They crucified two rebels <lb n="10"/> with him, one on his right and one on
                        his left. <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate
                            but not in the NIV translation. </note><lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Those who passed by hurled <lb n="13"/> insults at him, shaking their heads
                            <lb n="14"/> and saying, “So! You who are going to destroy the temple
                            <lb n="15"/> and build it in three days,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>come down <lb n="16"/> from the cross and save yourself!” <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way the chief priests and <lb n="18"/> the teachers of the law
                        mocked him among themselves. “He saved others,” they said, <lb n="19"/> “but
                        he can't save himself!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Let this Messiah, this king <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="106v"/> of Israel, come down now from the cross, that we may see <lb
                            n="1"/> and believe.” Those crucified with him also heaped insults on
                            <lb n="2"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>At noon, darkness <lb n="3"/> came over the whole land until three in the <lb
                            n="4"/> afternoon.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p> And at three in the afternoon <lb n="5"/> Jesus cried out in a loud voice,
                        “Eloi, Eloi, lema sabachthani?” (which means <lb n="6"/> “My God, my God,
                        why have you forsaken <lb n="7"/> me?”).</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>When some of those standing near heard this, they said, <lb n="8"/> “Listen,
                        he's calling Elijah.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Someone ran, <lb n="9"/> filled a sponge with wine vinegar, <lb n="10"/> put
                        it on a staff, and offered it to Jesus to drink. <lb n="11"/> “Now leave him
                        alone. Let's see if Elijah comes to take <lb n="12"/> him down,” he
                        said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>With a loud cry, Jesus breathed his last. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>The curtain of the temple was torn in two <lb n="14"/> from top to bottom.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>And when <lb n="15"/> the centurion, who stood there in front of Jesus, saw
                        how he died <lb n="16"/>, he said, “Surely this man was the Son <lb n="17"/>
                        of God!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>Some women were watching from a distance. <lb n="18"/> Among them were Mary
                        Magdalene, <lb n="19"/> Mary the mother of James the younger and of Joseph,
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="107r"/> and Salome.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>In Galilee these women had followed <lb n="1"/> him and cared for his needs.
                        Many <lb n="2"/> other women who had come up with him to Jerusalem were also
                        there. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>It was Preparation Day (that is, <lb n="4"/> the day before the Sabbath). So
                        as evening approached, <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent <lb n="6"/> member of the Council, who was
                        himself waiting for the kingdom <lb n="7"/> of God, went boldly to Pilate
                        and asked for <lb n="8"/> Jesus' body.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>Pilate was surprised to hear that he was already <lb n="9"/> dead. Summoning
                        the centurion, he asked <lb n="10"/> him if Jesus had already died.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>When he learned <lb n="11"/> from the centurion that it was so, he gave the
                        body to Joseph. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>So Joseph bought some linen cloth, took down the body, <lb n="13"/> wrapped
                        it in the linen, and placed it in a tomb <lb n="14"/> cut out of rock. Then
                        he rolled <lb n="15"/> a stone against the entrance of the tomb. <lb n="16"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother <lb n="17"/> of Joseph saw where he was
                        laid.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>When the <lb n="18"/> Sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother <lb
                            n="19"/> of James, and Salome bought spices so that they might go to <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="107v"/> anoint Jesus' body.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Very early on the first day <lb n="1"/> of the week, just after sunrise, they
                        were on their <lb n="2"/> way to the tomb</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>and they asked each other, “Who will roll the stone away <lb n="3"/> from the
                        entrance of the tomb?” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>But when they looked up, they saw that the stone <lb n="5"/>, which was very
                        large, had been rolled <lb n="6"/> away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>As they entered the tomb, they saw <lb n="7"/> a young man dressed in a white
                        robe sitting on the right side, <lb n="8"/> and they were alarmed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“Don't be alarmed,” he said. <lb n="9"/> “You are looking for Jesus the
                        Nazarene, who was crucified. <lb n="10"/> He has risen! He is not here. See
                        the place where they laid <lb n="11"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>But go, tell his disciples and <lb n="12"/> Peter, 'He is going ahead of you
                        into Galilee. There <lb n="13"/> you will see him, just as he told
                        you.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Trembling and bewildered <lb n="14"/>, the women went out and fled from the
                        tomb. <lb n="15"/> They said nothing to anyone, <lb n="16"/> because they
                        were afraid.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus rose early on the first day of the week <lb n="17"/>, he appeared
                        first to Mary Magdalene, <lb n="18"/> out of whom he had driven seven
                        demons.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>She went <lb n="19"/> and told those who had been with him and who were
                        mourning <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="108r"/> and weeping</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>When they heard that <lb n="1"/> Jesus was alive and that she had seen him,
                            <lb n="2"/> they did not believe it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Afterward Jesus appeared in a different form to two of them while they were
                        walking <lb n="3"/> in the country.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>These returned <lb n="4"/> and reported it to the rest; but they did not
                        believe them either. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Later Jesus appeared to the Eleven <lb n="6"/> as they were eating; he
                        rebuked them for their lack of faith <lb n="7"/> and their stubborn refusal
                            <lb n="8"/> to believe those who had seen him after he had risen. <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, “Go into all <lb n="10"/> the world and preach the gospel to
                        all <lb n="11"/> creation.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever believes and is baptized will be <lb n="12"/> saved, but whoever does
                        not believe will be condemned. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>And these signs will accompany those who believe: <lb n="14"/> In my name
                        they will drive out demons; they will <lb n="15"/> speak in new tongues;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>they will pick up snakes with their hands; <lb n="16"/> and when they drink
                        deadly poison, it will not hurt them at all; they will place their <lb
                            n="17"/> hands on sick people, and they will <lb n="18"/> get well.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>After the Lord Jesus had spoken to them, <lb n="19"/> he was taken up into
                        heaven and he sat <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="108v"/> at the right hand of God.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the disciples went out and preached <lb n="1"/> everywhere, and the Lord
                        worked with them and confirmed his word by <lb n="2"/> the signs that
                        accompanied it.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
