<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="tei-analysis.rng" type="xml"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="chs-gp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Saint Chad Gospels</title>
                <editor xml:id="bh">Bonnie Lewis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>A new transcription from digital imagery, with semantic markup, based on
                    digital images captured by the University of Kentucky’s Center for Visualization
                    and Virtual Environments, Brent Seales, Director. The images are copyrighted by
                    the Chapter of Lichfield Cathedral, 2010, and are released under a Creative
                    Commons License. This material is based upon work supported by the National
                    Science Foundation under Grants No. 0916148 &amp; No. 0916421. Any opinions,
                    findings and conclusions or recomendations expressed in this material are those
                    of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National
                    Science Foundation (NSF).</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name>Bonnie Lewis, Tony Brown, Christopher Blackwell, Brent Seales edd.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>under 1Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> The Center for Hellenic Studies of Harvard University </publisher>
                <authority>
                    <name>Casey Dué and Mary Ebbott, edd.</name>
                </authority>
                <availability>
                    <p> ©2012, Bonnie Lewis. This work is made available under the Creative Commons
                        Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States License:
                        http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/ </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p> File created electronically. </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="xgrc">Transliterated Greek</language>
                <language ident="deu">German</language>
                <language ident="fra">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>This is the <lb n="1"/> genealogy <lb n="2"/> of Jesus the Messiah <lb n="3"
                        /> the son of David, <lb n="4"/>
                        <pb n="1r"/> the son of Abraham</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Abraham was <lb n="1"/> the father of Isaac, Isaac the father of Jacob, <lb
                            n="2"/> Jacob the father of Judah and <lb n="3"/> his brothers,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Judah the father <lb n="4"/> of Perez and Zerah, whose mother was Tamar,
                        Perez <lb n="5"/> the father of Hezron, Hezron <lb n="6"/> the father of
                        Ram,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Ram the father of <lb n="7"/> Amminadab, Amminadab the father of <lb n="8"/>
                        Nahshon, Nahshon the father of <lb n="9"/> Salmon,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Salmon the father <lb n="10"/> of Boaz, whose mother was Rahab, Boaz the
                        father <lb n="11"/> of Obed, whose mother was Ruth, Obed the father <lb
                            n="12"/> of Jesse,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>and Jesse the father of King <lb n="13"/> David. David was the father of
                        Solomon, <lb n="14"/> whose mother had been Uriah's wife, <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Solomon the father of Rehoboam, <lb n="16"/>
                        <pb n="1v"/> Rehoboam the father of Abijah, <lb n="1"/> Abijah the father of
                        Asa, <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Asa the father of Jehoshaphat, <lb n="3"/> Jehoshaphat the father of Jehoram,
                            <lb n="4"/> Jehoram the father of Uzziah, <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Uzziah the father of Jotham, <lb n="6"/> Jotham the father of Ahaz, <lb n="7"
                        /> Ahaz the father of Hezekiah, <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Hezekiah the father of Manasseh, <lb n="9"/> Manasseh the father of Amon, <lb
                            n="10"/> Amon the father of Josiah, <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>and Josiah the father of Jeconiah <lb n="12"/> and his brothers <lb n="13"/>
                        at the time of the exile <lb n="14"/> to Babylon.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>After the exile <lb n="15"/> to Babylon: Jeconiah <lb n="16"/>
                        <pb n="2r"/> was the father of Shealtiel, <lb n="1"/> Shealtiel the father
                        of Zerubbabel, <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Zerubbabel the father of <lb n="3"/> Abihud, Abihud the father of <lb n="4"/>
                        Eliakim, Eliakim the father of <lb n="5"/> Azor,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Azor the father of <lb n="6"/> Zadok, Zadok the father of <lb n="7"/> Akim,
                        Akim the father of <lb n="8"/> Elihud,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Elihud the father of <lb n="9"/> Eleazar, Eleazar the father of <lb n="10"/>
                        Matthan, Matthan the <lb n="11"/> father of Jacob,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p> and Jacob <lb n="12"/> the father of Joseph, the husband of Mary, <lb n="13"
                        /> and Mary was the mother of Jesus <lb n="14"/> who is called the
                        Messiah.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Thus there were fourteen <lb n="15"/> generations in all from Abraham <lb
                            n="16"/>
                        <pb n="2v"/><hi rend="italic"> to David, fourteen from David to the exile to
                            Babylon, and fourteen from the exile to the Messiah. </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p><hi rend="italic"> This is how the birth of Jesus the Messiah came
                            about:</hi>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> Italicized text not found in the Latin
                            Vulgate.</note> His mother Mary was pledged to be married to Joseph, <lb
                            n="1"/> but before they came together, she was found <lb n="2"/> to be
                        pregnant through the Holy Spirit. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Because Joseph <lb n="3"/> her husband was faithful to the law, <lb n="4"/>
                        and yet did not want to expose her to public disgrace, he had in mind <lb
                            n="5"/> to divorce her quietly.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>But after he had considered <lb n="6"/> this, an angel of the Lord appeared
                        to him in a dream and <lb n="7"/> said, “Joseph son of David, do not <lb
                            n="8"/> be afraid to take Mary home as your wife, <lb n="9"/> because
                        what is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>She will give birth to a son, and you are to give him the name <lb n="11"/>
                        Jesus, because he will save his people <lb n="12"/> from their sins.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>All this took <lb n="13"/> place to fulfill <lb n="14"/> what the Lord had
                        said through the <lb n="15"/> prophet:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“The virgin will conceive <lb n="16"/> and give birth to a son, and they will
                        call <lb n="17"/> him Immanuel” which means <lb n="18"/> "God with us."</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="19"/> Joseph woke up, he did what <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="3v"/> the angel of the Lord had commanded him and took Mary home as
                            <lb n="1"/> his wife.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>But he did not consummate their <lb n="2"/> marriage until she gave birth to
                        a son <lb n="3"/>. And he gave him the name Jesus. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>After Jesus was born in Bethlehem <lb n="5"/> in Judea, during the time of
                        King Herod, Magi from the east <lb n="6"/> came to Jerusalem</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>and asked, <lb n="7"/> “Where is the one who has been born king of the Jews?
                        We saw <lb n="8"/> his star when it rose and <lb n="9"/> have come to
                        worship him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="10"/> King Herod heard this he was disturbed, and all Jerusalem
                            <lb n="11"/> with him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>When he had called together all the people's <lb n="12"/> chief priests and
                        teachers of the law, <lb n="13"/> he asked them where the Messiah <lb n="14"
                        /> was to be born.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“In Bethlehem in Judea,” they replied <lb n="15"/>, “for this is what the
                        prophet has written: <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“'But you, Bethlehem, in the land of Judah, <lb n="17"/> are by no means
                        least among the rulers of Judah; for out <lb n="18"/> of you will come a
                        ruler who will shepherd my people <lb n="19"/> Israel.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Herod called <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="4r"/> the Magi secretly and found out from them the exact time <lb
                            n="1"/> the star had appeared.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>He sent <lb n="2"/> them to Bethlehem and said, “Go and search <lb n="3"/>
                        carefully for the child. As soon as you find him, <lb n="4"/> report to me,
                        so that I too may go and worship <lb n="5"/> him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>After they had heard the king, they went on their way, <lb n="6"/> and the
                        star they had seen when it rose went <lb n="7"/> ahead of them until it <lb
                            n="8"/> stopped over the place where the child was.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="9"/> they saw the star, they were <lb n="10"/> overjoyed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>On coming to the house, they saw <lb n="11"/> the child with his mother Mary
                            <lb n="12"/>, and they bowed down and worshiped him. <lb n="13"/> Then
                        they opened their treasures and presented <lb n="14"/> him with gifts of
                        gold, frankincense and myrrh.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>And having been <lb n="15"/> warned in a dream not to go back <lb n="16"/> to
                        Herod, they returned to their country <lb n="17"/> by another route.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had gone, <lb n="18"/> an angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph <lb
                            n="19"/> in a dream. “Get up,” he said, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="4v"/> ”take the child and his mother and escape <lb n="1"/> to Egypt.
                        Stay there until I tell <lb n="2"/> you, for Herod is going to search for
                            <lb n="3"/> the child to kill him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="4"/> he got up, took the child and his mother during <lb n="5"/>
                        the night and left for Egypt,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>where he stayed <lb n="6"/> until the death of Herod. And so was fulfilled
                            <lb n="7"/> what the Lord had said through the prophet: <lb n="8"/> ”Out
                        of Egypt I called my son.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="9"/> Herod realized that he had been outwitted <lb n="10"/> by
                        the Magi, he was furious, and he gave <lb n="11"/> orders to kill all the
                        boys <lb n="12"/> in Bethlehem and its vicinity who <lb n="13"/> were two
                        years old and under, in accordance with the time <lb n="14"/> he had learned
                        from the Magi.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Then what was said <lb n="15"/> through the prophet Jeremiah <lb n="16"/> was
                        fulfilled:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“A voice is heard in Ramah, <lb n="17"/> weeping and great mourning, Rachel
                            <lb n="18"/> weeping for her children and refusing to be comforted, <lb
                            n="19"/> because they are no more.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>After Herod died, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="5r"/> an angel of the Lord appeared in <lb n="1"/> a dream to Joseph
                        in Egypt</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>and said, “Get up <lb n="2"/>, take the child and his mother and go <lb n="3"
                        /> to the land of Israel, <lb n="4"/> for those who were trying to take the
                        child's life are dead.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="5"/> he got up, took the child and his mother <lb n="6"/> and went
                        to the land of Israel.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>But <lb n="7"/> when he heard that Archelaus was reigning in Judea <lb n="8"
                        /> in place of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there. <lb n="9"/>
                        Having been warned in a dream, he withdrew to the district <lb n="10"/> of
                        Galilee,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>and he went and lived in a town <lb n="11"/> called Nazareth. So was
                        fulfilled <lb n="12"/> what was said through the prophets, <lb n="13"/> that
                        he would be called a Nazarene.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>In those days John <lb n="14"/> the Baptist <lb n="15"/> came, preaching in
                        the wilderness of Judea</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>and saying, <lb n="16"/> “Repent, for the kingdom of <lb n="17"/> heaven has
                        come near.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>This is <lb n="18"/> he who was spoken of through the prophet Isaiah: <lb
                            n="19"/> “A voice of one calling in the wilderness, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="5v"/>'Prepare the way for the Lord, make <lb n="1"/> straight paths
                        for him.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>John's clothes were made <lb n="2"/> of camel's hair, <lb n="3"/> and he had
                        a leather belt around <lb n="4"/> his waist. His food was locusts and <lb
                            n="5"/> wild honey.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>People went out to him from Jerusalem <lb n="6"/> and all Judea and the whole
                        region of the <lb n="7"/> Jordan.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Confessing their sins, they <lb n="8"/> were baptized by him in the Jordan
                        River. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>But when he saw many of the Pharisees and <lb n="10"/> Sadducees coming to
                        where he was baptizing, <lb n="11"/> he said to them: “You brood of vipers!
                            <lb n="12"/> Who warned you to flee from the coming <lb n="13"/>
                        wrath?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Produce fruit in keeping with repentance. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>And do not think you can say to yourselves, <lb n="15"/> 'We have Abraham as
                        our father.' I tell you <lb n="16"/> that out of these stones God can <lb
                            n="17"/> raise up children for Abraham.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>The ax is already <lb n="18"/> at the root of the trees, <lb n="19"/> and
                        every tree that does not produce good <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="6r"/> fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire. <lb n="1"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>“I baptize you with water for repentance. <lb n="2"/> But after me comes one
                        who is more powerful than <lb n="3"/> I, whose sandals I am not worthy to
                        carry. <lb n="4"/> He will baptize you with <lb n="5"/> the Holy Spirit and
                        fire.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>His winnowing fork is in <lb n="6"/> his hand, and he will clear his
                        threshing floor, <lb n="7"/> gathering his <lb n="8"/> wheat into the barn
                        and burning up the chaff with unquenchable fire.” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan <lb n="10"/> to be baptized by
                        John. <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>But John tried to deter him, saying, <lb n="12"/> “I need to be baptized by
                        you, and do you come <lb n="13"/> to me?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “Let it be <lb n="14"/> so now; it is proper for us to do this
                        to fulfill all righteousness.” <lb n="15"/> Then John consented.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>As soon as Jesus was baptized <lb n="16"/>, he went up out of the water. At
                        that moment heaven was <lb n="17"/> opened, and he saw the Spirit of God
                        descending <lb n="18"/> like a dove and alighting <lb n="19"/> on him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>And a voice from heaven said, “This is <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="6v"/> my Son, whom I love; with him I am well pleased.” <lb n="1"
                        /></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus was led by <lb n="2"/> the Spirit into the wilderness to be
                        tempted by the devil.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>After fasting <lb n="3"/> forty days and forty nights, he was <lb n="4"/>
                        hungry.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>The tempter came to him <lb n="5"/> and said, “If you are the Son of God,
                        tell these stones <lb n="6"/> to become bread.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered, “It is written: <lb n="7"/> 'Man shall not live on bread
                        alone, <lb n="8"/> but on every word that comes <lb n="9"/> from the mouth
                        of God.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the devil took him <lb n="10"/> to the holy city and had him stand <lb
                            n="11"/> on the highest point of the temple.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“If <lb n="12"/> you are the Son of God,” he said, “throw yourself down. For
                        it is written: <lb n="13"/> “'He will command his angels concerning you, and
                            <lb n="14"/> they will lift you up in their hands, so that you will not
                            <lb n="15"/> strike your foot against a stone.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus <lb n="16"/> answered him, “It is also written: 'Do not <lb n="17"/>
                        put the Lord your God to the test.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Again, the devil took <lb n="18"/> him to a very high mountain <lb n="19"/>
                        and showed him all the kingdoms of the world <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="7r"/> and their splendor.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“All this I will give you,” <lb n="1"/> he said, “if you will bow down and
                        worship me.” <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to him, “Away from me, Satan! <lb n="3"/> For it is written:
                        'Worship the Lord your God, <lb n="4"/> and serve him only.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the devil left <lb n="5"/> him, and angels came <lb n="6"/> and attended
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="7"/> Jesus heard that John had been put in prison, <lb n="8"/> he
                        withdrew to Galilee.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Leaving <lb n="9"/> Nazareth, he went and lived in Capernaum, <lb n="10"/>
                        which was by the lake in the area of Zebulun <lb n="11"/> and Naphtali</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>to fulfill what <lb n="12"/> was said through the prophet Isaiah: <lb n="13"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, <lb n="14"/> the Way of the Sea,
                        beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>the people living in darkness have seen <lb n="16"/> a great light; on those
                        living <lb n="17"/> in the land of the shadow of death a light has dawned.”
                            <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>From that time on Jesus began to preach, <lb n="19"/> “Repent, for the
                        kingdom <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="7v"/> of heaven has come near.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus was walking <lb n="1"/> beside the Sea of Galilee, he saw two
                        brothers, <lb n="2"/> Simon called Peter and his brother Andrew. <lb n="3"/>
                        They were casting a net into the lake, <lb n="4"/> for they were
                        fishermen.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“Come, follow me,” Jesus said, <lb n="5"/> “and I will send you out to fish
                        for <lb n="6"/> people.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>At once they left their <lb n="7"/> nets and followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Going on from <lb n="8"/> there, he saw two other brothers, James son of <lb
                            n="9"/> Zebedee and his brother John. They were in a boat <lb n="10"/>
                        with their father Zebedee, preparing their nets. <lb n="11"/> Jesus called
                        them,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>and immediately they <lb n="12"/> left the boat and their father and followed
                            <lb n="13"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus went throughout Galilee, <lb n="14"/> teaching in their synagogues,
                        proclaiming <lb n="15"/> the good news of the kingdom, and healing every
                        disease <lb n="16"/> and sickness among the people. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>News about him spread all over Syria, and people brought <lb n="18"/> to him
                        all who were ill with <lb n="19"/> various diseases, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="8r"/> those suffering severe pain, the demon-possessed, those having
                        seizures, <lb n="1"/> and the paralyzed; and he healed them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="2"/> Large crowds from Galilee, <lb n="3"/> the Decapolis, Jerusalem,
                        Judea <lb n="4"/> and the region across the Jordan followed him.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Now when Jesus saw <lb n="5"/> the crowds, he went up on a mountainside and
                        sat down. <lb n="6"/> His disciples came to him, <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>and he began to teach them. He said: <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>“Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom <lb n="9"/> of
                        heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are those who mourn, for they will <lb n="10"/> be comforted. <lb
                            n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are the meek, for they will inherit the earth. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for <lb n="13"/> righteousness, for
                        they will be filled. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are the merciful, for they will <lb n="15"/> be shown mercy.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are the pure in heart, for <lb n="16"/> they will see God. <lb n="17"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are the peacemakers, for they will be called children of God. <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed are those who are persecuted <lb n="19"/> because of righteousness,
                        for theirs <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="8v"/> is the kingdom of heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>“Blessed are you <lb n="1"/> when people insult you, persecute <lb n="2"/>you
                        and falsely say all kinds of evil <lb n="3"/> against you because <lb n="4 "
                        /> of me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Rejoice and be glad, because great <lb n="5"/> is your reward in heaven, for
                            <lb n="6"/> in the same way they persecuted the prophets who were before
                            <lb n="7"/> you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“You are the salt of the earth. <lb n="8"/> But if the salt loses its
                        saltiness, how can it be made salty again? <lb n="9"/> It is no longer good
                        for anything, except to be thrown <lb n="10"/> out and trampled
                        underfoot.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>“You are <lb n="11"/> the light of the world. A town built <lb n="12"/> on a
                        hill cannot be hidden.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Neither do people <lb n="13"/> light a lamp and put it under a bowl. Instead
                            <lb n="14"/> they put it on its stand, and it gives light to <lb n="15"
                        /> everyone in the house.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way, let your light shine before <lb n="16"/> others, that they
                        may see your <lb n="17"/> good deeds and glorify your Father <lb n="18"/> in
                        heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not think <lb n="19"/> that I have come to abolish the Law or the
                        Prophets; <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="9r"/> I have not come to abolish them but to fulfill them. <lb n="1"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>For truly I tell you, until <lb n="2"/> heaven and earth disappear, not the
                        smallest letter, not the least stroke of a pen, will by any <lb n="3"/>
                        means disappear from the Law until <lb n="4"/> everything is
                        accomplished.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore anyone who sets aside one <lb n="5"/> of the least of these
                        commands and teaches <lb n="6"/> others accordingly will be called least in
                        the kingdom <lb n="7"/> of heaven, but whoever practices and teaches <lb
                            n="8"/> these commands will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.
                            <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>For I tell you that unless your <lb n="10"/> righteousness surpasses that of
                        the Pharisees <lb n="11"/> and the teachers of the law, you will certainly
                        not enter <lb n="12"/> the kingdom of heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have heard that it was said <lb n="13"/> to the people long ago, 'You
                        shall not murder, and anyone who murders <lb n="14"/> will be subject to
                        judgment.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you that <lb n="15"/> anyone who is angry with a brother or sister
                            <lb n="16"/> will be subject to judgment. Again, anyone who says to a
                        brother or sister, <lb n="17"/> 'Raca,' is answerable to the court. And
                        anyone who <lb n="18"/> says, 'You fool!' will be in danger of the fire of
                        hell.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore, if <lb n="19"/> you are offering your gift at the altar <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="9v"/> and there remember that your brother or sister <lb n="1"/> has
                        something against you,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>leave <lb n="2"/> your gift there in front of the altar. First go <lb n="3"/>
                        and be reconciled to them; then <lb n="4"/> come and offer your gift.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“Settle matters quickly with <lb n="5"/> your adversary who is taking you to
                        court. Do it while you are still together <lb n="6"/> on the way, or your
                        adversary may hand you over to <lb n="7"/> the judge, and the judge may hand
                        you over to the officer, <lb n="8"/> and you may be thrown into prison.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you <lb n="9"/>, you will not get out until you have paid <lb
                            n="10"/> the last penny.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have heard that it was said, <lb n="11"/> 'You shall not commit
                        adultery.' <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you that anyone who <lb n="13"/> looks at a woman lustfully has
                            <lb n="14"/> already committed adultery with her in his heart.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>If <lb n="15"/> your right eye causes you to stumble, <lb n="16"/> gouge it
                        out and throw it away. It is better for <lb n="17"/> you to lose one part of
                            <lb n="18"/> your body than for your whole body <lb n="19"/> to be
                        thrown into hell.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>And if your right hand <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="10r"/> causes you to stumble, cut it off <lb n="1"/> and throw it
                        away. It is better for you to lose <lb n="2"/> one part of your body than
                        for <lb n="3"/> your whole body to go into hell. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>“It has been said, 'Anyone who divorces <lb n="5"/> his wife must give her a
                        certificate of divorce.' <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you that anyone who <lb n="7"/> divorces his wife, except for
                        sexual immorality <lb n="8"/>, makes her the victim of adultery, and <lb
                            n="9"/> anyone who marries a divorced woman commits adultery.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“Again <lb n="10"/>, you have heard that it was said to the people long ago,
                        'Do not <lb n="11"/> break your oath, but fulfill to the Lord the vows you
                        have <lb n="12"/> made.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you, do not <lb n="13"/> swear an oath at all: either by heaven,
                            <lb n="14"/> for it is God's throne;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>or by the earth, for it is his <lb n="15"/> footstool; or by <lb n="16"/>
                        Jerusalem, for it is the city of the Great <lb n="17"/> King.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>And do not swear by your head, <lb n="18"/> for you cannot make even one hair
                            <lb n="19"/> white or black.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>All you need <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="10v"/> to say is simply 'Yes' or 'No'; anything beyond <lb n="1"/>
                        this comes from the evil one.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have heard <lb n="2"/> that it was said, 'Eye for eye, and tooth <lb
                            n="3"/> for tooth.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you, do not <lb n="4"/> resist an evil person. If anyone slaps <lb
                            n="5"/> you on the right cheek, turn to <lb n="7"/> them the other cheek
                        also.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>And if anyone wants to <lb n="8"/> sue you and take your shirt, hand over
                        your <lb n="9"/> coat as well.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone <lb n="10"/> forces you to go one mile, go <lb n="11"/> with them
                        two miles.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Give to the one who asks <lb n="12"/> you, and do not turn away from the one
                        who wants to borrow from you. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have heard that it was said, 'Love your neighbor <lb n="14"/> and hate
                        your enemy.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>But I <lb n="15"/> tell you, love your enemies <lb n="16"/> and pray for
                        those who persecute <lb n="17"/> you,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>that you may be children of your Father <lb n="18"/> in heaven. He causes his
                        sun <lb n="19"/> to rise on the evil and the good, and sends rain on the <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="11r"/> righteous and the unrighteous.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>If you love <lb n="1"/> those who love you, what reward will you get? <lb
                            n="2"/> Are not even the tax collectors doing that? <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>And if you greet only your own people <lb n="4"/>, what are you doing more
                        than others? <lb n="5"/> Do not even pagans do that?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>Be <lb n="6"/> perfect, therefore, as your heavenly Father <lb n="7"/> is
                        perfect.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>“Be careful not to practice <lb n="8"/> your righteousness in front of others
                        to be <lb n="9"/> seen by them. If you do, you will have <lb n="10"/> no
                        reward from your Father <lb n="11"/> in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“So when you give to the needy <lb n="12"/>, do not announce it with
                        trumpets, <lb n="13"/> as the hypocrites do in the synagogues <lb n="14"/>
                        and on the streets, to be honored by others. <lb n="15"/> Truly I tell you,
                        they have received their <lb n="16"/> reward in full.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>But when you give <lb n="17"/> to the needy, do not let your left hand know
                        what <lb n="18"/> your right hand is doing,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>so that your giving <lb n="19"/> may be in secret. Then your Father, who sees
                        what is done in secret, will reward you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“And when you pray, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="11v"/> do not be like the hypocrites, for they love <lb n="1"/> to
                        pray standing in the synagogues and on <lb n="2"/> the street corners to be
                        seen by others. <lb n="3"/> Truly I tell you, they have received their
                        reward in <lb n="4"/> full.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>But when you pray, go <lb n="5"/> into your room, close the door and pray to
                            <lb n="6"/> your Father, who is unseen. Then your Father, <lb n="7"/>
                        who sees what is done in secret, will reward you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>And when you pray, do not keep on babbling like <lb n="8"/> pagans, <lb n="9"
                        /> for they think they will be heard because of their many <lb n="10"/>
                        words.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Do not be like <lb n="11"/> them, for your Father knows what <lb n="12"/> you
                        need before you ask him. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“This, then, is how you should pray: “'Our Father in heaven, <lb n="14"/>
                        hallowed be your name, <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>your kingdom come, your will be done, <lb n="16"/> on earth as it is in
                        heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Give us today <lb n="17"/> our daily bread.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>And forgive <lb n="18"/> us our debts, as we also have forgiven <lb n="19"/>
                        our debtors.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>And lead us not <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="12r"/> into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.'<lb n="1"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>For if you forgive other people <lb n="2"/> when they sin against you, your
                        heavenly Father <lb n="3"/> will also forgive you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>But if <lb n="4"/> you do not forgive others their sins, your Father <lb
                            n="5"/> will not forgive your sins. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“When you fast, do not look somber as the hypocrites <lb n="7"/> do, for they
                        disfigure their faces <lb n="8"/> to show others they are fasting. <lb n="9"
                        /> Truly I tell you, they have received their reward in <lb n="10"/>
                        full.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>But when you fast, put oil on <lb n="11"/> your head and wash your face,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>so that it will <lb n="12"/> not be obvious to others that you are fasting,
                        but only to your Father, <lb n="13"/> who is unseen; and your Father, who
                        sees what is done in secret, will reward you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not store up <lb n="14"/> for yourselves treasures on earth, <lb n="15"/>
                        where moths and vermin destroy, and where <lb n="16"/> thieves break in and
                        steal.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>But store up <lb n="17"/> for yourselves treasures in heaven, where <lb
                            n="18"/> moths and vermin do not destroy, and where thieves <lb n="19"/>
                        do not break in and steal.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>For where your <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="12v"/> treasure is, there your heart will be also. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“The eye is the lamp of the body. <lb n="2"/> If your eyes are healthy, your
                        whole <lb n="3"/> body will be full of light.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>But if your eyes are unhealthy, your whole body <lb n="4"/> will be full of
                        darkness. If then the light <lb n="5"/> within you is darkness, how great is
                            <lb n="6"/> that darkness!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“No one can serve two <lb n="7"/> masters. Either you will hate the <lb n="8"
                        /> one and love the other, or you <lb n="9"/> will be devoted to the one and
                        despise the other. You cannot serve both <lb n="10"/> God and money.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore I tell <lb n="11"/> you, do not worry about your life, <lb n="12"
                        /> what you will eat or drink; or about your body <lb n="13"/>, what you
                        will wear. Is not life more <lb n="14"/> than food, and the body more than
                        clothes? <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Look at the birds of the air; they do not sow <lb n="16"/> or reap or store
                        away in barns, and yet your heavenly Father <lb n="17"/> feeds them. Are you
                        not much more <lb n="18"/> valuable than they?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Can any one of you <lb n="19"/> by worrying add a single hour to <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="13r"/> your life?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“And why do you worry about clothes <lb n="1"/>? See how the flowers of <lb
                            n="2"/> the field grow. They do <lb n="3"/> not labor or spin.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Yet I tell you that not even Solomon <lb n="4"/> in all his splendor was
                        dressed <lb n="5"/> like one of these.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>If that is how God clothes the grass <lb n="6"/> of the field, which is here
                        today and tomorrow is thrown into the fire, <lb n="7"/> will he not much
                        more clothe you-<lb n="8"/> you of little faith?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>So do not worry, <lb n="9"/> saying, 'What shall we eat?' or 'What shall we
                        drink?' or <lb n="10"/> 'What shall we wear?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>For <lb n="11"/> the pagans run after all these things, and <lb n="12"/> your
                        heavenly Father knows that you need them. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>But seek first his kingdom <lb n="14"/> and his righteousness, and all these
                        things will be given <lb n="15"/> to you as well.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore do not worry about tomorrow, <lb n="16"/> for tomorrow will worry
                        about itself. <lb n="17"/> Each day has enough trouble of its own. <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not judge, or you too will be judged.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>For in <lb n="19"/> the same way you judge others, you will be judged, <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="13v"/> and with the measure you use, it will be measured <lb n="1"/>
                        to you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why do you look at the speck of sawdust <lb n="2"/> in your brother's eye
                        and pay no attention to the plank <lb n="3"/> in your own eye?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>How can you say <lb n="4"/> to your brother, 'Let me take the speck out of
                        your eye,' <lb n="5"/> when all the time there is a plank in your own eye?
                            <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>You hypocrite, first take the plank out of <lb n="7"/> your own eye, and then
                        you will see clearly to remove the speck <lb n="8"/> from your brother's
                        eye.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not give <lb n="9"/> dogs what is sacred; do not throw your <lb n="10"/>
                        pearls to pigs. If you do, they may trample <lb n="11"/> them under their
                        feet, and turn and <lb n="12"/> tear you to pieces.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“Ask and it will be given <lb n="13"/> to you; seek and you will find; knock
                            <lb n="14"/> and the door will be opened to you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>For everyone who asks <lb n="15"/> receives; the one who seeks finds; and to
                        the one who knocks, the door will <lb n="16"/> be opened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“Which of you, <lb n="17"/> if your son asks for bread, will <lb n="18"/>
                        give him a stone?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Or if he asks for a fish <lb n="19"/>, will give him a snake <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="14r"/>?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>If you, then, though you are evil, know how to <lb n="1"/> give good gifts to
                        your children, how much more will your <lb n="2"/> Father in heaven give
                        good <lb n="3"/> gifts to those who ask him!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>So in everything, <lb n="4"/> do to others what you would <lb n="5"/> have
                        them do to you, <lb n="6"/> for this sums up the Law and the Prophets.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“Enter through the narrow <lb n="7"/> gate. For wide is the gate and broad is
                            <lb n="8"/> the road that leads to destruction, <lb n="9"/> and many
                        enter through it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>But <lb n="10"/> small is the gate and narrow the road <lb n="11"/> that
                        leads to life, and only a few find <lb n="12"/> it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“Watch out for false prophets. <lb n="13"/> They come to you in sheep's
                        clothing, <lb n="14"/> but inwardly they are ferocious <lb n="15"/>
                        wolves.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>By their fruit you will recognize <lb n="16"/> them. Do people pick grapes
                        from thornbushes, <lb n="17"/> or figs from thistles?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Likewise, every <lb n="18"/> good tree bears good fruit, but a bad tree bears
                        bad fruit.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="19"/> A good tree cannot bear bad fruit, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="14v"/> and a bad tree cannot bear good fruit. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Every tree that does not bear <lb n="2"/> good fruit is cut down and thrown
                        into the fire. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Thus, by their fruit you will recognize <lb n="4"/> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“Not everyone who says to me, <lb n="5"/> 'Lord, Lord,' will enter the
                        kingdom of heaven, <lb n="6"/> but only the one who does the will of my
                        Father <lb n="7"/> who is in heaven <lb n="8"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Many will say to me on <lb n="9"/> that day, 'Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy
                        in your name <lb n="10"/> and in your name drive out demons <lb n="11"/> and
                        in your name perform <lb n="12"/> many miracles?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Then I will tell <lb n="13"/> them plainly, 'I never knew you. <lb n="14"/>
                        Away from me, you evildoers!' <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore everyone who hears these words of mine <lb n="16"/> and puts them
                        into practice is like a wise man <lb n="17"/> who built his house on <lb
                            n="18"/> the rock.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>The rain came down, the streams rose <lb n="19"/>, and the winds blew and
                        beat against <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="15r"/> that house; yet it did not fall, <lb n="1"/> because it had
                        its foundation on the rock.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>But everyone who <lb n="2"/> hears these words of mine and does not put them
                        into practice is <lb n="3"/> like a foolish man who built <lb n="4"/> his
                        house on sand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>The rain came down <lb n="5"/>, the streams rose, and <lb n="6"/> the winds
                        blew and beat against that house, and it fell <lb n="7"/> with a great
                        crash.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="8"/> Jesus had finished saying these things, <lb n="9"/> the
                        crowds were amazed at <lb n="10"/> his teaching,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>because he taught as one <lb n="11"/> who had authority, and not as <lb
                            n="12"/> their teachers of the law.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus came down <lb n="13"/> from the mountainside, large crowds <lb
                            n="14"/> followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>A man with leprosy came <lb n="15"/> and knelt before him and said, “Lord, if
                        you are willing, you can <lb n="16"/> make me clean.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus reached out his hand and touched <lb n="17"/> the man. ”I am willing,”
                        he said. “Be clean!” Immediately he <lb n="18"/> was cleansed of his
                        leprosy.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="19"/> Jesus said to him, “See that you don't tell anyone. But go,
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="15v"/> show yourself to the priest and offer <lb n="1"/> the gift
                        Moses commanded, as a testimony to them.” <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus had entered Capernaum, <lb n="3"/> a centurion came to him, asking
                            <lb n="4"/> for help.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“Lord,” he said, “my <lb n="5"/> servant lies at home paralyzed, suffering
                            <lb n="6"/> terribly.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to him, “Shall I come and <lb n="7"/> heal him?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>The centurion replied, <lb n="8"/> “Lord, I do not deserve to have you <lb
                            n="9"/> come under my roof. But just say the word, <lb n="10"/> and my
                        servant will be healed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>For I myself am a man <lb n="11"/> under authority, with soldiers <lb n="12"
                        /> under me. I tell this one, 'Go,' and he goes; and that one, <lb n="13"/>
                        'Come,' and he comes. I say to my servant, 'Do <lb n="14"/> this,' and he
                        does it.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus heard this, he was amazed and said <lb n="15"/> to those following
                        him, “Truly I tell you, I have not <lb n="16"/> found anyone in Israel with
                        such great faith. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>I say to you that many will come from the east <lb n="18"/> and the west, and
                        will take their places at the feast <lb n="19"/> with Abraham, Isaac and
                        Jacob in the kingdom of <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="16r"/> heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>But the subjects of the kingdom will be thrown outside, <lb n="1"/> into the
                        darkness, where there will be weeping <lb n="2"/> and gnashing of
                        teeth.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said to the centurion <lb n="3"/>, “Go! Let it be done just as you
                        believed it would.” And <lb n="4"/> his servant was healed at that
                        moment.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus came into Peter's house, he saw <lb n="5"/> Peter's mother-in-law
                            <lb n="6"/> lying in bed with a fever.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>He touched <lb n="7"/> her hand and the fever left her, and she got up <lb
                            n="8"/> and began to wait on him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>When evening came <lb n="9"/>, many who were demon-possessed were brought to
                        him, and he drove out the spirits <lb n="10"/> with a word and healed all
                        the sick.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>This was to fulfill <lb n="11"/> what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah:
                            <lb n="12"/> “He took up our infirmities <lb n="13"/> and bore our
                        diseases.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus saw the crowd around <lb n="14"/> him, <lb n="15"/> he gave orders
                        to cross to the other side of the lake.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Then a teacher of the law came to <lb n="16"/> him and said, “Teacher, I will
                        follow <lb n="17"/> you wherever you go.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="18"/> “Foxes have dens and <lb n="19"/> birds have
                        nests, but the Son of Man <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="16v"/> has no place to lay his head.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Another <lb n="1"/> disciple said to him, “Lord, first let <lb n="2"/> me go
                        and bury my father.”<lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus told him, “Follow me, and <lb n="4"/> let the dead bury their own
                        dead <lb n="5"/>.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he got into the boat and <lb n="6"/> his disciples followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Suddenly a <lb n="7"/> furious storm came up on the lake, <lb n="8"/> so that
                        the waves swept over the boat. <lb n="9"/> But Jesus was sleeping. <lb
                            n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples went and woke <lb n="11"/> him, saying, “Lord, save us! We're
                        going to drown!” <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “You of little faith, why are you so afraid?” <lb n="13"/> Then
                        he got up and rebuked the winds <seg n="14" type="lb"/> and the waves, and
                        it was completely calm. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>The men were amazed and asked, <lb n="16"/> “What kind of man is this? Even
                        the winds and the waves obey <lb n="17"/> him!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>When he arrived at the other <lb n="18"/> side in the region of the
                        Gadarenes, <lb n="19"/> two demon-possessed men coming <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="17r"/> from the tombs met him. They were so violent <lb n="1"/> that
                        no one could pass that <lb n="2"/> way.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you want with us, Son of God?” they shouted <lb n="3"/>. ”Have you
                        come here to torture us <lb n="4"/> before the appointed time?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Some <lb n="5"/> distance from them a large herd of pigs was <lb n="6"/>
                        feeding.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>The demons begged <lb n="7"/> Jesus, “If you drive us out, send <lb n="8"/>
                        us into the herd of pigs.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, <lb n="9"/> “Go!” So they came out and went into the pigs,
                        and <lb n="10"/> the whole herd rushed down the steep bank <lb n="11"/> into
                        the lake and died in the water.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Those tending <lb n="12"/> the pigs ran off, went into the town <lb n="13"/>
                        and reported all this, including what had happened to <lb n="14"/> the
                        demon-possessed men.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the whole town <lb n="15"/> went out to meet Jesus. And when they saw
                        him, they pleaded with him <lb n="16"/> to leave their region.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus stepped into a boat, crossed over <lb n="17"/> and came <lb n="18"/> to
                        his own town.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Some men brought to <lb n="19"/> him a paralyzed man, lying on a mat. When
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="17v"/> Jesus saw their faith, he said to the man, <lb n="1"/> “Take
                        heart, son; your sins are forgiven.” <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>At this, some of the teachers of the law said to themselves, <lb n="3"/>
                        ”This fellow is blaspheming!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Knowing their thoughts, Jesus <lb n="4"/> said, “Why do you entertain evil
                        thoughts <lb n="5"/> in your hearts?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Which is easier: <lb n="6"/> to say, 'Your sins are forgiven,' or <lb n="7"/>
                        to say, 'Get up and walk'?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>But I want you to know <lb n="8"/> that the Son of Man has authority <lb
                            n="9"/> on earth to forgive sins.” So he said to the paralyzed man <lb
                            n="10"/> , “Get up, take your mat and go <lb n="11"/> home.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the man got up and went <lb n="12"/> home.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>When the crowd saw this, they were <lb n="13"/> filled with awe; and they
                        praised God, who had given <lb n="14"/> such authority to man.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="15"/> As Jesus went on from there, he saw a man named Matthew sitting
                            <lb n="16"/> at the tax collector's booth. “Follow me,” <lb n="17"/> he
                        told him, and Matthew got up and followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>While Jesus was having dinner at Matthew's <lb n="18"/> house, <lb n="19"/>
                        many tax collectors and sinners came and <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="18r"/> ate with him and his disciples. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>When the Pharisees saw this, they asked his disciples, <lb n="2"/> "Why does
                        your teacher eat with tax <lb n="3"/> collectors and sinners?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>On hearing this, Jesus said, <lb n="4"/> “It is not the healthy who need a
                        doctor, <lb n="5"/> but the sick.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>But go and <lb n="6"/> learn what this means: 'I desire mercy, <lb n="7"/>
                        not sacrifice.' For I have not come to call the <lb n="8"/> righteous, but
                        sinners.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="9"/> John's disciples came and asked him, “How <lb n="10"/> is it
                        that we and the Pharisees fast often, but your <lb n="11"/> disciples do not
                        fast?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered <lb n="12"/> “How can the guests of the bridegroom mourn <lb
                            n="13"/> while he is with them? The time will come <lb n="14"/> when the
                        bridegroom will be taken from them; <lb n="15"/> then they will fast. <lb
                            n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“No one sews a patch <lb n="17"/> of unshrunk cloth on an old garment, <lb
                            n="18"/> for the patch will pull away from the garment, <lb n="19"/>
                        making the tear worse.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Neither do people pour new wine <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="18v"/> into old wineskins. If they do, the skins will burst; <lb
                            n="1"/> the wine will run out and the wineskins <lb n="2"/> will be
                        ruined. No, they pour new wine into <lb n="3"/> new wineskins, and both are
                        preserved.” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>While he was saying this, a synagogue leader <lb n="5"/> came and knelt
                        before him and said, <lb n="6"/> “My daughter has just died. But come <lb
                            n="7"/> and put your hand on her, and <lb n="8"/> she will live.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus got up and went with him, and so did <lb n="9"/> his disciples.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Just then a woman who had been subject to bleeding <lb n="10"/> for twelve
                        years came up behind him <lb n="11"/> and touched the edge of his cloak.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>She said <lb n="12"/> to herself, “If I only touch his cloak, <lb n="13"/> I
                        will be healed.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus turned <lb n="14"/> and saw her. “Take heart, daughter,” he said, “your
                        faith <lb n="15"/> has healed you.” And the woman was healed at <lb n="16"/>
                        that moment.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus entered the synagogue leader's house <lb n="17"/> and saw the
                        noisy crowd and people playing pipes,<lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>he said, “Go away. The <lb n="19"/> girl is not dead but asleep.” But they
                        laughed at <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="19r"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>After the crowd had been put outside, he went in <lb n="1"/> and took the
                        girl by the hand, and she got up. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>News of this spread through all that region. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus went on from there, <lb n="4"/> two blind men followed him, calling
                        out, “Have mercy <lb n="5"/> on us, Son of David!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>When he had gone <lb n="6"/> indoors, the blind men came to him <lb n="7"/>,
                        and he asked them, “Do you believe that I am able to do this?” <lb n="8"/>
                        “Yes, Lord,” they replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he touched <lb n="9"/> their eyes and said, “According to your faith <lb
                            n="10"/> let it be done to you”;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>and their <lb n="11"/> sight was restored. Jesus warned them sternly, <lb
                            n="12"/> “See that no one knows about this.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>But they went out and spread <lb n="13"/> the news about him all over that
                        region. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>While they were going out, <lb n="15"/> a man who was demon-possessed and
                        could not talk <lb n="16"/> was brought to Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>And when the demon was driven out <lb n="17"/>, the man who had been mute
                        spoke. The crowd was amazed and said, <lb n="18"/> “Nothing like this has
                        ever been seen in Israel.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>But the Pharisees <lb n="19"/> said, “It is by the prince of demons that he
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="19v"/> drives out demons.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus went <lb n="1"/> through all the towns and villages, teaching <lb n="2"
                        /> in their synagogues, proclaiming the good news <lb n="3"/> of the kingdom
                        and healing every disease <lb n="4"/> and sickness.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>When he saw <lb n="5"/> the crowds, he had compassion on them, because they
                        were harassed <lb n="6"/> and helpless, like sheep without a shepherd. <lb
                            n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he said to his disciples <lb n="8"/>, “The harvest is plentiful but the
                        workers are few. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Ask the Lord of the harvest, therefore, to send <lb n="10"/> out workers into
                        his harvest field.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus called <lb n="11"/> his twelve disciples to him and gave <lb n="12"/>
                        them authority to drive out <lb n="13"/> impure spirits and to heal every
                        disease <lb n="14"/> and sickness.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>These are the names of the twelve <lb n="15"/> apostles: first, <lb n="16"/>
                        Simon (who is called Peter) and his brother Andrew; James son of Zebedee,
                        and <lb n="17"/> his brother John; <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Philip and Bartholomew; <lb n="19"/> Thomas and Matthew the tax collector;
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="20r"/> James son of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus;</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Simon <lb n="1"/> the Zealot and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed <lb n="2"/>
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>These twelve Jesus sent out with the following <lb n="3"/> instructions: “Do
                        not go among the Gentiles or enter any town of <lb n="4"/> the
                        Samaritans.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Go rather to the lost sheep <lb n="5"/> of Israel. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>As you go, proclaim this message: <lb n="7"/> 'The kingdom of heaven has come
                        near.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Heal the sick <lb n="8"/>, raise the dead, cleanse those who have leprosy,
                            <lb n="9"/> drive out demons. Freely you have received; <lb n="10"/>
                        freely give.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not get any gold <lb n="11"/> or silver or copper to take with you in
                        your <lb n="12"/> belts</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>no bag for the journey or extra <lb n="13"/> shirt or sandals or a staff, <lb
                            n="14"/> for the worker is worth his keep. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Whatever town or village you enter, <lb n="16"/> search there for some worthy
                        person <lb n="17"/> and stay at their house until you leave.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>As you enter <lb n="18"/> the home, give it your greeting. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>If the <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="20v"/> home is deserving, let your peace rest on <lb n="1"/> it; if
                        it is not, let your peace <lb n="2"/> return to you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone will <lb n="3"/> not welcome you or listen to your words, <lb n="4"
                        /> leave that home <lb n="5"/> or town and shake <lb n="6"/> the dust off
                        your feet. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, it will be more bearable for <lb n="8"/> Sodom and Gomorrah
                        on the day <lb n="9"/> of judgment than for that town.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="10"/> “I am sending you out like sheep among wolves. <lb n="11"/>
                        Therefore be as shrewd as snakes and as innocent <lb n="12"/> as doves.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Be on your guard; <lb n="13"/> you will be handed over to the local councils
                            <lb n="14"/> and be flogged in the synagogues. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>On my account you will be brought <lb n="16"/> before governors and kings as
                        witnesses to them <lb n="17"/> and to the Gentiles.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>But when they arrest you, <lb n="18"/> do not worry about what to say or how
                        to say it. <lb n="19"/> At that time you will be given <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="21r"/> what to say,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>for it will not be you <lb n="1"/> speaking, but the Spirit of your Father
                        speaking <lb n="2"/> through you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“Brother will betray <lb n="3"/> brother to death, and a father his child;
                        children will rebel <lb n="4"/> against their parents and have them put to
                        death <lb n="5"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>You will be hated by everyone <lb n="6"/> because of me, but the <lb n="7"/>
                        one who stands firm to the end will <lb n="8"/> be saved.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>When you are persecuted in one place, <lb n="9"/> flee to another. Truly I
                        tell you, <lb n="10"/> you will not finish going through the towns of Israel
                            <lb n="11"/> before the Son of Man comes.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“The student is not <lb n="12"/> above the teacher, nor a servant <lb n="13"
                        /> above his master.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>It is enough for students <lb n="14"/> to be like their teachers, and
                        servants like <lb n="15"/> their masters. If the head of the house has been
                        called Beelzebul, <lb n="16"/> how much more the members of his
                            household!<lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“So do not be afraid of them, for there is nothing <lb n="18"/> concealed
                        that will not be disclosed, <lb n="19"/> or hidden that will not be made
                        known.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>What I tell <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="21v"/> you in the dark, speak in the daylight; what is whispered <lb
                            n="1"/> in your ear, proclaim from the roofs. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Do not be afraid of those who kill the body <lb n="3"/> but cannot kill the
                        soul. <lb n="4"/> Rather, be afraid of the One who can destroy both <lb
                            n="5"/> soul and body in hell. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Are not two sparrows sold for a penny? <lb n="7"/> Yet not one of them will
                        fall to the ground <lb n="8"/> outside your Father's care. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>And even the very hairs of your head <lb n="10"/> are all numbered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>So don't be afraid; <lb n="11"/> you are worth more than many sparrows. <lb
                            n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>“Whoever acknowledges me <lb n="13"/> before others, I will also acknowledge
                        before <lb n="14"/> my Father in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>But whoever disowns me before others,<lb n="15"/> I will disown <lb n="16"/>
                        before my Father in heaven. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do not suppose that I have come to bring <lb n="18"/> peace to the earth. I
                        did not come <lb n="19"/> to bring peace, but a sword.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>For I have come to turn <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="22r"/> “'a man against his father, <lb n="1"/> a daughter against her
                        mother, a daughter-in-law <lb n="2"/> against her mother-in-law </p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>a man's enemies <lb n="3"/> will be the members of <lb n="4"/> his own
                        household.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>“Anyone who loves their father or mother more than me is not worthy <lb n="5"
                        /> of me; anyone who loves their son or daughter more <lb n="6"/> than me is
                        not worthy of me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever does not take up <lb n="7"/> their cross and follow me is not <lb
                            n="8"/> worthy of me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever finds their life <lb n="9"/> will lose it, and whoever loses their
                            <lb n="10"/> life for my sake will find it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>“Anyone who welcomes you welcomes me <lb n="11"/>, and anyone who welcomes me
                        welcomes the one <lb n="12"/> who sent me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever welcomes a prophet as a prophet <lb n="13"/> will receive a prophet's
                        reward, and whoever welcomes <lb n="14"/> a righteous person as a righteous
                        person will receive <lb n="15"/> a righteous person's reward.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>And if anyone <lb n="16"/> gives even a cup <lb n="17"/> of cold water to one
                        of these little ones who is my disciple, <lb n="18"/> truly I tell you, that
                        person will certainly not lose their reward.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>After Jesus had finished instructing <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="22v"/> his twelve disciples, <lb n="1"/> he went on from there <lb
                            n="2"/> to teach and preach in the towns of Galilee. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>When John, who was in prison, heard <lb n="4"/> about the deeds of the
                        Messiah, he sent his disciples <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>to ask him, “Are you the one who is to come, <lb n="6"/> or should we expect
                        someone else?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="7"/> “Go back and report to John <lb n="8"/> what you
                        hear and see:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>The blind receive <lb n="9"/> sight, the lame walk, those who have leprosy
                        are cleansed <lb n="10"/>, the deaf hear, the dead are raised, and <lb
                            n="11"/> the good news is proclaimed to the poor.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>Blessed is anyone who does not stumble on account of me.” <lb n="12"/>
                        <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>As John's disciples were leaving, Jesus began to speak <lb n="14"/> to the
                        crowd about John: “What did you go out into the wilderness to see? A reed
                            <lb n="15"/>
                        <lb n="16"/> swayed by the wind?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>If not, <lb n="17"/> what did you go out to see? <lb n="18"/> A man dressed
                        in fine clothes? No, those who wear fine clothes <lb n="19"/> are in kings'
                        palaces.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Then what did you go out to see <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="22r"/>? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and more than a prophet. <lb
                            n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>This is the one about whom it is written: “'I will send my messenger ahead of
                        you, <lb n="2"/> who <lb n="3"/> will prepare your way before you.' <lb
                            n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, among those born of <lb n="5"/> women there has not risen
                        anyone greater than John the Baptist <lb n="6"/>; yet whoever is least in
                        the kingdom of heaven <lb n="7"/> is greater than he.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>From the days of John <lb n="8"/> the Baptist until now, the kingdom of
                        heaven <lb n="9"/> has been subjected to violence, and violent people have
                        been raiding it. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>For all the Prophets and the Law <lb n="11"/> prophesied until John.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>And if <lb n="12"/> you are willing to accept it, he is the Elijah who was to
                        come. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever has ears, let them hear. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“To what can I compare this generation? <lb n="15"/> They are like children
                        sitting <lb n="16"/> in the marketplaces and calling out to others:<lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“'We played the pipe for you, and you did not <lb n="18"/> dance; we sang a
                        dirge, and you did not <lb n="19"/> mourn.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>For John came neither <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="23v"/> eating nor drinking, and they say, <lb n="1"/> 'He has a
                        demon.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>The Son of Man came <lb n="2"/> eating and drinking, and they say, <lb n="3"
                        /> 'Here is a glutton and a drunkard, <lb n="4"/> a friend of tax collectors
                        and sinners.' <lb n="5"/> But wisdom is proved right by her deeds.” <lb
                            n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus began to denounce the towns <lb n="7"/> in which most of his
                        miracles had been performed <lb n="8"/>, because they did not repent. <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! <lb n="10"/> For if the
                        miracles that were performed in you had been performed in Tyre and Sidon,
                            <lb n="11"/> they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and <lb
                            n="12"/> ashes.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you, <lb n="13"/> it will be more bearable for Tyre and Sidon <lb
                            n="14"/> on the day of judgment than for you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>And you, Capernaum, <lb n="15"/> will you be lifted to the heavens? <lb
                            n="16"/> No, you will go down to Hades. For if the miracles that were
                        performed in you had been performed in Sodom <lb n="17"/>, it would have
                        remained <lb n="18"/>
                        <note place="margin" type="gloss"> A portion of this verse is found in the
                            Latin Vulgate and not in the NIV translation.</note><lb n="19"/> to this
                        day.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="24r"/> that it will be more bearable for Sodom <lb n="1"/> on the day
                        of judgment than for you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>At that <lb n="2"/> time Jesus said, “I praise <lb n="3"/> you, Father, Lord
                        of heaven and earth, <lb n="4"/> because you have hidden these things from
                        the wise and learned, <lb n="5"/> and revealed them to little children.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Yes, <lb n="6"/> Father, for this is what you were pleased to <lb n="7"/>
                        do.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“All things have been committed to me by my Father. <lb n="8"/> No one knows
                        the Son except the Father, <lb n="9"/> and no one knows <lb n="10"/> the
                        Father except the Son and those to whom the Son chooses to reveal him. <lb
                            n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“Come to me, all you who are weary and <lb n="12"/> burdened, and I will give
                        you rest.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Take <lb n="13"/> my yoke upon you and learn <lb n="14"/> from me, for I am
                        gentle and humble in heart, <lb n="15"/> and you will find rest for your
                        souls. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>For my yoke is easy and <lb n="17"/> my burden is light.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time <lb n="18"/> Jesus went through the grainfields on the Sabbath.
                            <lb n="19"/> His disciples were hungry and began to pick some heads of
                        grain and <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="24v"/> eat them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>When the Pharisees saw this <lb n="1"/>, they said to him, “Look! Your
                        disciples <lb n="2"/> are doing what is unlawful on the Sabbath.” <lb n="3"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, “Haven't you read <lb n="4"/> what David did when he and his
                        companions were hungry? <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>He entered the house <lb n="6"/> of God, and he and his companions ate the
                        consecrated bread-which <lb n="7"/> was not lawful for them to do, <lb n="8"
                        /> but only for the priests.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Or haven't <lb n="9"/> you read in the Law that the priests on Sabbath duty
                            <lb n="10"/> in the temple desecrate the Sabbath and yet <lb n="11"/>
                        are innocent?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>I tell you that something <lb n="12"/> greater than the temple is here.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>If you had known what <lb n="13"/> these words mean, 'I desire mercy, not
                        sacrifice, <lb n="14"/>' you would not have condemned <lb n="15"/> the
                        innocent.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>For the Son of Man is Lord of <lb n="16"/> the Sabbath.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Going on from that <lb n="17"/> place, he went into their synagogue,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>and a man with <lb n="18"/> a shriveled hand was there. Looking for a reason
                            <lb n="19"/> to bring charges against Jesus, they <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="25r"/> asked him, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, <lb n="1"/> “If any of you has <lb n="2"/> a sheep and it
                        falls into a pit on the Sabbath <lb n="3"/>, will you not take hold of it
                        and lift it out? <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>How much more valuable is a person than <lb n="5"/> a sheep! Therefore it is
                        lawful to do good on the Sabbath.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he said to the man, “Stretch out your <lb n="6"/> hand.” So he stretched
                        it out and <lb n="7"/> it was completely restored, just as sound as the
                        other.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>But the Pharisees <lb n="8"/> went out and <lb n="9"/> plotted how they might
                        kill Jesus. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Aware of this, Jesus withdrew <lb n="11"/> from that place. A large crowd
                        followed him, and he healed <lb n="12"/> all who were ill.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>He warned them not to tell others <lb n="13"/> about him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>This was to fulfill what was spoken <lb n="14"/> through the prophet Isaiah:
                            <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Here is my servant whom I have chosen, <lb n="16"/> the one I love, in whom
                        I delight; I will put my <lb n="17"/> Spirit on him, and he will proclaim
                        justice <lb n="18"/> to the nations.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>He will not <lb n="19"/> quarrel or cry out; no one will hear <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="25v"/> his voice in the streets.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>A bruised reed he <lb n="1"/> will not break, and a smoldering wick he will
                            <lb n="2"/> not snuff out, till he has brought justice through to
                        victory. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>In his name the nations will put their hope.” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Then they brought him a demon-possessed man <lb n="5"/> who was blind and
                        mute, and Jesus healed him, <lb n="6"/> so that he could both talk and
                        see.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>All the people were astonished <lb n="7"/> and said, “Could <lb n="8"/> this
                        be the Son of David?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>But when the Pharisees <lb n="9"/> heard this, they said, “It is only by
                        Beelzebul, the prince of demons <lb n="10"/>, that this fellow drives out
                        demons.” <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus knew their thoughts and said <lb n="12"/> to them, “Every kingdom
                        divided against itself will be ruined, <lb n="13"/> and every city or
                        household <lb n="14"/> divided against itself will not stand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>If Satan drives out <lb n="15"/> Satan, he is divided against himself. <lb
                            n="16"/> How then can his kingdom stand? <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>And if I drive out demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your people drive them
                        out? So then, they will be <lb n="18"/> your judges.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>But if it is by the Spirit of God that I drive out demons, <lb n="19"/> then
                        the kingdom of God has come upon you. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="26r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“Or again, how can anyone enter <lb n="1"/> a strong man's house and carry
                        off his <lb n="2"/> possessions unless he first ties up the strong man? <lb
                            n="3"/> Then he can plunder his house.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>“Whoever <lb n="4"/> is not with me is against me, <lb n="5"/> and whoever
                        does not gather with me scatters.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>And so I tell <lb n="6"/> you, every kind of sin and slander <lb n="7"/> can
                        be forgiven, but blasphemy against the Spirit will <lb n="8"/> not be
                        forgiven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Anyone <lb n="9"/> who speaks a word against the Son of Man <lb n="10"/> will
                        be forgiven, but anyone who speaks against <lb n="11"/> the Holy Spirit will
                        not be forgiven, either in <lb n="12"/> this age or in the age to come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“Make a tree good and its fruit will be good <lb n="13"/>, or make <lb n="14"
                        /> a tree bad and its fruit will be <lb n="15"/> bad, for a tree is
                        recognized by its fruit. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>You brood of vipers, how can you <lb n="17"/> who are evil say anything good?
                        For the mouth speaks what the heart is full of. <lb n="18"/>
                        <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>A good man brings good things <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="26v"/> out of the good stored up in him, and an evil man brings evil
                        things out of the evil <lb n="1"/> stored up in him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell <lb n="2"/> you that everyone will have to give account on the <lb
                            n="3"/> day of judgment for every <lb n="4"/> empty word they have
                        spoken.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>For by your words <lb n="5"/> you will be acquitted, and by your words you
                        will <lb n="6"/> be condemned.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Then some <lb n="7"/> of the Pharisees and teachers of the law said to him
                            <lb n="8"/>, “Teacher, we want to see a sign <lb n="9"/> from you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, “A wicked and adulterous generation <lb n="10"/> asks for a
                        sign! But none will be <lb n="11"/> given it except the sign of <lb n="12"/>
                        the prophet Jonah.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>For as Jonah was <lb n="13"/> three days and three <lb n="14"/> nights in the
                        belly of a huge fish, so the Son of Man will be <lb n="15"/> three days and
                        three nights in the heart of the earth. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>The men of Nineveh will stand up at the judgment <lb n="17"/> with this
                        generation and condemn it; <lb n="18"/> for they repented at the preaching
                            <lb n="19"/> of Jonah, and now something greater than <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="27r"/> Jonah is here.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>The Queen of the South will rise at the judgment with <lb n="1"/> this
                        generation and condemn it; <lb n="2"/> for she came from the ends of the
                        earth to listen to Solomon's wisdom, <lb n="3"/> and now something greater
                        than Solomon is <lb n="4"/> here.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>“When an impure spirit comes <lb n="5"/> out of a person, it goes through
                        arid places <lb n="6"/> seeking rest and does not find it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="7"/> it says, 'I will return to the house I left.' <lb n="8"/>
                        When it arrives, it finds the house unoccupied, swept <lb n="9"/> clean and
                        put in order.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>Then it goes <lb n="10"/> and takes with it seven other spirits more wicked
                        than <lb n="11"/> itself, and they go in and live there. <lb n="12"/> And
                        the final condition of that person is worse than the first. That is how it
                            <lb n="13"/> will be with this wicked generation.” <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>While Jesus was still talking to the crowd, <lb n="15"/> his mother and
                        brothers stood outside, <lb n="16"/> wanting to speak to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>Someone told him, “Your mother <lb n="17"/> and brothers <lb n="18"/> are
                        standing outside, wanting to speak <lb n="19"/> to you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied to him, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="27v"/> “Who is my mother, and who are <lb n="1"/> my brothers?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>Pointing to his disciples, <lb n="2"/> he said, “Here are my mother and <lb
                            n="3"/> my brothers.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>For whoever does the will of <lb n="4"/> my Father in heaven is <lb n="5"/>
                        my brother and sister and mother.” <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>That same day Jesus went out of the house and sat <lb n="7"/> by the
                        lake.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Such large crowds gathered around him <lb n="8"/> that he got into a boat and
                            <lb n="9"/> sat in it, while all the people stood on the shore. <lb
                            n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he told them many things in parables, saying: <lb n="11"/> “A farmer
                        went out to sow his seed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>As he was scattering <lb n="12"/> the seed, some fell along the path, and the
                        birds <lb n="13"/> came and ate it up.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Some fell on rocky places, where it did <lb n="14"/> not <lb n="15"/> have
                        much soil. It sprang up quickly <lb n="16"/>, because the <lb n="17"/> soil
                        was shallow.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>But when the sun came up, the plants were scorched <lb n="18"/>, and they
                        withered because they had no root. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Other seed fell among thorns, which <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="28r"/> grew up and choked the plants.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Still other seed fell on good soil <lb n="1"/>, where it produced a <lb n="2"
                        /> crop-a hundred, sixty or thirty times <lb n="3"/> what was sown.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever has ears, <lb n="4"/> let them hear.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples came to him <lb n="5"/> and asked, “Why do you speak to the
                        people in parables?” <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “Because the knowledge of <lb n="7"/> the secrets of the kingdom
                        of heaven <lb n="8"/> has been given to you, but not to them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Whoever <lb n="9"/> has will be given more, and they will have an abundance.
                        Whoever does <lb n="10"/> not have, even what they have will be taken <lb
                            n="11"/> from them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>This is why I speak to them in parables: <lb n="12"/> “Though seeing, they do
                        not see; <lb n="13"/> though hearing, they do not hear or understand.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>In them is fulfilled <lb n="14"/> the prophecy of Isaiah: “'You will be ever
                        hearing <lb n="15"/> but never understanding; you will be ever seeing <lb
                            n="16"/> but never perceiving.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>For this <lb n="17"/> people's heart has become calloused; they hardly hear
                        with their ears, <lb n="18"/> and they have closed their eyes. Otherwise
                        they might see with their <lb n="19"/> eyes, hear with their ears, <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="28v"/> understand with their hearts <lb n="1"/> and turn, and I would
                        heal them.'<lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>But blessed are your eyes because they see, and <lb n="3"/> your ears because
                        they hear.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>For truly I tell you, many <lb n="4"/> prophets <lb n="5"/> and righteous
                        people longed to see what <lb n="6"/> you see but did not see it, and to
                        hear <lb n="7"/> what you hear but did not hear it. <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Listen then to what the parable of the sower means: <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>When anyone hears the message about the kingdom <lb n="10"/> and does not
                        understand it, the evil one comes and snatches away <lb n="11"/> what was
                        sown in their heart. This is <lb n="12"/> the seed sown along the path.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>The seed falling <lb n="13"/> on rocky ground refers to someone who hears <lb
                            n="14"/> the word and at once <lb n="15"/> receives it with joy.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>But since they have no <lb n="16"/> root, they last only a short time. When
                            <lb n="17"/> trouble or persecution comes <lb n="18"/> because of the
                        word, they quickly fall away. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>The seed falling among the thorns <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="29r"/> refers to someone who hears the word, but the worries <lb
                            n="1"/> of this life and the deceitfulness <lb n="2"/> of wealth choke
                        the word, making it <lb n="3"/> unfruitful.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>But the seed falling on good soil <lb n="4"/> refers to someone who hears the
                        word <lb n="5"/> and understands it. This is the one who produces a crop,
                        yielding <lb n="6"/> a hundred, sixty or thirty times what was <lb n="7"/>
                        sown.” <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus told them another parable: <lb n="9"/> “The kingdom of heaven <lb
                            n="10"/> is like a man who sowed good <lb n="11"/> seed in his
                        field.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>But while everyone was sleeping <lb n="12"/>, his enemy came and sowed <lb
                            n="13"/> weeds among the wheat, and went away. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>When the wheat sprouted and formed heads, <lb n="15"/> then the weeds also
                        appeared.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“The owner's <lb n="16"/> servants came to him and said, <lb n="17"/> 'Sir,
                        didn't you sow <lb n="18"/> good seed in your field? Where then did the
                        weeds come from?' <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“'An enemy did this,' he replied. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="29v"/> ”The servants asked him, 'Do you want us <lb n="1"/> to go and
                        pull them up?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“'No,' he answered, 'because while you are pulling <lb n="2"/> the weeds, you
                        may uproot the wheat with <lb n="3"/> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Let both grow together <lb n="4"/> until the harvest. At that time <lb n="5"
                        /> I will tell the harvesters: <lb n="6"/> First collect the weeds and tie
                        them in bundles <lb n="7"/> to be burned; then gather the wheat and bring
                            <lb n="8"/> it into my barn.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>He told them another parable: <lb n="9"/> “The kingdom of <lb n="10"/> heaven
                        is like a mustard seed, which <lb n="11"/> a man took and planted in his
                        field.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Though it is the smallest <lb n="12"/> of all seeds, yet when it grows, <lb
                            n="13"/> it is the largest of garden plants and <lb n="14"/> becomes a
                        tree, so that the birds <lb n="15"/> come and perch in its branches.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>He told them still another parable: <lb n="16"/> “The kingdom of heaven is
                            <lb n="17"/> like yeast that a woman took and mixed <lb n="18"/> into
                        about sixty pounds <lb n="19"/> of flour until it <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="30r"/> worked all through the dough.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus spoke all these things <lb n="1"/> to the crowd in parables; he did not
                        say anything to them without <lb n="2"/> using a parable.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>So was fulfilled <lb n="3"/> what was spoken through the prophet: <lb n="4"/>
                        “I will open my mouth <lb n="5"/> in parables, “I will open my mouth <lb
                            n="5"/> in parables, I will utter things hidden since the creation of
                            <lb n="6"/> the world.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he left the crowd and went <lb n="7"/> into the house. His disciples <lb
                            n="8"/> came to him and said, “Explain to us the parable of <lb n="9"/>
                        the weeds in the field.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, <lb n="10"/> “The one who sowed the good seed is the Son of Man.
                            <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>The field is the world, and the good <lb n="12"/> seed stands for the people
                        of the kingdom. <lb n="13"/> The weeds are the people of the evil one,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>and the enemy who sows them is the <lb n="14"/> devil. <lb n="15"/> The
                        harvest is the end of the age, and <lb n="16"/> the harvesters are
                        angels.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>“As <lb n="17"/> the weeds are pulled up and burned in the fire, <lb n="18"/>
                        so it will be at the end of the age. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>The Son of Man will send out his angels, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="30v"/> and they will weed out of his kingdom everything that causes
                        sin <lb n="1"/> and all who do evil. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>They will throw them into the blazing furnace, where there will be <lb n="3"
                        /> weeping and gnashing of teeth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the righteous <lb n="4"/> will shine like the sun in the kingdom of
                        their Father. Whoever <lb n="5"/> has ears, let them hear.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>“The kingdom of heaven is like <lb n="6"/> treasure hidden <lb n="7"/> in a
                        field. When a man found it, <lb n="8"/> he hid it again, and then in his joy
                        went <lb n="9"/> and sold all he had and bought <lb n="10"/> that field.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>“Again, the kingdom <lb n="11"/> of heaven is like a merchant looking for <lb
                            n="12"/> fine pearls.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>When he found one <lb n="13"/> of great value, he went away and sold <lb
                            n="14"/> everything he had and bought it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>“Once <lb n="15"/> again, the kingdom of heaven is like <lb n="16"/> a net
                        that was let down into the lake and caught all kinds of fish. <lb n="17"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>When it was full, the fishermen pulled it <lb n="18"/> up on the shore. Then
                        they sat down and collected the good <lb n="19"/> fish in baskets, but threw
                        the bad away. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="31r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>This is how it will be at the end of the age. <lb n="1"/> The angels will
                        come and separate the wicked from the righteous <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>and throw them into the blazing <lb n="3"/> furnace, where there will be
                        weeping and gnashing of teeth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>“Have you understood <lb n="4"/> all these things?” Jesus asked. “Yes,” they
                        replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>He <lb n="5"/> said to them, “Therefore every teacher of <lb n="6"/> the law
                        who has become a disciple in the kingdom of heaven is like the owner of a
                        house <lb n="7"/> who brings out of his storeroom new treasures as well as
                        old.” <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="53" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus had finished these parables, <lb n="9"/> he moved on from
                        there.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="54" type="verse">
                    <p>Coming to his hometown <lb n="10"/>, he began teaching the people in their
                        synagogue, and <lb n="11"/> they were amazed. “Where did this man get this
                        wisdom and <lb n="12"/> these miraculous powers?” they asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="55" type="verse">
                    <p>“Isn't this <lb n="13"/> the carpenter's son? Isn't his mother's name Mary,
                            <lb n="14"/> and aren't his brothers James, Joseph, Simon <lb n="15"/>
                        and Judas?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="56" type="verse">
                    <p>Aren't all his sisters with us? <lb n="16"/> Where then did this man get all
                        these things?” <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="57" type="verse">
                    <p>And they took offense at him. But Jesus said <lb n="18"/> to them, “A prophet
                        is not without honor except <lb n="19"/> in his own town and in his own
                        home.” </p>
                </div>
                <div n="58" type="verse">
                    <p>And he did not <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="31v"/> do many miracles there because of their <lb n="1"/> lack of
                        faith.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time <lb n="2"/> Herod the tetrarch heard the reports about
                        Jesus,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>and he said <lb n="3"/> to his attendants, “This is John the Baptist; <lb
                            n="4"/> he has risen from the dead! That is why miraculous powers <lb
                            n="5"/> are at work in him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Now Herod had arrested <lb n="6"/> John and bound him and put him in prison
                        because of Herodias, <lb n="7"/> his brother Philip's wife,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>for John had been saying to him: <lb n="8"/> “It is not lawful for you to
                        have her.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>Herod wanted <lb n="9"/> to kill John, but he was afraid of the people,
                        because <lb n="10"/> they considered John a prophet.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>On Herod's birthday the daughter of <lb n="11"/> Herodias <lb n="12"/> danced
                        for the guests and pleased Herod so much</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>that <lb n="13"/> he promised with an oath to give her <lb n="14"/> whatever
                        she asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="15"/> Prompted by her mother, she said, “Give me <lb n="16"/> here on
                        a platter the head of John the Baptist.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="17"/> The king was distressed, but because of his oaths <lb n="18"/>
                        and his dinner guests, he ordered that her request be granted <lb n="19"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>and had John beheaded <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="32r"/> in the prison.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>His head was brought in on a platter <lb n="1"/> and given to the girl, who
                        carried it to <lb n="2"/> her mother.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>John's disciples came and took <lb n="3"/> his body and buried it. Then they
                        went <lb n="4"/> and told Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus heard what had happened, he withdrew <lb n="5"/> by boat privately
                        to <lb n="6"/> a solitary place. Hearing of this, <lb n="7"/> the crowds
                        followed him on foot <lb n="8"/> from the towns.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus landed and saw a large crowd, <lb n="9"/> he had compassion on
                        them and healed <lb n="10"/> their sick.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>As evening approached, <lb n="11"/> the disciples came to him and said, <lb
                            n="12"/> ”This is a remote place, and it's already getting late. <lb
                            n="13"/> Send the crowds away, so they can go to the villages <lb n="14"
                        /> and buy themselves some food.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="15"/> “They do not need to go away. You give them
                        something <lb n="16"/> to eat.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“We have <lb n="17"/> here only five loaves of bread and two <lb n="18"/>
                        fish,” they answered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Bring them here to me,” he said. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>And he directed the people to sit down <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="32v"/> on the grass. Taking the five loaves <lb n="1"/> and the two
                        fish and looking up to <lb n="2"/> heaven, he gave thanks and broke the
                        loaves. Then he gave them to the disciples <lb n="3"/>, and the disciples
                        gave them to the people. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>They all ate and were satisfied, <lb n="5"/> and the disciples picked up
                        twelve <lb n="6"/> basketfuls of broken pieces that were left over.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>The number of those who ate <lb n="7"/> was about five <lb n="8"/> thousand
                        men, besides women <lb n="9"/> and children.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately Jesus made the disciples <lb n="10"/> get into the boat and go on
                        ahead <lb n="11"/> of him to the other side, while he dismissed <lb n="12"/>
                        the crowd.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>After he had dismissed them, he went up <lb n="13"/> on a mountainside by
                        himself to pray. Later that night, he was there alone, <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>and the boat <lb n="15"/> was already a considerable distance from land,
                        buffeted by the waves <lb n="16"/> because the wind was against it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Shortly <lb n="17"/> before dawn Jesus went out to them, walking <lb n="18"/>
                        on the lake.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>When the disciples saw him walking on <lb n="19"/> the lake, they were
                        terrified. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="33r"/> “It's a ghost,” they said, and <lb n="1"/> cried out in
                        fear.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus <lb n="2"/> immediately said to them: “Take courage! <lb n="3"/> It
                        is I. Don't be afraid.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“Lord, if it's you,” Peter replied, <lb n="4"/> “tell <lb n="5"/> me to come
                        to you on the water.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“Come,” <lb n="6"/> he said. Then Peter got down out of the boat, <lb n="7"/>
                        walked on the water and <lb n="8"/> came toward Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>But when he saw the wind <lb n="9"/>, he was afraid and, beginning <lb n="10"
                        /> to sink, cried out, “Lord, save me!” <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately Jesus reached out his hand <lb n="12"/> and caught him. “You of
                        little <lb n="13"/> faith,” he said, “why did you doubt?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>And when they climbed into the boat, <lb n="14"/> the wind died down. <lb
                            n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Then those who were in the boat <lb n="16"/> worshiped him, saying, “Truly
                        you are <lb n="17"/> the Son of God.” </p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had crossed over <lb n="18"/>, they landed at Gennesaret. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>And <lb n="19"/> when the men of that place recognized Jesus, they <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="33v"/> sent word to all the surrounding country. <lb n="1"/> People
                        brought all their sick to him <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>and begged him to let the sick just touch the edge <lb n="3"/> of his cloak,
                        and all who touched it <lb n="4"/> were healed. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Then some Pharisees and teachers of <lb n="6"/> the law came to Jesus from
                        Jerusalem and asked, <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why do your disciples break <lb n="8"/> the tradition of the elders? They
                        don't wash <lb n="9"/> their hands before they eat!” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “And <lb n="11"/> why do you break the command <lb n="12"/> of
                        God for the sake of your tradition? <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>For God said, 'Honor your father <lb n="14"/> and mother' and 'Anyone who
                        curses their father or <lb n="15"/> mother is to be put to death.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>But <lb n="16"/> you say that if anyone declares that what might have been
                        used to help their father or <lb n="17"/> mother is <lb n="18"/> 'devoted to
                        God,'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>they are not to 'honor <lb n="19"/> their father or mother' <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="34r"/> with it. Thus you nullify the word of God for the sake <lb
                            n="1"/> of your tradition.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>You hypocrites! <lb n="2"/> Isaiah was right when he prophesied about you:
                            <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>“'These people honor me with their lips, but <lb n="4"/> their hearts are far
                        from me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="5"/> They worship me in vain; their teachings <lb n="6"/> are merely
                        human rules.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus called <lb n="7"/> the crowd to him and said, “Listen and understand.
                            <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>What goes into someone's mouth does not defile <lb n="9"/> them, but what
                        comes out of their mouth, that is what <lb n="10"/> defiles them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="11"/> the disciples came to him and asked, “Do you know that the
                        Pharisees <lb n="12"/> were offended when they heard this?” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “Every plant <lb n="14"/> that my heavenly Father <lb n="15"/>
                        has not planted will be pulled up by the roots.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Leave them; they are blind guides <lb n="16"/>. If the blind lead the blind,
                        <lb/> both will fall into <lb n="18"/> a pit.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter said, <lb n="19"/> “Explain the parable to <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="34v"/> us.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“Are you still so dull?” <lb n="1"/> Jesus asked them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“Don't you see that <lb n="2"/> whatever enters the mouth goes into the
                        stomach <lb n="3"/> and then out of the body?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>But the things <lb n="4"/> that come out of a person's mouth come from the
                        heart, <lb n="5"/> and these defile them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>For out of the heart <lb n="6"/> come evil thoughts-murder, <lb n="7"/>
                        adultery, sexual immorality, theft, <lb n="8"/> false testimony,
                        slander.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>These <lb n="9"/> are what defile a person; <lb n="10"/> but eating with <lb
                            n="11"/> unwashed hands does not defile them.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Leaving that place, <lb n="12"/> Jesus withdrew to the region of Tyre and <lb
                            n="13"/> Sidon.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>A Canaanite woman <lb n="14"/> from that vicinity came to him, crying out,
                            <lb n="15"/> “Lord, Son of David, have mercy on me! My daughter is <lb
                            n="16"/> demon-possessed and suffering terribly.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus did not answer <lb n="17"/> a word. So his disciples came to him and
                        urged him, <lb n="18"/> “Send her away, for she keeps crying out after <lb
                            n="19"/> us.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>He answered, “I was <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="35r"/> sent only to the lost sheep <lb n="1"/> of Israel.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>The woman came <lb n="2"/> and knelt before him. “Lord, help <lb n="3"/> me!”
                        she said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “It is not right <lb n="4"/> to take the children's bread and
                        toss it to the dogs.” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“Yes it is, Lord,” she said. “Even the dogs <lb n="6"/> eat the crumbs that
                        fall from <lb n="7"/> their master's table.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said to her <lb n="8"/>, “Woman, you have great faith! <lb n="9"/>
                        Your request is granted.” And her daughter was healed at <lb n="10"/> that
                        moment.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus left there and went along <lb n="11"/> the Sea of Galilee <lb n="12"/>
                        Then he went up on a mountainside and sat down. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Great crowds came to him, <lb n="14"/> bringing the lame, the blind, the
                        crippled, <lb n="15"/> the mute and many others, and laid them <lb n="16"/>
                        at his feet; and he healed them. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>The people were amazed when they saw <lb n="18"/> the mute speaking, the
                        crippled made well, the lame walking and the blind seeing. <lb n="19"/> And
                        they praised the God of Israel. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="35v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus called his disciples <lb n="1"/> to him and said, “I have compassion
                        for these people; <lb n="2"/> they have already been <lb n="3"/> with me
                        three days and have nothing <lb n="4"/> to eat. I do not want to send them
                        away hungry, <lb n="5"/> or they may collapse on the way.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>His disciples answered, <lb n="6"/> “Where could we get enough bread <lb
                            n="7"/> in this remote place to feed such a crowd?” <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>“How many loaves do you have?” <lb n="9"/> Jesus asked. “Seven,” they
                        replied, “and a few small fish.” <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>He told the crowd to sit down <lb n="11"/> on the ground.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he took the seven <lb n="12"/> loaves and the fish, and when he had
                        given thanks, he broke them <lb n="13"/> and gave them to the disciples, and
                        they in turn to the people. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>They all ate and <lb n="15"/> were satisfied. Afterward the disciples picked
                        up seven basketfuls of broken pieces <lb n="16"/> that were left over. <lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>The number of those who ate was four <lb n="18"/> thousand men, besides women
                            <lb n="19"/> and children.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>After Jesus had sent the crowd away, he got <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="36r"/> into the boat and went to the vicinity of Magadan. <lb n="1"
                        /></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>The Pharisees and Sadducees <lb n="2"/> came to Jesus and tested him by
                        asking him to show them a sign <lb n="3"/> from heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, <lb n="4"/> “When evening comes, you say, <lb n="5"/> 'It will be
                        fair weather, <lb n="6"/> for the sky is red,'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>and in the morning, 'Today it will be stormy, <lb n="7"/> for the sky is red
                        and overcast.' <lb n="8"/> You know how to interpret the appearance of the
                        sky, <lb n="9"/> but you cannot interpret the signs of the times.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>A wicked <lb n="10"/> and adulterous generation looks for a sign <lb n="11"
                        />, but none will be given it except the sign of Jonah.” <lb n="12"/> Jesus
                        then left them and went away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>When they went <lb n="13"/> across the lake, the disciples forgot <lb n="14"
                        /> to take bread.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“Be careful,” Jesus said <lb n="15"/> to them. “Be on your guard against the
                        yeast of the Pharisees <lb n="16"/> and Sadducees.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>They discussed this among themselves and said, <lb n="17"/> “It is because we
                        didn't bring any bread.” <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Aware of their discussion <lb n="19"/>, Jesus asked, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="36v"/> “You of little faith, why are you talking among yourselves
                        about <lb n="1"/> having no bread?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Do you still not understand? <lb n="2"/> Don't you remember the five loaves
                            <lb n="3"/> for the five thousand, and how many <lb n="4"/> basketfuls
                        you gathered?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Or the seven loaves <lb n="5"/> for the four thousand, and how many
                        basketfuls you <lb n="6"/> gathered?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>How is it you don't understand <lb n="7"/> that I was not talking to you
                        about bread? But be on your guard against the yeast of <lb n="8"/> the
                        Pharisees and Sadducees.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="9"/> they understood that he was not telling them to guard <lb
                            n="10"/> against the yeast used in bread, but against the teaching of
                        the Pharisees <lb n="11"/> and Sadducees. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus came to the region of Caesarea <lb n="13"/> Philippi, he asked his
                        disciples, <lb n="14"/> “Who do people say the Son <lb n="15"/> of Man
                        is?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>They replied, “Some say John the Baptist; <lb n="16"/> others say Elijah; and
                        still others, <lb n="17"/> Jeremiah or one of the prophets.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“But what about you?” <lb n="18"/> he asked. “Who do you say I am?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Simon Peter answered <lb n="19"/>, “You are the Messiah, the <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="37r"/> Son of the living God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="1"/> “Blessed are you, Simon son of Jonah, <lb n="2"/>
                        for this was not revealed to you <lb n="3"/> by flesh and blood, but by my
                        Father in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>And I <lb n="4"/> tell you that you are Peter, <lb n="5"/> and on this rock I
                        will build my church, <lb n="6"/> and the gates of Hades will not overcome
                            <lb n="7"/> it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; <lb n="8"/> whatever you
                        bind on <lb n="9"/> earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever <lb n="10"/>
                        you loose on earth will be loosed <lb n="11"/> in heaven.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he ordered his disciples <lb n="12"/> not to tell anyone that he was <lb
                            n="13"/> the Messiah.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>From that time on Jesus began to explain to his disciples <lb n="14"/> that
                        he must go <lb n="15"/> to Jerusalem and suffer many things at the hands of
                        the elders, <lb n="16"/> the chief priests and the teachers of the law, <lb
                            n="17"/> and that he must be killed and on the third day be raised to
                        life.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="18"/> Peter took him aside and began to rebuke <lb n="19"/> him.
                        ”Never, Lord!” he said. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="37v"/> “This shall never happen to you!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus turned and said to Peter, <lb n="1"/> “Get behind me, Satan! <lb n="2"
                        /> You are a stumbling block to me; you do not have in mind the concerns of
                        God, <lb n="3"/> but merely human concerns.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said <lb n="4"/> to his disciples, “Whoever wants to be my
                        disciple <lb n="5"/> must deny themselves and take up <lb n="6"/> their
                        cross and follow me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>For whoever <lb n="7"/> wants to save their life <lb n="8"/> will lose it,
                        but whoever loses their life <lb n="9"/> for me will find it. <lb n="10"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>What good will it be for someone to gain <lb n="11"/> the whole world, yet
                        forfeit their soul? <lb n="12"/> Or what can anyone give <lb n="13"/> in
                        exchange for their soul? <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>For the Son of Man is going to come <lb n="15"/> in his Father's glory with
                        his angels, and <lb n="16"/> then he will reward each person according to
                        what they have done. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you, some who <lb n="18"/> are standing here will not <lb
                            n="19"/> taste death before they see the <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="38r"/> Son of Man coming in his kingdom.” <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>After six days Jesus took with him <lb n="2"/> Peter, James and John the
                        brother of James, <lb n="3"/> and led them up a high mountain <lb n="4"/> by
                        themselves.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>There he was transfigured <lb n="5"/> before them. His face shone like the
                        sun <lb n="6"/>, and his clothes <lb n="7"/> became as white as the
                        light.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Just then <lb n="8"/> there appeared before them Moses and Elijah, <lb n="9"
                        /> talking with Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter said to Jesus, <lb n="10"/> “Lord, it is good for us to be <lb n="11"/>
                        here. If you wish, I will put up three <lb n="12"/> shelters-one for you,
                        one for Moses <lb n="13"/> and one for Elijah.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>While he was still speaking <lb n="14"/>, a bright cloud covered them, and
                            <lb n="15"/> a voice from the cloud said, “This is my Son <lb n="16"/>,
                        whom I love; with him I am well pleased. <lb n="17"/> Listen to him!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>When the <lb n="18"/> disciples heard this, they fell facedown to the ground,
                            <lb n="19"/> terrified.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="38v"/> came and touched them. “Get up,” he said. <lb n="1"/> “Don't
                        be afraid.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>When they looked up <lb n="2"/>, they saw no one except <lb n="3"/>
                        Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>As they were coming down the mountain, <lb n="4"/> Jesus instructed them,
                        “Don't tell anyone what you have seen, <lb n="5"/> until the Son of Man has
                        been raised from the dead.” <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples asked him, <lb n="7"/> “Why then do the teachers of the law say
                            <lb n="8"/> that Elijah must come first?” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “To be sure, Elijah comes and will restore all things.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>But I tell you, Elijah has already <lb n="10"/> come, and they did not
                        recognize him, but have done <lb n="11"/> to him everything they wished. <lb
                            n="12"/> In the same way the Son of Man is going to suffer at their
                        hands.” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the disciples understood <lb n="14"/> that he was talking to them about
                        John the Baptist. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>When they came to the crowd, <lb n="16"/> a man approached Jesus and knelt
                        before <lb n="17"/> him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“Lord, have mercy on my son,” <lb n="18"/> he said. “He has seizures and is
                        suffering greatly. <lb n="19"/> He often falls into the fire or into the <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="39r"/> water.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>I brought him to your disciples, <lb n="1"/> but they could not heal
                        him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="2"/> “You unbelieving and <lb n="3"/> perverse generation,” Jesus
                        replied, “how long shall I stay with you? <lb n="4"/> How long shall I put
                        up with you? Bring the boy here <lb n="5"/> to me.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus rebuked the demon, <lb n="6"/> and it came out of the boy, and he was
                        healed <lb n="7"/> at that moment.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the disciples <lb n="8"/> came to Jesus in private and asked, “Why <lb
                            n="9"/> couldn't we drive it out?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, <lb n="10"/> “Because you have so little faith. <lb n="11"/>
                        Truly I tell you, if you have <lb n="12"/> faith as small as a mustard seed,
                        you can say <lb n="13"/> to this mountain, 'Move from here to there,' and
                            <lb n="14"/> it will move. Nothing will be impossible for you.” <lb
                            n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="16"/>
                        <lb n="17"/> When they came together in Galilee, he said to them, <lb n="18"
                        /> “The Son of Man is going to be delivered into the hands <lb n="19"/> of
                        men.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>They will kill him, and on the third <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="39v"/> day he will be raised to life.” And the disciples were filled
                        with grief.<lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>After Jesus and his disciples arrived in Capernaum, <lb n="2"/> the
                        collectors of the two-drachma temple tax came <lb n="3"/> to Peter and
                        asked, “Doesn't your teacher <lb n="4"/> pay the temple tax?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“Yes, he does,” he replied.<lb n="5"/> When Peter came into the house, <lb
                            n="6"/> Jesus was the first to speak. “What do you think, Simon?” <lb
                            n="7"/> he asked. “From whom do the kings of the earth collect duty and
                        taxes <lb n="8"/> -from their own children or from others?” <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“From others,” Peter answered. <lb n="10"/> “Then the children are exempt,”
                        Jesus said to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“But so that we may not <lb n="11"/> cause offense, go to the lake <lb n="12"
                        /> and throw out your line. Take the first <lb n="13"/> fish you catch; <lb
                            n="14"/> open its mouth and you will find a four-drachma coin. Take it
                        and <lb n="15"/> give it to them for my tax and yours.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time <lb n="16"/> the disciples came to Jesus and asked, “Who, <lb
                            n="17"/> then, is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?” <lb n="18"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>He called a little child to him, and placed <lb n="19"/> the child among
                        them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>And he said: “Truly I tell you <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="40r"/>, unless you change and become like little children <lb n="1"
                        />, you will never enter <lb n="2"/> the kingdom of heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore, whoever <lb n="3"/> takes the lowly position of this child <lb
                            n="4"/> is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>And whoever <lb n="5"/> welcomes one such child <lb n="6"/> in my name
                        welcomes me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“If anyone <lb n="7"/> causes one of these little ones-those <lb n="8"/> who
                        believe in me-to stumble, it would be better for them to have a <lb n="9"/>
                        large millstone hung around <lb n="10"/> their neck and to be drowned in the
                        depths of <lb n="11"/> the sea.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Woe to the world because of the things that cause people to stumble! <lb
                            n="12"/> Such things must come <lb n="13"/>, but woe to the person <lb
                            n="14"/> through whom they come!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>If your hand or your foot causes you to stumble <lb n="15"/>
                        <lb n="16"/>, cut it off and throw it away. <lb n="17"/> It is better for
                        you to enter life maimed <lb n="18"/> or crippled than to have two hands or
                            <lb n="19"/> two feet and be thrown into eternal fire. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="40v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>And if your eye causes you to stumble, <lb n="1"/> gouge it out and throw it
                        away. It is better <lb n="2"/> for you to enter life with one eye <lb n="3"
                        /> than to have two eyes and be thrown <lb n="4"/> into the fire of
                        hell.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>“See <lb n="5"/> that you do not despise <lb n="6"/> one of these little
                        ones. <lb n="7"/> For I tell you that their angels in heaven always <lb
                            n="8"/> see the face of my Father in heaven. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p><note place="margin" type="gloss"> This verse is found in the Latin Vulgate
                            and not in the NIV translation.</note><lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you think? <lb n="11"/> If a man owns a hundred sheep, <lb n="12"/>
                        and one of them wanders away, will he not leave <lb n="13"/> the ninety-nine
                        on the hills <lb n="14"/> and go to look for the one that wandered off?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>And <lb n="15"/> if he finds it, truly I tell <lb n="16"/> you, he is happier
                        about that one sheep than <lb n="17"/> about the ninety-nine that did <lb
                            n="18"/> not wander off.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way your <lb n="19"/> Father in heaven is not willing that <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="41r"/> any of these little ones should perish. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“If your brother or sister sins, go <lb n="2"/> and point out their fault,
                        just between the two of you <lb n="3"/>. If they listen to you, you have won
                        them over. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>But if they will not listen, take one or two others along <lb n="5"/>, so
                        that every matter may be established by the testimony of two <lb n="6"/> or
                        three witnesses.' <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>If they still refuse to listen, tell it to the church; <lb n="8"/> and if
                        they refuse to listen even to the church, treat them as <lb n="9"/> you
                        would a pagan or a tax collector.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you, whatever you bind <lb n="11"/> on earth will be bound in
                        heaven, <lb n="12"/> and whatever you loose on <lb n="13"/> earth will be
                        loosed in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“Again, <lb n="14"/> truly I tell you that if two of you <lb n="15"/> on
                        earth agree about <lb n="16"/> anything they ask for, it will be done for
                        them <lb n="17"/> by my Father in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>For where <lb n="18"/> two or three gather in my name <lb n="19"/>, there am
                        I with them." <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="41v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Peter came to Jesus and asked, <lb n="1"/> “Lord, how many times shall I
                        forgive my brother or sister <lb n="2"/> who sins against me? Up to seven
                        times?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered, <lb n="3"/> “I tell you, not seven times, but seventy- <lb
                            n="4"/> seven times.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore, the kingdom <lb n="5"/> of heaven is like a king who wanted <lb
                            n="6"/> to settle accounts with his servants.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>As he <lb n="7"/> began the settlement, a man who owed <lb n="8"/> him ten
                        thousand bags <lb n="9"/> of gold was brought to him. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Since he was not able to pay, <lb n="11"/> the master ordered that he and his
                        wife and his children and all that he had be sold to repay the debt. <lb
                            n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“At this the servant fell on <lb n="13"/> his knees before him. 'Be patient
                        with me,' <lb n="14"/> he begged, 'and I will pay back everything.' <lb
                            n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>The servant's master took pity on him, canceled <lb n="16"/> the debt and let
                        him go.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“But when <lb n="17"/> that servant went out, he found one of his fellow
                        servants <lb n="18"/> who owed him a hundred silver coins. <lb n="19"/> He
                        grabbed him and began to choke him. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="42r"/> 'Pay back what you owe me!' he demanded.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“His fellow servant fell to <lb n="1"/> his knees and begged him, 'Be patient
                            <lb n="2"/> with me, and I will pay it back.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>“But <lb n="3"/> he refused. Instead, he went off and had the man thrown <lb
                            n="4"/> into prison until he could pay the debt.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>When the other servants saw <lb n="5"/> what had happened, <lb n="6"/> they
                        were outraged and went <lb n="7"/> and told their master everything that <lb
                            n="8"/> had happened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then the master <lb n="9"/> called the servant in. 'You wicked servant,' he
                        said, 'I canceled all that debt <lb n="10"/> of yours because you begged me
                        to. <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Shouldn't you have had mercy on <lb n="12"/> your fellow servant just as I
                        had on you?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="13"/> In anger his master handed him over to the jailers to be
                        tortured, <lb n="14"/> until he should pay back all he owed. <lb n="15"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>“This is how my heavenly Father will treat each <lb n="16"/> of you unless
                        you forgive <lb n="17"/> your brother or sister from your heart.”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="18"/>When Jesus had finished saying these things <lb n="19"/>, he left
                        Galilee and went into the <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="42v"/> region of Judea to the other side of the Jordan.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="1"/> Large crowds followed him, and he healed <lb n="2"/> them
                        there.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Some Pharisees came to him <lb n="3"/> to test him. They asked, “Is it lawful
                        for <lb n="4"/> a man to divorce his wife for any and <lb n="5"/> every
                        reason?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>“Haven't you read,” he replied, <lb n="6"/> “that at the beginning the
                        Creator <lb n="7"/> 'made them male and female,'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>and said, <lb n="8"/> 'For this reason a man will leave his father and <lb
                            n="9"/> mother and be united to his wife, and <lb n="10"/> the two will
                        become one flesh'?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>So they are no longer <lb n="11"/> two, but one flesh. Therefore what God has
                        joined together, <lb n="12"/> let no one separate.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why then,” they asked, <lb n="13"/> “did Moses command that a man give his
                        wife a certificate of divorce <lb n="14"/> and send her away?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="15"/> “Moses permitted you to divorce your wives
                        because your hearts were hard. <lb n="16"/> But it was not this way <lb
                            n="17"/> from the beginning.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>I tell you <lb n="18"/> that anyone who divorces his wife <lb n="19"/> except
                        for sexual immorality, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="43r"/> and marries another woman <lb n="1"/> commits adultery.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>The disciples said <lb n="2"/> to him, “If this is the situation between a
                        husband and wife <lb n="3"/>, it is better not to marry.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “Not <lb n="4"/> everyone can accept this word, but <lb n="5"
                        /> only those to whom it has been given.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>For there are eunuchs <lb n="6"/> who were born that way, <lb n="7"/> and
                        there are eunuchs who have been made eunuchs by others <lb n="8"/> -and
                        there are those who choose to live like eunuchs <lb n="9"/> for the sake of
                        the kingdom of heaven. <lb n="10"/> The one who can accept this should
                        accept it.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="11"/> people brought little children to Jesus for him to place
                        his hands on them and pray for them. <lb n="12"/> But the disciples rebuked
                        them. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said, “Let the little children come to me, and <lb n="14"/> do not
                        hinder them, <lb n="15"/> for the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as
                        these.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="16"/> he had placed his hands on them, he went on from there. <lb
                            n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Just then a man came up to Jesus and asked, “Teacher, <lb n="18"/> what good
                        thing must I do to get <lb n="19"/> eternal life ?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why do you ask <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="43v"/> me about what is good?” Jesus replied. “There is only One who
                        is good. <lb n="1"/> If you want to enter life, <lb n="2"/> keep the
                        commandments.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“Which ones?” he inquired. Jesus <lb n="3"/> replied, “'You shall not murder,
                        you shall not <lb n="4"/> commit adultery, you shall not steal, you shall
                        not <lb n="5"/> give false testimony,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>honor <lb n="6"/> your father and mother,' and 'love <lb n="7"/> your
                        neighbor as yourself.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>“All these <lb n="8"/> I have kept,” the young man said. <lb n="9"/> “What do
                        I still lack?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered, “If you want <lb n="10"/> to be perfect, go, sell your
                        possessions and <lb n="11"/> give to the poor, and you will have <lb n="12"
                        /> treasure in heaven. Then come, follow <lb n="13"/> me.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>When the young man <lb n="14"/> heard this, he went away sad, because <lb/>
                        he had great wealth.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus <lb n="16"/> said to his disciples, <lb n="17"/> ”Truly I tell
                        you, it is hard for someone who is rich <lb n="18"/> to enter the kingdom of
                        heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Again I tell you <lb n="19"/>, it is easier for a camel <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="44r"/> to go through the eye of a needle than for someone who is rich
                            <lb n="1"/> to enter the kingdom of God.” <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>When the disciples heard this, <lb n="3"/> they were greatly astonished and
                        asked, “Who then <lb n="4"/> can be saved?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus looked at them <lb n="5"/> and said, “With man this is impossible, <lb
                            n="6"/> but with God all things are possible.” <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter answered him, <lb n="8"/> “We have left everything to follow you! <lb
                            n="9"/> What then will there be for us?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to them, “Truly I tell you, <lb n="10"/>
                        <lb n="11"/> at the renewal of all things, <lb n="12"/> when the Son of Man
                            <lb n="13"/> sits on his glorious throne, you who have followed me will
                        also sit <lb n="14"/> on twelve thrones, judging <lb n="15"/> the twelve
                        tribes of Israel.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>And everyone who <lb n="16"/> has left houses or brothers or <lb n="17"/>
                        sisters or father or mother <lb n="18"/> or wife or children or fields <lb
                            n="19"/> for my sake will receive a hundred times as much <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="44v"/> and will inherit eternal life. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>But many who are first <lb n="2"/> will be last, and many who are last will
                        be first.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="3"/> “For the kingdom of heaven is like a landowner <lb n="4"/> who
                        went out early in the morning to hire <lb n="5"/> workers for his
                        vineyard.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>He agreed <lb n="6"/> to pay them <lb n="7"/> a denarius for the day and sent
                        them into his vineyard.<lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>“About nine in the morning <lb n="9"/> he went out and saw others standing in
                        the marketplace doing nothing. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>He told them, 'You also go and work in my vineyard, <lb n="11"/> and I will
                        pay you whatever is right.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="12"/> they went. “He went out again about <lb n="13"/> noon and
                        about three in the afternoon and did the same thing. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>About five in the afternoon he went out and <lb n="15"/> found still others
                        standing around. He asked them, <lb n="16"/> 'Why have you been standing
                        here all day long doing nothing?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“'Because <lb n="17"/> no one has hired us,' they answered. ”He said to them,
                        'You also go and work <lb n="18"/> in my vineyard.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>“When evening came, <lb n="19"/> the owner of the vineyard said to his
                        foreman, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="45r"/> 'Call the workers and pay <lb n="1"/> them their wages,
                        beginning with the last ones hired and going <lb n="2"/> on to the
                        first.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“The workers <lb n="3"/> who were hired about five in the <lb n="4"/>
                        afternoon came and each received a denarius. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>So when those came who were hired first, <lb n="6"/> they expected to receive
                        more. But each one of <lb n="7"/> them also received a denarius. <lb n="8"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>When they received it, they began to grumble <lb n="9"/> against the
                        landowner.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="10"/> 'These who were hired last worked only one hour,' <lb n="11"/>
                        they said, 'and you have made them equal to us who have <lb n="12"/> borne
                        the burden of the work and the heat of the day.' <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“But he answered one of them, <lb n="14"/> 'I am not being unfair to you,
                        friend. Didn't <lb n="15"/> you agree to work for a denarius? <lb n="16"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Take your pay and go. I want <lb n="17"/> to give the one who was hired last
                        the same as I gave <lb n="18"/> you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Don't I have the right to do what <lb n="19"/> I want with my own money? Or
                        are you envious <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="45v"/> because I am generous?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="1"/> “So the last will be first <lb n="2"/>, and the first will be
                        last.” <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Now Jesus was going up to Jerusalem. <lb n="4"/> On the way, he took the
                        Twelve <lb n="5"/> aside and said to them,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>“We are going up <lb n="6"/> to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be
                        delivered over to <lb n="7"/> the chief priests and the teachers of the law.
                            <lb n="8"/> They will condemn him to death</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>and will hand <lb n="9"/> him over to the Gentiles to be mocked and flogged
                            <lb n="10"/> and crucified. On the third day he will <lb n="11"/> be
                        raised to life!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the mother <lb n="12"/> of Zebedee's sons came to Jesus with her sons
                        and, kneeling down, <lb n="13"/> asked a favor of him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“What is it you want?” <lb n="14"/> he asked. She said, “Grant that one of
                        these two sons <lb n="15"/> of mine may sit at your right and the other <lb
                            n="16"/> at your left in your kingdom.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="17"/> “You don't know what you are asking,” Jesus said to them. “Can
                        you <lb n="18"/> drink the cup I am going to drink?” <lb n="19"/> ”We can,”
                        they answered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to them, “You will indeed drink from my cup <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="46r"/>, but to sit at <lb n="1"/> my right or left is not <lb n="2"/>
                        for me to grant. These places belong to those for whom they have been
                        prepared <lb n="3"/> by my Father.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>When the ten heard <lb n="4"/> about this, they were indignant with the two
                        brothers. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus called them together and said, <lb n="6"/> “You know that the rulers of
                        the Gentiles lord it over <lb n="7"/> them, and their high officials <lb
                            n="8"/> exercise authority over them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Not so with you. Instead <lb n="9"/>, whoever wants to become great among <lb
                            n="10"/> you must be your servant, <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>and whoever wants to be first must be <lb n="12"/> your slave</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>just as the Son of Man <lb n="13"/> did not come to be served, but to serve,
                            <lb n="14"/> and to give his life as a ransom <lb n="15"/> for
                        many.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus and <lb n="16"/> his disciples were leaving Jericho, <lb n="17"/> a
                        large crowd followed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>Two blind men were sitting by <lb n="18"/> the roadside, and when they heard
                        that Jesus was going by, <lb n="19"/> they shouted, “Lord, Son of David, <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="46v"/> have mercy on us!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>The crowd rebuked <lb n="1"/> them and told them to be quiet, <lb n="2"/> but
                        they shouted all the louder, “Lord, <lb n="3"/> Son of David, have mercy on
                        us!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus stopped and called them. <lb n="4"/> “What do you want me to do for <lb
                            n="5"/> you?” he asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“Lord,” they answered, <lb n="6"/> “we want our sight.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus had compassion <lb n="7"/> on them and touched their eyes. <lb n="8"/>
                        Immediately they received their sight and followed him. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>As they approached Jerusalem <lb n="10"/> and came to Bethphage on the Mount
                            <lb n="11"/> of Olives, Jesus sent two disciples, <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>saying to them, “Go to the village <lb n="13"/> ahead of you, and at once you
                        will find a donkey <lb n="14"/> tied there, with her colt by her. Untie them
                            <lb n="15"/> and bring them to me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>If anyone says anything to you <lb n="16"/>, say that the Lord needs them,
                            <lb n="17"/> and he will send them right away.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>This took place to fulfill <lb n="18"/> what <lb n="19"/> was spoken through
                        the prophet <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="47r"/>:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“Say to Daughter Zion, 'See, your king comes <lb n="1"/> to you, gentle and
                        riding on a donkey, <lb n="2"/> and on a colt, the foal of a donkey.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="3"/> The disciples went and did as <lb n="4"/> Jesus had instructed
                        them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>They brought the donkey and <lb n="5"/> the colt and placed their cloaks <lb
                            n="6"/> on them for Jesus to sit on.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>A very <lb n="7"/> large crowd spread their cloaks <lb n="8"/> on the road,
                        while others cut branches from the trees <lb n="9"/> and spread them on the
                        road.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>The crowds <lb n="10"/> that went ahead of him and those that followed <lb
                            n="11"/> shouted, “Hosanna to the Son of David!” <lb n="12"/> ”Blessed
                        is he who comes in the name <lb n="13"/> of the Lord!” “Hosanna in the
                        highest heaven!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus entered Jerusalem, the whole city <lb n="14"/> was stirred and <lb
                            n="15"/> asked, “Who is this?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>The crowds <lb n="16"/> answered, “This is Jesus, the prophet from Nazareth
                            <lb n="17"/> in Galilee.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus entered the temple courts <lb n="18"/> and drove out all who were
                        buying and selling <lb n="19"/> there. He overturned the tables of the money
                        changers <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="47v"/> and the benches of those selling doves. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“It is written,” he said to them, <lb n="2"/> “'My house will be called a
                        house of prayer,' <lb n="3"/> but you are making it 'a den of robbers.'” <lb
                            n="4"/>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>The blind and <lb n="5"/> the lame came to him at the temple, and he healed
                        them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>But when <lb n="6"/> the chief priests and <lb n="7"/> the teachers of the
                        law saw the wonderful things he did and the children <lb n="8"/> shouting in
                        the temple courts, “Hosanna <lb n="9"/> to the Son of David,” they were
                        indignant.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do you hear <lb n="10"/> what these children are <lb n="11"/> saying?” they
                        asked him. “Yes,” replied Jesus, “have you never read, <lb n="12"/> “'From
                        the lips of children and infants you, Lord, have called forth your <lb
                            n="13"/> praise'?"</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>And he left them and went <lb n="14"/> out of the city to Bethany, where he
                        spent the night. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Early in the morning, as Jesus was on his way back to the city, <lb n="16"/>
                        he was hungry.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Seeing a fig tree <lb n="17"/> by the road, he went up to it but found
                        nothing <lb n="18"/> on it except leaves. <lb n="19"/> Then he said to it,
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="48r"/> “May you never bear fruit again!” Immediately <lb n="1"/> the
                        tree withered.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>When the disciples saw this, <lb n="2"/> they were amazed. “How did the fig
                        tree wither so quickly?” <lb n="3"/> they asked.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="4"/> “Truly I tell you, if you have faith <lb n="5"/>
                        and do not doubt, not only can you do what was done to the fig tree, <lb
                            n="6"/> but also you can say to this mountain, 'Go, <lb n="7"/> throw
                        yourself into the sea,' and it will be done.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>If you believe, you will <lb n="8"/> receive <lb n="9"/> whatever you ask for
                        in prayer.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus entered <lb n="10"/> the temple courts, and, while he was teaching, <lb
                            n="11"/> the chief priests and the elders of the people <lb n="12"/>
                        came to him. “By what authority are you doing these things?” <lb n="13"/>
                        they asked. “And who gave you this authority?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="14"/> “I will also ask you one question. <lb n="15"/>
                        If you answer me, I will tell you by what <lb n="16"/> authority I am doing
                            <lb n="17"/> these things.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>John's baptism-<lb n="18"/> where did it come from? Was it from heaven, or of
                        human origin?” They discussed it <lb n="19"/> among themselves and said, “If
                        we say, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="48v"/> 'From heaven,' he will ask, 'Then why didn't you believe <lb
                            n="1"/> him?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>But if we say, 'Of human <lb n="2"/> origin'-we are afraid of the people, for
                            <lb n="3"/> they all hold that John was a prophet.” <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>So they answered Jesus, “We don't know.” <lb n="5"/> Then he said, ”Neither
                        will I tell you by what authority <lb n="6"/> I am doing these things.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“What do you <lb n="7"/> think? There was a man who had two sons. <lb n="8"/>
                        He went to the first and said, 'Son, go and work <lb n="9"/> today in the
                        vineyard.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="10"/> “'I will not,' he answered, but later he changed his mind <lb
                            n="11"/> and went.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then <lb n="12"/> the father went to the other son and said the same thing.
                            <lb n="13"/> He answered, 'I will, sir,' but he did not go. <lb n="14"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>“Which of the two did what his <lb n="15"/> father wanted?” ”The first,” they
                        answered. Jesus said to them, “Truly I tell you, <lb n="16"/> the tax
                        collectors <lb n="17"/> and the prostitutes are entering the kingdom of <lb
                            n="18"/> God ahead of you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>For John came to you to show you <lb n="19"/> the way of righteousness, and
                        you did not believe him, but the tax collectors <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="49r"/> and the prostitutes did. <lb n="1"/> And even after you saw
                        this, <lb n="2"/> you did not repent and believe him. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“Listen to another parable: There was <lb n="4"/> a landowner who planted a
                        vineyard. <lb n="5"/> He put a wall around it, dug a winepress in it <lb
                            n="6"/> and built a watchtower. Then he rented <lb n="7"/> the vineyard
                        to some farmers and moved to another place. <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>When the harvest time approached, <lb n="9"/> he sent his servants to the
                        tenants <lb n="10"/> to collect his fruit.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>“The tenants <lb n="11"/> seized his servants; <lb n="12"/> they beat one,
                        killed another, <lb n="13"/> and stoned a third.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he sent other servants <lb n="14"/> to them, more than the first time,
                        and the tenants treated them <lb n="15"/> the same way.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Last of all, he sent his <lb n="16"/> son to them. 'They will respect <lb
                            n="17"/> my son,' he said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>“But when the tenants saw <lb n="18"/> the son, they said to each other,
                        'This is the heir. Come, let's kill <lb n="19"/> him and take <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="49v"/> his inheritance.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>So they took him and threw him <lb n="1"/> out of the vineyard and killed
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore, when <lb n="2"/> the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do
                        to those tenants?” <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>“He will bring those wretches to a wretched end,” they replied, “and he will
                        rent the vineyard <lb n="4"/> to other tenants, who will give him his share
                        of the crop at harvest <lb n="5"/> time.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus said to them, “Have you never <lb n="6"/> read in the Scriptures: ”'The
                        stone the builders <lb n="7"/> rejected has become the cornerstone; <lb
                            n="8"/> the Lord has done this, and it <lb n="9"/> is marvelous in our
                        eyes'?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore I tell you <lb n="10"/> that the kingdom of God will be taken away
                        from you and <lb n="11"/> given to a people who will produce its fruit.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>Anyone who <lb n="12"/> falls on this stone will be broken to pieces; <lb
                            n="13"/> anyone on whom it falls will be crushed.” <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>When the chief priests <lb n="15"/> and the Pharisees heard Jesus' parables,
                        they knew <lb n="16"/> he was talking about them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>They looked <lb n="17"/> for a way to arrest him, but they were afraid of the
                        crowd because the people <lb n="18"/> held that he was a prophet. <lb n="19"
                        /></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus spoke to them again in parables, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="50r"/> saying:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“The kingdom of heaven is like <lb n="1"/> a king who prepared <lb n="2"/> a
                        wedding banquet for his son.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>He sent his servants to those who had been invited to the banquet <lb n="3"/>
                        to tell them to come, but they refused <lb n="4"/> to come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then he sent some more servants and said, <lb n="5"/> 'Tell those who have
                        been invited that I have prepared my <lb n="6"/> dinner: My oxen and
                        fattened cattle have been butchered, and everything <lb n="7"/> is ready.
                        Come to the wedding banquet.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“But <lb n="8"/> they paid no attention and went off <lb n="9"/> one to his
                        field, another to his business. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>The rest seized his servants, <lb n="11"/> mistreated them and killed them.
                            <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>The king was enraged. <lb n="13"/> He sent his army and destroyed <lb n="14"
                        /> those murderers and burned their city. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then he said to his servants, 'The wedding banquet is <lb n="16"/> ready,
                        but those I invited did <lb n="17"/> not deserve to come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>So go to the street corners <lb n="18"/> and invite to the banquet anyone you
                        find.' <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>So the servants went out into <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="50v"/> the streets and gathered all the people they could find, <lb
                            n="1"/> the bad as well as the good, and <lb n="2"/> the wedding hall
                        was filled with guests.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>“But when <lb n="3"/> the king came in to see the guests, he noticed <lb
                            n="4"/> a man there who was not wearing wedding clothes. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>He asked, 'How did you get in here <lb n="6"/> without wedding clothes,
                        friend ?' The man was <lb n="7"/> speechless.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then the king told the attendants, 'Tie <lb n="8"/> him hand and foot, and
                        throw him outside, into <lb n="9"/> the darkness, where there will be
                        weeping and <lb n="10"/> gnashing of teeth.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>“For many are invited, <lb n="11"/> but few are chosen.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the Pharisees went out and <lb n="12"/> laid <lb n="13"/> plans to trap
                        him in his words.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>They sent <lb n="14"/> their disciples to him along with the Herodians. <lb
                            n="15"/> “Teacher,” they said, “we know that you are a man of integrity
                        and that you teach <lb n="16"/> the way of God in accordance with the truth.
                            <lb n="17"/> You aren't swayed by others, because you pay no attention
                            <lb n="18"/> to who they are.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Tell us then, <lb n="19"/> what is your opinion? Is it right to pay the
                        imperial tax to <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="51r"/> Caesar or not?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus, knowing <lb n="1"/> their evil intent, said, ”You hypocrites, <lb
                            n="2"/> why are you trying to trap me?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Show me the coin used <lb n="3"/> for paying the tax.” They brought him <lb
                            n="4"/> a denarius,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>and he asked them, “Whose <lb n="5"/> image is this? And whose
                        inscription?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“Caesar's,” they replied. <lb n="6"/> Then he said to them, ”So give back to
                        Caesar what is Caesar's, and to God what is God's.” <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>When they heard this, they were amazed. So they left him and <lb n="8"/> went
                        away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>That same day <lb n="9"/> the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection,
                            <lb n="10"/> came to him with a question.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="11"/> “Teacher,” they said, “Moses told us that if a man dies <lb
                            n="12"/> without having children, <lb n="13"/> his brother must marry
                        the widow and <lb n="14"/> raise up offspring for him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Now there <lb n="15"/> were seven brothers among us. The first one <lb n="16"
                        /> married and died, and since he had no <lb n="17"/> children, he left his
                        wife to his brother. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>The same thing happened to the second and third brother, <lb n="19"/> right
                        on down to the seventh.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Finally, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="51v"/> the woman died.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Now then, at the resurrection, <lb n="1"/> whose wife will she be of the
                        seven, since <lb n="2"/> all of them were married to her?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="3"/> “You are in error because you do not know the
                        Scriptures or <lb n="4"/> the power of God.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>At the resurrection people <lb n="5"/> will neither marry nor be given in
                        marriage; <lb n="6"/> they will be like the angels in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>But about the resurrection <lb n="7"/> of the dead-have you not read <lb
                            n="8"/> what God said to you,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>'I <lb n="9"/> am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, <lb n="10"/> and the
                        God of Jacob'? He is not the God of the dead but of the living.” <lb n="11"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>When the crowds heard this, they were astonished at <lb n="12"/> his
                        teaching.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Hearing that <lb n="13"/> Jesus had silenced the Sadducees, the Pharisees got
                            <lb n="14"/> together.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>One of them, <lb n="15"/> an expert in the law, tested him with <lb n="16"/>
                        this question:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>“Teacher, which is <lb n="17"/> the greatest commandment in the Law?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied: “'Love <lb n="18"/> the Lord your God with all your heart and
                        with all <lb n="19"/> your soul and with all your mind.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>This <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="52r"/> is the first and greatest commandment. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>And the second is like it: <lb n="2"/> 'Love your neighbor as yourself.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="3"/> All the Law and the Prophets hang <lb n="4"/> on these two
                        commandments.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>While the Pharisees were gathered <lb n="5"/> together, Jesus asked them,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>“What <lb n="6"/> do you think about the Messiah? Whose son is he?” <lb n="7"
                        /> “The son of David,” they replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>He said to them, “How is it then that <lb n="8"/> David, speaking by the
                        Spirit, calls him 'Lord'? For he says, <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>“'The Lord said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until <lb n="10"/> I put
                        your enemies under <lb n="11"/> your feet.”'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>If then David calls him <lb n="12"/> 'Lord,' how can he be his son?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>No one could <lb n="13"/> say a word in reply, and from that day on <lb
                            n="14"/> no one dared to ask him any more questions. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said to the crowds <lb n="16"/> and to his disciples:</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“The teachers of the law <lb n="17"/> and the Pharisees sit in Moses' seat.
                            <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>So you must be careful <lb n="19"/> to do everything they tell you. <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <lb n="52v"/> But do not do what they do, for they do not practice what they
                        preach. <lb n="1"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>They tie up heavy, cumbersome loads <lb n="2"/> and put them on other
                        people's shoulders, <lb n="3"/> but they themselves are not willing to lift
                        a finger <lb n="4"/> to move them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“Everything they do is done <lb n="5"/> for people to see: They make <lb
                            n="6"/> their phylacteries wide and the tassels on their garments long;
                            <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>they love the place of honor <lb n="8"/> at banquets and the most important
                        seats in the synagogues; <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>they love to be greeted with respect in the marketplaces and to be called <lb
                            n="10"/> 'Rabbi' by others.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>“But you are not <lb n="11"/> to be called 'Rabbi,' for you have one Teacher,
                            <lb n="12"/> and you are all brothers. <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>And do not call anyone on <lb n="14"/> earth 'father,' for you have one
                        Father, and he <lb n="15"/> is in heaven.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Nor are you to be called <lb n="16"/> instructors, for you have one
                        Instructor, the Messiah.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>The greatest among you will be <lb n="17"/> your servant. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>For those who exalt themselves will be humbled, <lb n="19"/> and those who
                        humble themselves will be exalted. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="53r"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law <lb n="1"/> and Pharisees, you hypocrites!
                        You shut the door of the kingdom <lb n="2"/> of heaven in people's faces.
                        You yourselves <lb n="3"/> do not enter, nor will you let those enter who
                        are trying to. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p/>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! <lb n="5"/>
                        You travel over land <lb n="6"/> and sea to win a single convert, <lb n="7"
                        /> and when you have succeeded, you make them <lb n="8"/> twice as much a
                        child of hell as you are.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, blind guides! <lb n="9"/> You say, 'If anyone swears by the
                        temple, <lb n="10"/> it means nothing; but anyone who swears by <lb n="11"/>
                        the gold of the temple is bound by that oath.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>You blind fools! <lb n="12"/> Which is greater: the gold, or the temple <lb
                            n="13"/> that makes the gold sacred?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>You also say, 'If anyone swears <lb n="14"/> by the altar, it means nothing;
                        but anyone who swears <lb n="15"/> by the gift on the altar <lb n="16"/> is
                        bound by that oath.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>You blind men! Which is greater: the gift, <lb n="17"/> or the altar that
                        makes the gift sacred? <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore, anyone who swears by the altar swears by it and by <lb n="19"/>
                        everything on it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>And anyone <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="53v"/> who swears by the temple swears by it and by the one <lb n="1"
                        /> who dwells in it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>And anyone who swears by heaven <lb n="2"/> swears by God's throne and by the
                        one who sits on it. <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! <lb n="4"/>
                        You give a tenth of your spices-mint, dill <lb n="5"/> and cumin. But you
                        have neglected <lb n="6"/> the more important matters of the law-justice,
                        mercy <lb n="7"/> and faithfulness. You should have practiced the latter,
                            <lb n="8"/> without neglecting the former.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>You blind guides! <lb n="9"/> You strain out a gnat but swallow a camel. <lb
                            n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, <lb n="11"/> you hypocrites!
                        You clean <lb n="12"/> the outside of the cup and dish, but inside they are
                            <lb n="13"/> full of greed and self-indulgence.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Blind Pharisee! <lb n="14"/> First clean the inside <lb n="15"/> of the cup
                        and dish, and then <lb n="16"/> the outside also will be clean.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law <lb n="17"/> and Pharisees, you hypocrites!
                        You are like <lb n="18"/> whitewashed tombs, <lb n="19"/> which look
                        beautiful on the outside but on the inside are <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="54r"/> full of the bones of the dead and everything <lb n="1"/>
                        unclean.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way, on the outside you appear to <lb n="2"/> people as righteous
                        but on the inside you are <lb n="3"/> full of hypocrisy and wickedness. <lb
                            n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! <lb n="5"/>
                        You build tombs for the prophets <lb n="6"/> and decorate the graves of the
                        righteous. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>And you say, 'If we had lived in the days of our ancestors, <lb n="8"/> we
                        would not have taken part with them in shedding <lb n="9"/> the blood of the
                        prophets.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="10"/> you testify against yourselves that you are <lb n="11"/> the
                        descendants of those who murdered the prophets. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>Go ahead, then, and complete what your ancestors started! <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>“You snakes! You brood of vipers! <lb n="14"/> How will you escape being
                        condemned to hell? <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore I am sending you prophets and sages <lb n="16"/> and teachers. Some
                        of them you will kill and crucify; <lb n="17"/> others you will flog in your
                        synagogues <lb n="18"/> and pursue from town <lb n="19"/> to town.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>And so upon you <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="54v"/> will come all the righteous blood that has been shed <lb n="1"
                        /> on earth, from the blood <lb n="2"/> of righteous Abel to the blood of
                        Zechariah <lb n="3"/> son of Berekiah, whom you murdered between <lb n="4"/>
                        the temple and the altar.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, <lb n="5"/> all this will come on this generation. <lb
                            n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>“Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill <lb n="7"/> the prophets and stone those
                        sent to you, <lb n="8"/> how often I have longed to gather your children
                        together <lb n="9"/>, as a hen gathers <lb n="10"/> her chicks under her
                        wings, and you were not willing. <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Look, your house is left to you <lb n="12"/> desolate.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>For I tell you, you will not see me <lb n="13"/> again until you say,
                        'Blessed <lb n="14"/> is he who comes in the name of the Lord.'”</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus left <lb n="15"/> the temple and was walking away when his disciples
                            <lb n="16"/> came up to him to call his attention to its <lb n="17"/>
                        buildings.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“Do you see all <lb n="18"/> these things?” he asked. “Truly I tell <lb
                            n="19"/> you, not one stone here will be left on another; <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="55r"/> every one will be thrown down.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>As Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives, <lb n="1"/>
                        <lb n="2"/> the disciples came to him privately. <lb n="3"/> “Tell us,” they
                        said, “when will this happen, <lb n="4"/> and what will be the sign of your
                        coming and of the end of <lb n="5"/> the age?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus answered: <lb n="6"/> “Watch out that no one deceives you. <lb n="7"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>For many will come in my name, claiming, <lb n="8"/> 'I am the Messiah,' and
                        will deceive many. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>You will hear of wars and rumors <lb n="10"/> of wars, but see to it that you
                        are not alarmed. <lb n="11"/> Such things must happen, but the end is still
                        to come. <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom <lb n="13"/> against kingdom.
                        There will be famines and <lb n="14"/> earthquakes in various places.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>All these <lb n="15"/> are the beginning of birth pains.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then you will be handed over <lb n="16"/> to be persecuted and put to death,
                            <lb n="17"/> and you will be hated by all nations because <lb n="18"/>
                        of me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time many will turn away <lb n="19"/> from the faith and will betray
                        and hate <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="55v"/> each other,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>and many false prophets will appear <lb n="1"/> and deceive many people.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>Because <lb n="2"/> of the increase of wickedness, the love <lb n="3"/> of
                        most will grow cold,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>but the one who stands firm <lb n="4"/> to the end will be saved.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>And <lb n="5"/> this gospel of the kingdom will be preached in the whole
                        world <lb n="6"/> as a testimony to all nations, and <lb n="7"/> then the
                        end will come.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>“So when you see <lb n="8"/> standing in the holy place 'the abomination that
                        causes desolation,' <lb n="9"/> spoken of through the prophet Daniel <lb
                            n="10"/> -let the reader understand-</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains. <lb n="11"/>
                        <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>Let no one on the housetop go down to take <lb n="13"/> anything out of the
                        house.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Let no one in the field <lb n="14"/> go back to get their cloak. <lb n="15"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>How dreadful it will be in those days <lb n="16"/> for pregnant women and
                        nursing mothers!</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>Pray that <lb n="17"/> your flight will not take place in winter or on the
                        Sabbath. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>For then there will be great distress, <lb n="19"/> unequaled from the
                        beginning of the world until now-and never to be <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="56r"/> equaled again.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“If those days had not been cut short <lb n="1"/>, no one would survive, <lb
                            n="2"/> but for the sake of the elect <lb n="3"/> those days will be
                        shortened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time if anyone says to you, <lb n="4"/> 'Look, here is the Messiah!'
                        or, 'There he is!' do not believe it. <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>For false messiahs and false prophets will appear <lb n="6"/> and perform
                        great signs and <lb n="7"/> wonders to deceive, if possible, <lb n="8"/>
                        even the elect.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>See, I have told you ahead of time.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“So if anyone <lb n="9"/> tells you, 'There he is, out in the wilderness,' do
                        not <lb n="10"/> go out; or, 'Here he is, in the inner rooms,' do not <lb
                            n="11"/> believe it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>For as lightning that comes from the east <lb n="12"/> is visible even in the
                        west, so will be the coming <lb n="13"/> of the Son of Man.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>Wherever <lb n="14"/> there is a carcass, there the vultures will gather. <lb
                            n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>“Immediately after the distress <lb n="16"/> of those days “'the sun will be
                        darkened, <lb n="17"/> and the moon will not give its light; the stars <lb
                            n="18"/> will fall from the sky, and the heavenly bodies <lb n="19"/>
                        will be shaken.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then will appear the sign of <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="56v"/> the Son of Man in heaven. And then <lb n="1"/> all the peoples
                        of the earth will mourn when they see <lb n="2"/> the Son of Man coming on
                        the clouds of heaven, <lb n="3"/> with power and great glory.<lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>And he will send his angels with a loud <lb n="5"/> trumpet call, and they
                        will gather his elect from the four <lb n="6"/> winds, from one end of the
                        heavens <lb n="7"/> to the other.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>“Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: <lb n="8"/> As soon as its twigs
                        get <lb n="9"/> tender and its leaves come out, you know that <lb n="10"/>
                        summer is near.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Even so, when you see <lb n="11"/> all these things, you know that it is
                        near, <lb n="12"/> right at the door.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, <lb n="13"/> this generation will certainly not pass away
                        until all <lb n="14"/> these things have happened.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>Heaven and earth will pass away <lb n="15"/>, but my words will never pass
                            away.<lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>“But about that day or hour no one knows, <lb n="17"/> not even the angels in
                        heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>As it was in the days of Noah, so it will be at the coming of the Son of Man.
                            <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>For in the days before the flood, people were eating and drinking, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="57r"/> marrying and giving in marriage, <lb n="1"/> up to the day
                        Noah entered the ark; <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>and they knew nothing about what would happen until the flood came <lb n="3"
                        /> and took them all away. That is how it will be <lb n="4"/> at the coming
                        of the Son of Man.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>Two men <lb n="5"/> will be in the field; one will be taken and the other <lb
                            n="6"/> left.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>Two women will be grinding with a hand mill; one <lb n="7"/> will be taken
                        and the other left.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore keep watch <lb n="8"/>, because you do not know on what day your
                        Lord will come. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>But understand this: <lb n="10"/> If the owner of the house had known at what
                        time of night the thief was <lb n="11"/> coming, he would have kept watch
                        and would not have let <lb n="12"/> his house be broken into.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>So <lb n="13"/> you also must be ready, because the Son of Man will come at
                        an <lb n="14"/> hour when you do not expect him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>“Who then is the faithful and wise servant, <lb n="15"/> whom the master has
                        put in charge <lb n="16"/> of the servants in his household to give <lb
                            n="17"/> them their food at the proper time? <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>It will be good for that servant whose <lb n="19"/> master finds him doing so
                        when he returns.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="57v"/> I tell you, he will put him in <lb n="1"/> charge of all his
                        possessions.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>But suppose <lb n="2"/> hat servant is wicked and says to himself, <lb n="3"
                        /> 'My master is staying away a long time,'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>and he then begins <lb n="4"/> to beat his fellow servants and to eat <lb
                            n="5"/> and drink with drunkards.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>The master of that servant <lb n="6"/> will come on a day when he does not
                        expect him and at an hour <lb n="7"/> he is not aware of.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>He will cut him to pieces and assign <lb n="8"/> him a place with the
                        hypocrites, where there will be <lb n="9"/> weeping and gnashing of
                        teeth.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>“At that time <lb n="10"/> the kingdom of heaven will be like ten virgins <lb
                            n="11"/> who took their lamps and went out to meet <lb n="12"/> the
                        bridegroom.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>Five of them <lb n="13"/> were foolish and five were wise. <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>The foolish ones took their lamps <lb n="15"/> but did not take any oil with
                        them. <lb n="16"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>The wise ones, however, took oil in <lb n="17"/> jars along with their
                        lamps.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>The bridegroom was a long time <lb n="18"/> in coming, and they all became
                        drowsy <lb n="19"/> and fell asleep.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>“At midnight <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="58r"/> the cry rang out: 'Here's the bridegroom! <lb n="1"/> Come out
                        to meet him!'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then <lb n="2"/> all the virgins woke up and trimmed <lb n="3"/> their
                        lamps.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>The foolish ones <lb n="4"/> said to the wise, 'Give us some of your oil; <lb
                            n="5"/> our lamps are going out.' <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“'No,' they replied, <lb n="7"/> 'there may not be enough for both us <lb
                            n="8"/> and you. Instead, go to those who sell oil and <lb n="9"/> buy
                        some for yourselves.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>“But while they were on their way to buy the oil, <lb n="10"/> the bridegroom
                        arrived. The virgins who were ready went in <lb n="11"/> with him to the
                        wedding banquet. And the door was <lb n="12"/> shut.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>“Later the others also came. <lb n="13"/> 'Lord, Lord,' they said, 'open the
                        door for us!'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>“But he <lb n="14"/> replied, 'Truly I tell you, I don't <lb n="15"/> know
                        you.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>“Therefore keep watch, because you do not know <lb n="16"/> the day or the
                        hour.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>“Again, it will be like a man going on a journey <lb n="17"/>, who called his
                        servants and entrusted his <lb n="18"/> wealth to them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>To one he gave five bags <lb n="19"/> of gold, to another two bags, and to
                        another <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="58v"/> one bag, each according to his ability. <lb n="1"/> Then he
                        went on his journey.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>The man who had received five bags <lb n="2"/> of gold went at once and put
                        his money to work <lb n="3"/> and gained five bags more. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>So also, the one with two bags of gold gained <lb n="5"/> two more.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>But the man <lb n="6"/> who had received one bag went off, dug a hole in the
                        ground and hid <lb n="7"/> his master's money.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>“After a long <lb n="8"/> time the master of those servants <lb n="9"/>
                        returned and settled accounts with <lb n="10"/> them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>The man who had received five bags of gold <lb n="11"/> brought the other
                        five. 'Master,' <lb n="12"/> he said, 'you entrusted me <lb n="13"/> with
                        five bags of gold. See, I have gained five more.'<lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“His master replied, 'Well done, good <lb n="15"/> and faithful servant! You
                        have been <lb n="16"/> faithful with a few things; I will put you in charge
                        of many things. Come <lb n="17"/> and share your master's happiness!'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“The man with <lb n="18"/> two bags of gold also came. 'Master,' he said,
                        'you entrusted me with two bags of gold; <lb n="19"/> see, I have gained two
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="59r"/> more.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“His master replied, 'Well done, <lb n="1"/> good and faithful servant! You
                        have been faithful with a few <lb n="2"/> things; I will put you in charge
                        of many things. <lb n="3"/> Come and share your master's happiness!'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then <lb n="4"/> the man who had received one bag of gold came. <lb n="5"/>
                        'Master,' he said, 'I knew that you are a hard man, harvesting where you
                        have <lb n="6"/> not sown and gathering where you have not scattered seed.
                            <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>So I was afraid and went out and hid <lb n="8"/> your gold in the ground.
                        See, here is what belongs <lb n="9"/> to you.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>“His master replied, <lb n="10"/> 'You wicked, lazy servant! So you knew that
                        I harvest where I have not sown and <lb n="11"/> gather where I have not
                        scattered <lb n="12"/> seed?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Well then, you should have put <lb n="13"/> my money on deposit with the
                        bankers, so that when I returned <lb n="14"/> I would have received it back
                            <lb n="15"/> with interest.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>“'So take the bag of gold from him <lb n="16"/> and give it to the one who
                        has ten bags. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>For whoever has will be given more, and they will have <lb n="18"/> an
                        abundance. Whoever does not have, even <lb n="19"/> what they have will be
                        taken from them.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>And throw <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="59v"/> that worthless servant outside, into the darkness, where there
                        will be weeping <lb n="1"/> and gnashing of teeth.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>“When <lb n="2"/> the Son of Man comes in his glory, <lb n="3"/> and all the
                        angels with him, he will sit <lb n="4"/> on his glorious throne.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>All the nations <lb n="5"/> will be gathered before him, and he will separate
                            <lb n="6"/> the people one from another as a shepherd <lb n="7"/>
                        separates the sheep from the goats.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>He will put the sheep <lb n="8"/> on his right and the goats on his left. <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then the King will say to those on his right, <lb n="10"/> 'Come, you who
                        are blessed by my Father; take your inheritance, <lb n="11"/> the kingdom
                        prepared for you since the creation of <lb n="12"/> the world.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>For I was hungry and you gave <lb n="13"/> me something to eat, I was thirsty
                        and you gave <lb n="14"/> me something to drink, I was a stranger and you
                        invited me in,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>I needed clothes <lb n="15"/> and you clothed me, I was sick and you looked
                        after <lb n="16"/> me, I was in prison and you came to visit me.' <lb n="17"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then the righteous will answer him, <lb n="18"/> 'Lord, when did we see you
                        hungry <lb n="19"/> and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to <lb
                            n="20"/>
                        <pb n="60r"/> drink?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>When did we see you <lb n="1"/> a stranger and invite you in, or needing
                        clothes <lb n="2"/> and clothe you?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>When did we see <lb n="3"/> you sick or in prison and go to visit <lb n="4"/>
                        you?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>“The King will reply, <lb n="5"/> 'Truly I tell you, whatever you did for one
                        of the least of these brothers <lb n="6"/> and sisters of mine, you did for
                        me.' <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then he will say to those on his left, 'Depart <lb n="8"/> from me, you who
                        are cursed, into the eternal fire <lb n="9"/> prepared for the devil and his
                        angels. <lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>For I was hungry and you gave me <lb n="11"/> nothing to eat, I was thirsty
                        and you gave me nothing to drink, <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>I was a stranger and you did not invite me in, I needed clothes <lb n="13"/>
                        and you did not clothe me, I was sick <lb n="14"/> and in prison and you did
                        not look after me.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>“They also will answer, 'Lord, when <lb n="15"/>
                        <lb n="16"/> did we see you hungry or thirsty or <lb n="17"/> a stranger or
                        needing clothes or sick or <lb n="18"/> in prison, and did not help
                        you?'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="19"/> “He will reply, 'Truly I tell you, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="60v"/> whatever you did not do for one of the least of these <lb
                            n="1"/>, you did not do for me.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>“Then they will go away <lb n="2"/> to eternal punishment, but the righteous
                        to <lb n="3"/> eternal life. “</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>When Jesus had finished <lb n="4"/> saying all these things, he said to <lb
                            n="5"/> his disciples,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>“As you know, <lb n="6"/> the Passover is two days away-and the Son of Man
                        will be handed over <lb n="7"/> to be crucified.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the chief priests <lb n="8"/> and the elders of the people assembled in
                        the palace of <lb n="9"/> the high priest, whose name was <lb n="10"/>
                        Caiaphas,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>and they schemed to arrest <lb n="11"/> Jesus secretly and kill him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>“But not during <lb n="12"/> the festival,” they said, “or there may be a
                        riot among the people.” <lb n="13"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>While Jesus was in Bethany <lb n="14"/> in the home of Simon the Leper,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>a woman came to him <lb n="15"/> with an alabaster jar of very expensive
                        perfume <lb n="16"/>, which she poured on his head as he was reclining at
                        the table. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>When the disciples saw this, they were indignant. <lb n="18"/> ”Why this
                        waste?” they asked. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>“This perfume could have been sold at a high price <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="61r"/> and the money given to the poor.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Aware of this, <lb n="1"/> Jesus said to them, “Why are you bothering this
                        woman? She has done <lb n="2"/> a beautiful thing to me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="3"/> The poor you will always have with you, <lb n="4"/> but you will
                        not always have me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>When she poured this perfume on <lb n="5"/> my body, <lb n="6"/> she did it
                        to prepare me for burial. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Truly I tell you, wherever <lb n="8"/> this gospel is preached throughout <lb
                            n="9"/> the world, what she has done will also be told, in memory <lb
                            n="10"/> of her.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>Then one of the Twelve <lb n="11"/>-the one called Judas Iscariot -<lb n="12"
                        /> went to the chief priests</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>and asked, “What <lb n="13"/> are you willing to give me if I deliver him
                        over to you?” <lb n="14"/> So they counted out for him thirty pieces of
                        silver. <lb n="15"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>From then on Judas watched for an opportunity <lb n="16"/> to hand him
                        over.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>On the first <lb n="17"/> day of the Festival of Unleavened Bread, the
                        disciples came to <lb n="18"/> Jesus and asked, “Where do you want us to
                        make preparations for you to eat <lb n="19"/> the Passover?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>He replied, “Go into the city <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="61v"/> to a certain man and tell him, 'The Teacher says: My appointed
                        time <lb n="1"/> is near. I am going to celebrate the Passover <lb n="2"/>
                        with my disciples at your house.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>So the disciples <lb n="3"/> did as Jesus had directed them and prepared <lb
                            n="4"/> the Passover.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>When evening came, Jesus was reclining at the table with <lb n="5"/> the
                        Twelve. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>And while they were eating, he said, “Truly I tell <lb n="7"/> you, one of
                        you will betray me.” <lb n="8"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>They were very sad and began to say <lb n="9"/> to him one after the other,
                        “Surely you don't mean me, Lord?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, <lb n="10"/> “The one who has dipped <lb n="11"/> his hand
                        into the bowl with me will <lb n="12"/> betray me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>The Son of Man will go <lb n="13"/> just as it is written about him. But woe
                        to that man <lb n="14"/> who betrays the Son of Man! It would be better <lb
                            n="15"/> for him if he had not been born.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="16"/> Judas, the one who would betray him <lb n="17"/>, said,
                        “Surely you don't mean me, Rabbi?” <lb n="18"/> Jesus answered, “You have
                        said so.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>While they were eating, <lb n="19"/> Jesus took bread, and when he had given
                        thanks <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="62r"/>, he broke it and gave it to his disciples <lb n="1"/>, saying,
                        “Take and eat; this is <lb n="2"/> my body.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he took a cup, and when he had given thanks <lb n="3"/>, he gave it to
                        them, saying, “Drink from it, <lb n="4"/> all of you.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>This is my blood of the <lb n="5"/> covenant, which is poured out for many
                            <lb n="6"/> for the forgiveness of sins.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>I tell <lb n="7"/> you, I will not drink from this <lb n="8"/> fruit of the
                        vine from now on until that day <lb n="9"/> when I drink it new with you in
                            <lb n="10"/> my Father's kingdom.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had sung a hymn, they went <lb n="11"/> out to the Mount of
                        Olives.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus told <lb n="12"/> them, “This very night you will all fall away
                            <lb n="13"/> on account of me, for it is written: <lb n="14"/> “'I will
                        strike the shepherd, and <lb n="15"/> the sheep of the flock will be
                        scattered.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>But after I have risen, I will go ahead <lb n="16"/> of you into
                        Galilee.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>Peter replied, <lb n="17"/> “Even if all fall away <lb n="18"/> on account of
                        you, I never will.” <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>“Truly I tell you,” Jesus answered, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="62v"/> ”this very night, before the rooster crows, <lb n="1"/> you
                        will disown me three times.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>But Peter declared, “Even if <lb n="2"/> I have to die with you, I will never
                        disown you.” <lb n="3"/> And all the other disciples said the same. <lb
                            n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus went with his disciples to a place called <lb n="5"/> Gethsemane,
                        and he said to them, <lb n="6"/> “Sit here while I go over there and
                        pray.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>He took <lb n="7"/> Peter and the two sons of Zebedee along with him, <lb
                            n="8"/> and he began to be sorrowful and troubled.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he said <lb n="9"/> to them, “My soul is overwhelmed with sorrow to the
                        point of death. <lb n="10"/> Stay here and keep watch with me.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>Going a little farther <lb n="11"/>, he fell with his face to the ground and
                        prayed, <lb n="12"/> “My Father, if it is possible, may this <lb n="13"/>
                        cup be taken from me. Yet not as I will, <lb n="14"/> but as you will.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he returned to his disciples <lb n="15"/> and found them sleeping.
                        ”Couldn't you men keep watch <lb n="16"/> with me for one hour?” he asked
                        Peter. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>“Watch and pray so that you will not fall <lb n="18"/> into temptation. The
                        spirit is willing, <lb n="19"/> but the flesh is weak.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>He went away a second time <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="63r"/> and prayed, “My Father, <lb n="1"/> if it is not possible for
                        this cup to be taken away unless <lb n="2"/> I drink it, may your will be
                        done.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>When he came <lb n="3"/> back, he again found them sleeping, <lb n="4"/>
                        because their eyes were heavy.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>So he left them <lb n="5"/> and went away once more and prayed the third
                        time, <lb n="6"/> saying the same thing.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he returned to the disciples <lb n="7"/> and said to them, ”Are you
                        still sleeping and resting? <lb n="8"/> Look, the hour has come, and the Son
                            <lb n="9"/> of Man is delivered into the hands of sinners. <lb n="10"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>Rise! Let us go! Here comes <lb n="11"/> my betrayer!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>While he was still speaking <lb n="12"/>, Judas, one of the Twelve, arrived.
                        With <lb n="13"/> him was a large crowd armed with swords and clubs, <lb
                            n="14"/> sent from the chief priests and the elders of <lb n="15"/> the
                        people.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>Now the betrayer <lb n="16"/> had arranged a signal with them: <lb n="17"/>
                        “The one I kiss is the man; arrest him.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>Going <lb n="18"/> at once to Jesus, Judas said, “Greetings, Rabbi!” <lb
                            n="19"/> and kissed him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>Jesus replied, “Do what you came for, friend.” <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="63v"/> Then the men stepped forward, seized Jesus <lb n="1"/> and
                        arrested him. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>With that, one of Jesus' companions reached <lb n="3"/> for his sword, drew
                        it out and struck <lb n="4"/> the servant of the high priest, <lb n="5"/>
                        cutting off his ear.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>“Put <lb n="6"/> your sword back in its place,” Jesus said to him, <lb n="7"
                        /> “for all who draw the sword <lb n="8"/> will die by the sword.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="53" type="verse">
                    <p>Do you think <lb n="9"/> I cannot call on my Father, and <lb n="10"/> he will
                        at once put at my disposal more than twelve legions <lb n="11"/> of
                        angels?</p>
                </div>
                <div n="54" type="verse">
                    <p>But how then would <lb n="12"/> the Scriptures be fulfilled that say it must
                        happen in this way?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="55" type="verse">
                    <p>In that <lb n="13"/> hour Jesus said to the crowd, “Am I leading a rebellion,
                            <lb n="14"/> that you have come out with swords and clubs to capture <lb
                            n="15"/> me? Every day I sat in the temple courts <lb n="16"/> teaching,
                        and you did not arrest me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="56" type="verse">
                    <p>But this <lb n="17"/> has all taken place that <lb n="18"/> the writings of
                        the prophets might be fulfilled.” <lb n="19"/> Then all the disciples
                        deserted him and fled.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="57" type="verse">
                    <p>Those who had arrested <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="64r"/> Jesus took him to Caiaphas the high <lb n="1"/> priest, where
                        the teachers of the law and the elders <lb n="2"/> had assembled.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="58" type="verse">
                    <p>But Peter followed <lb n="3"/> him at a distance, right up to the courtyard
                        of the high <lb n="4"/> priest. He entered and <lb n="5"/> sat down with the
                        guards to see the outcome. <lb n="6"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="59" type="verse">
                    <p>The chief priests and <lb n="7"/> the whole Sanhedrin were looking for false
                            <lb n="8"/> evidence against Jesus so that they could put him to death.
                            <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="60" type="verse">
                    <p>But they did not find any, though <lb n="10"/> many false witnesses came
                        forward. Finally <lb n="11"/> two came forward</p>
                </div>
                <div n="61" type="verse">
                    <p>and <lb n="12"/> declared, “This fellow said, 'I am able to destroy <lb
                            n="13"/> the temple of God and rebuild it in three days.'” <lb n="14"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="62" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the high priest stood up <lb n="15"/> and said to Jesus, “Are you not
                        going to answer? What is this <lb n="16"/> testimony that these men are
                        bringing against you?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="63" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus <lb n="17"/> remained silent. The high priest said to him, <lb
                            n="18"/> “I charge you under oath by the living God: Tell <lb n="19"/>
                        us if you are the Messiah, the Son of God.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="64" type="verse">
                    <p>“You have said so,” Jesus <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="64v"/> replied. “But I say to all of you: <lb n="1"/> From now on you
                        will see the Son of Man sitting <lb n="2"/> at the right hand of the Mighty
                        One and coming <lb n="3"/> on the clouds of heaven.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="65" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the high <lb n="4"/> priest tore his clothes and said, <lb n="5"/> “He
                        has spoken blasphemy! Why do <lb n="6"/> we need any more witnesses? Look,
                        now you have heard <lb n="7"/> the blasphemy.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="66" type="verse">
                    <p>What do you think?” <lb n="8"/> “He is worthy of death,” they answered. <lb
                            n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="67" type="verse">
                    <p>Then they spit in his face and struck <lb n="10"/> him with their fists. <lb
                            n="11"/> Others slapped him</p>
                </div>
                <div n="68" type="verse">
                    <p>and said, “Prophesy <lb n="12"/> to us, Messiah. Who hit you?” <lb n="13"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="69" type="verse">
                    <p>Now Peter was sitting out in the courtyard, <lb n="14"/> and a servant girl
                        came to him. <lb n="15"/> “You also were with Jesus of Galilee,” she
                        said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="70" type="verse">
                    <p>But he denied <lb n="16"/> it before them all. “I don't know what you're
                        talking about,” <lb n="17"/> he said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="71" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he went out to the gateway, where another servant girl saw <lb n="18"/>
                        him and said to the people there, “This fellow <lb n="19"/> was with Jesus
                        of Nazareth.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="72" type="verse">
                    <p>He denied it again, <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="65r"/> with an oath: “I don't know <lb n="1"/> the man!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="73" type="verse">
                    <p>After a little while, <lb n="2"/> those standing there went up to Peter <lb
                            n="3"/> and said, “Surely you are one of them; your <lb n="4"/> accent
                        gives you away.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="74" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he began to call down curses, <lb n="5"/> and he swore to them, ”I don't
                        know <lb n="6"/> the man!” Immediately a rooster crowed. <lb n="7"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="75" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Peter remembered the word Jesus had <lb n="8"/> spoken: “Before the
                        rooster crows, you <lb n="9"/> will disown me three times.” And he went
                        outside and wept bitterly.<lb n="10"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>Early in the morning, <lb n="11"/> all the chief priests <lb n="12"/> and the
                        elders of the people made their plans how to have Jesus <lb n="13"/>
                        executed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>So they bound <lb n="14"/> him, led him away and handed him over to Pilate
                            <lb n="15"/> the governor.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>When Judas, who had betrayed him <lb n="16"/>, saw that Jesus was condemned,
                        he was seized with remorse <lb n="17"/> and returned the thirty pieces of
                        silver to <lb n="18"/> the chief priests and the elders. <lb n="19"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>“I have sinned,” he said, “for I have betrayed innocent <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="65v"/> blood.” “What is that to us?” they replied. <lb n="1"/>
                        “That's your responsibility.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>So Judas threw the money into the temple and left. <lb n="2"/> Then he went
                        away and hanged himself.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>The chief priests <lb n="3"/> picked up the coins and said, ”It is against
                            <lb n="4"/> the law to put this into the treasury, since it <lb n="5"/>
                        is blood money.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>So they decided to use <lb n="6"/> the money to buy the potter's field as a
                        burial place <lb n="7"/> for foreigners.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>That is <lb n="8"/> why it has been called <lb n="9"/> the Field of Blood to
                        this <lb n="10"/> day.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p>Then what was spoken <lb n="11"/> by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled: <lb
                            n="12"/> “They took the thirty pieces of silver, <lb n="13"/> the price
                        set on him <lb n="14"/> by the people of Israel,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>and they used them to buy the potter's field <lb n="15"/>, as the Lord
                        commanded me.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>Meanwhile Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, <lb
                            n="16"/>
                        <lb n="17"/> “Are you <lb n="18"/> the king of the Jews?” “You have said
                        so,” Jesus replied.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="19"/> he was accused by the chief priests <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="66r"/> and the elders, he gave no answer.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>Then <lb n="1"/> Pilate asked him, “Don't you hear the testimony <lb n="2"/>
                        they are bringing against you?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>But Jesus made no reply <lb n="3"/>, not even to a single charge-to the great
                            <lb n="4"/> amazement of the governor.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>Now <lb n="5"/> it was the governor's custom at <lb n="6"/> the festival to
                        release a prisoner <lb n="7"/> chosen by the crowd.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>At that time they had <lb n="8"/> a well-known prisoner <lb n="9"/> whose
                        name was Jesus Barabbas.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>So when the crowd <lb n="10"/> had gathered, Pilate asked them, “Which one do
                        you want me to release <lb n="11"/> to you: Jesus Barabbas, or Jesus who is
                        called <lb n="12"/> the Messiah?”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>For he knew it was out of self-interest that <lb n="13"/> they had handed
                        Jesus over to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>While Pilate was sitting on the judge's seat <lb n="14"/>, his wife sent him
                        this message: <lb n="15"/> “Don't have anything to do with that innocent
                        man, for <lb n="16"/> I have suffered a great deal today in a dream because
                        of him.” <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>But the chief priests and the elders <lb n="18"/> persuaded the crowd to ask
                        for Barabbas <lb n="19"/> and to have Jesus executed.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="verse">
                    <p>“Which <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="66v"/> of the two do you want me to release <lb n="1"/> to you?”
                        asked the governor. “Barabbas,” they answered. <lb n="2"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="verse">
                    <p>“What shall I do, then, with <lb n="3"/> Jesus who is called the Messiah?”
                        Pilate asked. They all answered <lb n="4"/>, “Crucify him!” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="verse">
                    <p>“Why? What crime has he committed?” asked Pilate. But they <lb n="6"/>
                        shouted all the louder, “Crucify him!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="verse">
                    <p>When <lb n="7"/> Pilate saw that he was getting nowhere, but <lb n="8"/> that
                        instead an uproar was starting, he took water <lb n="9"/> and washed his
                        hands in front of the crowd. “I am innocent <lb n="10"/> of this man's
                        blood,” he said. ”It is your responsibility!” <lb n="11"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="verse">
                    <p>All the people answered, <lb n="12"/> “His blood is on us and on <lb n="13"/>
                        our children!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="verse">
                    <p>Then he released Barabbas <lb n="14"/> to them. But he had Jesus flogged, and
                        handed him over <lb n="15"/> to be crucified.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the governor's soldiers <lb n="16"/> took Jesus into the Praetorium and
                            <lb n="17"/> gathered the whole company of soldiers around him. <lb
                            n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="verse">
                    <p>They stripped him and put a scarlet robe <lb n="19"/> on him,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="verse">
                    <p>and then twisted together a crown <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="67r"/> of thorns and set it on <lb n="1"/> his head. They put a staff
                        in his right hand. <lb n="2"/> Then they knelt in front of him and mocked
                        him. <lb n="3"/> “Hail, king of the Jews!” they said.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="verse">
                    <p>They spit on him, and took the staff <lb n="4"/>
                        <lb n="5"/> and struck him on the head again and again.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="verse">
                    <p>After <lb n="6"/> they had mocked him, they took off the robe <lb n="7"/> and
                        put his own clothes on him. Then they led <lb n="8"/> him away to crucify
                        him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="verse">
                    <p>As they were going out <lb n="9"/>, they met a man from Cyrene, <lb n="10"/>
                        named Simon, <lb n="11"/> and they forced him to carry the cross. <lb n="12"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="verse">
                    <p>They came to a place called <lb n="13"/> Golgotha (which means “the place of
                        the skull”). <lb n="14"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="verse">
                    <p>There they offered Jesus wine to drink <lb n="15"/>, mixed with gall; but
                        after tasting it, he refused <lb n="16"/> to drink it.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="verse">
                    <p>When they had crucified <lb n="17"/> him, they divided up his clothes by <lb
                            n="18"/> casting lots.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="verse">
                    <p>And sitting down, they kept watch over <lb n="19"/> him there.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="verse">
                    <p>Above his head they placed the written charge against him <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="67v"/>: THIS IS JESUS, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="1"/> Two rebels were crucified with him, one on his <lb n="2"/> right
                        and one on his left.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="verse">
                    <p>Those who passed <lb n="3"/> by hurled insults at him, <lb n="4"/> shaking
                        their heads</p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="verse">
                    <p>and saying, “You who <lb n="5"/> are going to destroy the temple and build it
                        in three days <lb n="6"/>, save yourself! Come down from the cross, if you
                        are the Son <lb n="7"/> of God!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="41" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way the chief <lb n="8"/> priests, the teachers of the law <lb
                            n="9"/> and the elders mocked him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="verse">
                    <p>“He saved others,” <lb n="10"/> they said, “but he can't save himself! <lb
                            n="11"/> He's the king of Israel! Let him come down <lb n="12"/> now
                        from the cross, and we will believe in him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="verse">
                    <p>He trusts <lb n="13"/> in God. Let God rescue him now if he wants him, <lb
                            n="14"/> for he said, 'I am the Son of God.'”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="verse">
                    <p>In the same way <lb n="15"/> the rebels who were crucified <lb n="16"/> with
                        him also heaped insults on him. <lb n="17"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="45" type="verse">
                    <p>From noon until three in the afternoon darkness <lb n="18"/> came over all
                            <lb n="19"/> the land.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="46" type="verse">
                    <p>About <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="68r"/> three in the afternoon Jesus cried out in <lb n="1"/> a loud
                        voice, “Eli, Eli, lema sabachthani?” <lb n="2"/> (which means “My God, my
                        God, why have you forsaken me?”). <lb n="3"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="47" type="verse">
                    <p>When some of those standing <lb n="4"/> there heard this, they said, ”He's
                        calling Elijah.” <lb n="5"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="48" type="verse">
                    <p>Immediately one of them ran and got <lb n="6"/> a sponge. He filled it with
                        wine vinegar, put it <lb n="7"/> on a staff, and offered it to Jesus to
                        drink.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="49" type="verse">
                    <p>The rest <lb n="8"/> said, “Now leave him alone. <lb n="9"/> Let's see if
                        Elijah comes to save him.” <note place="margin" type="gloss"> A portion of
                            this verse is found in the Latin Vulgate and not the NIV
                            translation.</note><lb n="10"/>
                        <lb n="11"/>
                        <lb n="12"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="50" type="verse">
                    <p>And when Jesus had cried out again in a loud voice, <lb n="13"/> he gave up
                        his spirit.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="51" type="verse">
                    <p>At that moment the curtain of the temple <lb n="14"/> was torn in two from
                        top to bottom. <lb n="15"/> The earth shook, the rocks <lb n="16"/>
                        split</p>
                </div>
                <div n="52" type="verse">
                    <p>and the tombs broke open. The bodies of <lb n="17"/> many holy people who had
                        died were raised to life. <lb n="18"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="53" type="verse">
                    <p>They came out of the tombs <lb n="19"/> after Jesus' resurrection and went
                            <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="68v"/> into the holy city and appeared to <lb n="1"/> many
                        people.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="54" type="verse">
                    <p>When the centurion and those with him <lb n="2"/> who were guarding Jesus saw
                        the earthquake and all that had <lb n="3"/> happened, they were terrified,
                        and exclaimed, <lb n="4"/> “Surely he was the Son of God!”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="55" type="verse">
                    <p>Many women were there, <lb n="5"/> watching from a distance. <lb n="6"/> They
                        had followed Jesus from Galilee to care for his needs.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="56" type="verse">
                    <p>Among <lb n="7"/> them were Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother <lb n="8"/> of
                        James and Joseph, and the mother of Zebedee's sons. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="57" type="verse">
                    <p>As evening approached, there came <lb n="10"/> a rich man from Arimathea,
                        named <lb n="11"/> Joseph, who had himself become a disciple of Jesus.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="58" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="12"/> Going to Pilate, he asked for Jesus' <lb n="13"/> body, and
                        Pilate ordered that it be given to him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="59" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="14"/> Joseph took the body, wrapped it in a clean <lb n="15"/> linen
                        cloth,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="60" type="verse">
                    <p>and placed it in his own new tomb <lb n="16"/> that he had cut out of the
                        rock. <lb n="17"/> He rolled a big stone in front of the entrance <lb n="18"
                        /> to the tomb and went away.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="61" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="19"/> Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="69r"/> sitting there opposite the tomb.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="62" type="verse">
                    <p>The next day <lb n="1"/>, the one after Preparation Day, <lb n="2"/> the
                        chief priests and the Pharisees <lb n="3"/> went to Pilate.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="63" type="verse">
                    <p>“Sir,” they said, “we remember <lb n="4"/> that while he was still <lb n="5"
                        /> alive that deceiver said, 'After three days I will rise again.' <lb n="6"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="64" type="verse">
                    <p>So give the order for the tomb to be made secure <lb n="7"/> until the third
                        day. Otherwise, his disciples may come <lb n="8"/> and steal the body and
                        tell the people that he has been raised <lb n="9"/> from the dead. This last
                        deception will be <lb n="10"/> worse than the first.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="65" type="verse">
                    <p>“Take a guard,” Pilate answered. <lb n="11"/> “Go, make the tomb as secure as
                        you know how.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="66" type="verse">
                    <p>So they <lb n="12"/> went and made the tomb secure by putting a seal on the
                        stone <lb n="13"/> and posting the guard.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
                <div n="1" type="verse">
                    <p>After the Sabbath, at dawn <lb n="14"/> on the first day <lb n="15"/> of the
                        week, Mary Magdalene and the other <lb n="16"/> Mary went to look at the
                        tomb.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="verse">
                    <p>There was <lb n="17"/> a violent earthquake, for an angel <lb n="18"/> of the
                        Lord came down from heaven and, going to the tomb, <lb n="19"/> rolled back
                        the stone and sat on it. <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="69v"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="3" type="verse">
                    <p>His appearance was like lightning, <lb n="1"/> and his clothes were white as
                            <lb n="2"/> snow.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="verse">
                    <p>The guards were so afraid of him that <lb n="3"/> they shook and became like
                        dead men. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="verse">
                    <p>The angel said to <lb n="5"/> the women, “Do not be afraid, for I know <lb
                            n="6"/> that you are looking for Jesus, who was crucified. <lb n="7"
                        /></p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="verse">
                    <p>He is not here; he has risen, just as he said. <lb n="8"/> Come and see the
                        place where he lay. <lb n="9"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="verse">
                    <p>Then go quickly and tell his disciples: <lb n="10"/> 'He has risen from the
                        dead and is going <lb n="11"/> ahead of you into Galilee. There you will see
                        him.' <lb n="12"/> Now I have told you.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="verse">
                    <p>So the women hurried away from the tomb, <lb n="13"/> afraid yet filled with
                        joy, <lb n="14"/> and ran to tell his disciples.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="verse">
                    <p><lb n="15"/> Suddenly Jesus met them. “Greetings,” he said. <lb n="16"/> They
                        came to him, clasped his feet <lb n="17"/> and worshiped him.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus said to them, <lb n="18"/> “Do not be afraid. Go and tell <lb
                            n="19"/> my brothers to go to Galilee; <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="70r"/> there they will see me.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="verse">
                    <p>While the women were on their way, <lb n="1"/> some of the guards went into
                        the city <lb n="2"/> and reported to the chief priests <lb n="3"/>
                        everything that had happened. <lb n="4"/></p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="verse">
                    <p>When the chief priests had met with the elders <lb n="5"/> and devised a
                        plan, <lb n="6"/> they gave the soldiers a large sum of money,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="13" type="verse">
                    <p>telling them, “You are to say, 'His disciples <lb n="7"/> came during the
                        night and stole him away <lb n="8"/> while we were asleep.'</p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="verse">
                    <p>If this report gets to <lb n="9"/> the governor, we will satisfy him and keep
                            <lb n="10"/> you out of trouble.”</p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="verse">
                    <p>So the soldiers took the money <lb n="11"/> and did as they were instructed.
                        And this story <lb n="12"/> has been widely circulated among the Jews to <lb
                            n="13"/> this very day.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="verse">
                    <p>Then the eleven disciples went <lb n="14"/> to Galilee, <lb n="15"/> to the
                        mountain where Jesus had told them to go.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="verse">
                    <p>When they saw <lb n="16"/> him, they worshiped him; but some <lb n="17"/>
                        doubted.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="verse">
                    <p>Then Jesus came to them <lb n="18"/> and said, “All authority <lb n="19"/> in
                        heaven and on earth has been given to me.</p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="verse">
                    <p>Therefore go and make disciples of <lb n="20"/>
                        <pb n="70v"/> all nations, baptizing <lb n="1"/> them in the name of the
                        Father and of the Son <lb n="2"/> and of the Holy Spirit,</p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="verse">
                    <p>and teaching them to obey <lb n="3"/> everything <lb n="4"/> I have commanded
                        you. And surely I <lb n="5"/> am with you always, <lb n="6"/> to the very
                        end <lb n="7"/> of the age.” <lb n="8"/>
                        <pb n="71r"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
